<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here begynnethe the lanterne of lyght</title>
            <title>Lanterne of lyght.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1535</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 231 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15225</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108268</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843937</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843937</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8704</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05083)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8704)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 103:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here begynnethe the lanterne of lyght</title>
                  <title>Lanterne of lyght.</title>
                  <author>Grime, John, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Hardy, William, fl. 1535, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>lxxiii, [1] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Fletestrete, by me Robert Redman, dwellyng at the sygne of the George, nexte to Saynt Dunstones church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1535?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Grime and to William Hardy.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and address from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Antichrist --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8704:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8704:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnethe the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of lyght. <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8704:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="ii" facs="tcp:8704:2"/>
            <head>☞ Take here of our gracious lorde god this lytle treatice that here is offred / called the Lanterne of lyght conteynynge. xiij. chapyters.</head>
            <div type="prologue">
               <head>Fyrſt a Prologe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Od that is good hym</hi> ſelfe / fayre in his Angels mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uelous in his ſainctes / merciful apon ſynners / haue mercy on vs nowe and euer / and gyue vs grace to holde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way of trought in theſe dayes of great tribulacyon for now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that ſemed to be ſtable in vertue fallen from theyr holy purpoſe dreding loſſe &amp; bodely paine:<note place="margin">Mat. 24. Quoniam habundauit iniquitas refrigeſcit caritas mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torum.</note> as Chryſt ſayd That thabu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of wyckednes ſhall coole the charite of many / for Sathan hath nowe deſtroyed thys worlde by hys leue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunt Antechryſt / that men be borne aboute in diuers doubtes as waues of the ſee / wredchy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dly diuided in diuers opinions one agaynſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But ſeynt Paule dyd ſette one accorde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge the chiſten people ſaynge / ther is but one Lorde that all men ſhulde loue and dred / one faythe that all men ſhulde kepe and byleue with out varyenge / <note place="margin">Ephe. 4. Vnus dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: vna fides &amp; vnum bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſma. &amp;c.</note> and one Baptyme that all men ſhuld haue &amp; ſtedfaſtly holde without defouling. Alas howe is this vnyte broken that men vnru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led walken after their luſtes as beſtes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corne: truly the wycked man that Chriſt ſpake of hath
<pb facs="tcp:8704:3"/>
done thys dede for he hath ſowen faves &amp; cokle vpon the ſede of god.<note place="margin">Math. 13. Inimicus homo ſuper ſeminauit zi zannia.</note> Thys wycked enemye is Antechriſte / that cloutyth hys lawes as rotten Ragges to the clene cloth of Chriſtes goſpell. And waketh in malice as Iudas chylde / why for Simon ſlepith and taketh non hede. O thou wycked man is there any othere man that may ſaue ſoulles than Ieſu Chryſt / god ſaid by the mouthe of Moyſes I ſhall ſmyte / and I ſhall hele and there is none that can delyuer or rydde from my hande / <note place="margin">☞Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipſis. 1.</note> who hathe the keyes of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid to open heuen gates / and none othere clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyth / to cloſe / and then none othere openeth / ſayncte Iohn ſayeth holy and true Chriſte hath the keye of Dauid that openeth / whiche caſtith downe / and than no man reyſeth / who reyſeth and than no man caſtyth downe. Iob ſayeth / whan the Lorde god hathe dyſtroyed there may none other buylde / <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Iob.</note> &amp; when the Lord god caſtyth in pryſon ther may none other delyuer or quyte hym of his bondes. And therfore in the vertue of this name Ieſu / ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth al ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſaluation / as it is wrytten in thactes of thapoſteles.<note place="margin">Actuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 4.</note> ſeynct Peter ſayde. There is none othere name vnder heuen geuen / but thys name Ieſu / whereof we may ſaued be / for alonely in the vertue of thys name Ieſu is the remyſſyon of ſynnes / as it is wrytten / Luce .xxiiij. It behoued to be prechyd amonge the people / penaunce &amp; remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſynnes in the name of Ieſu art thou nat then a wycked man / a folyſhe-herde / a cruell beſte / the ſon of perdicion And Antechriſt hym
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:8704:3"/>
ſelfe that pretendeſt in the / &amp; in thy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers / to bleſſe &amp; to curſſe to bynde &amp; to vnbynde beſydes this name Ieſu / people w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre folowynge the &amp; thy deuyded lawes ben deuided fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſte Ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and go with the blyndefolde into hell for euermore and thys is great ſorowe / ſo ferforth that Chryſt maketh lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tacyon and mournyng ther vpon ſaynge / Iohi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. v.<note place="margin">Tu es qui ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>turns est an alium ex pectamus.</note> I haue come in the name of my father and ye haue not taken me when another ſhall come in hys owne name him ſhall ye take / and thys is Antechryſte. And ſeyncte Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Criſoſtome / vpon theſe wordes of the goſpel / Mathei. xxj.<note place="margin">Lucerna pe dibꝪ meis verbum tull domine.</note> For who that wyll not receyue Chriſt in payne of ſynne he is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led &amp; conſtrayned to receyue Antechriſt / and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore in this tyme of tribulacion &amp; hydeous darke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / let vs ſeke the Lanterne of lyght wherof the prophet ſpekith. Lord thy worde is a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne to my fete / <note place="margin">Neque ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba neque malagina ſa nauit illos / <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:absed"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>sed</ex>
                     </expan> omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens ſermo tuus qui ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat omnia.</note> for as fer as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light of this La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terne ſhyneth / ſo far darknes of ſyn &amp; cloudes of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacyon of the fende vanyſſheth away &amp; may not abyde. And euermore when thys Lanterne lighteneth into an herte / it purgyth it &amp; cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſith it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corrupcion / it ſwagyth &amp; healyth goſtely ſores / as the wyſema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth / that nether herbe nor plaſter hathe heled them / but Lorde thy myghty worde that heleth al thynges. For tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lord whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou dyed apon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe thou dydeſt put in thy worde the ſpryt of lyfe / <note place="margin">Verba que ego locutus ſum ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s et vita ſmit.</note> &amp; gaueſt to it power of quickenyng by thyne owne precious bloud / as thou ſaid thy ſelf. Io. vj. The wordes that I ſpake to you / bene ſpryte and lyfe. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb facs="tcp:8704:4"/>
               <head>¶ A peticion of thauctor.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iacobi. 2. Multu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let depreca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio iuſti aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidua.</note>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ere Brother in Chriſt</hi> helpe me with your prayer to almighty god: for ſeinct Iames ſaith The buſy praier of a right wyſe man is moche worthe. Ye haue deſyered me to take thys trauayle apon me / whiche is full chargeous to me / but as towarde our ſwete Lorde god no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge is impoſſyble as Chryſte ſayde and in thys fayth.<note place="margin">Math. 19. Marci. 10. Luce. 18. Iſaye. 18. Deus ipſe ola opera operat in no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bis.</note> Yſaye ſayde. The Lorde god hym ſelfe wyrcheth all our workes in vs / fayle we not then god in good leui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. And he may not faile to geue vs ſuche wyſdom / as is nedefull to vs &amp; to tempre our tonge / &amp; gyue vs true organ / &amp; redy ſpeche / in edefyeng of our neyghbour / for without the helpe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite of god our labour were but loſt / as Chriſt ſaid / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was not we y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> coulde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeke profitably / but the ſpirite of the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpeketh in vs / for thapoſtels &amp; other holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / <note place="margin">Math. 18. Non enim vos eſtis qui loqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:absed"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>sed</ex>
                     </expan> ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s veſtri quiloquitur in vobis.</note> that trauayled in dedly letters / meked the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes as ſimple ydiottes: as Hierom ſayd / that prechers vnlerned bene ſent for to preche / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the faith of the true beleuers ſhuld be trowed to be brought in (not by ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes vertue) but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpech &amp; doctrine of god. And ſeynt Auſten wryting vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to Simplician ſayth. what ſuffren we / what here we / vnlerned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ariſen &amp; catche heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And we with our clergi ben dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched in hel. And ſeinct Gregory in his Moralles affirmith this ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb n="iiii" facs="tcp:8704:4"/>
and ſayth. Ryght as trough incarnate / that is Chriſt in manhede choſith ſimple poore ydiottes to hys prechynge ſo agaynwarde Antechriſte is for to chaſe ſtourdy and doble men hauynge the wyſdom of thys worlde for to preche his falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hede. Haue we then ful faythe in our lorde Ieſu with perfyte lyuynge and this Lorde throughe your prayer ſhal lead this warke after his owne pleaſure / and brynge it to a perfyte ende to hys honour and glory / and to profyte &amp; edificacyon of his faythefull ſeruauntes. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Capitulum tertium. ¶ What Antecriſt is in general with .vi. condycions.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O ſpeake generally yf</hi> ye demaunde me who is Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt I aunſwere and ſay that he (whoſe lyfe and doctryne is contrary to Chriſtes:<note place="margin">Iohi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. 2. Nunc aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſunt multi antechriſti.</note> is an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techriſt / as ſeyncte Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaid / forſothe nowe bene many Antecriſtes. And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſayth ſeynct Auſten. who that lyueth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Chryſt) is an Antechriſt / be thou with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in or be thou without / be thou high / or be thou lowe / be thou ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all (as they call it) or be thou temporal / be thou riche or poore / Pope or page or of any degree thou canſt rekene / yf thou lyue contrary to Chriſt / thou art but chafe wherof Chriſte ſpeketh ſayeng that the chafe ſhal brine with fyer that may not be quenched.<note place="margin">Maih. 3.</note> And the
<pb facs="tcp:8704:5"/>
ſoull that is but chafe ſhall euer ſuffre and neuer bye / as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophete ſayth. Yſa. ix. Euery proude ſoule that ryſeth in ſwellynge agaynſt god / <note place="margin">Yſaye. 9.</note> and euery body defouled in Glottony &amp; Lechery ſhal be into ſwellynge &amp; mete of the fyre that ſhall euer brenne him with moſt greuous payne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sex peta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> contra ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note>Six ſynnes there be agaynſt the holy goſte that toke the wretched ſoull in to thys chafe / but for aſmoche as no daunger is feared but it be fyrſte knowen / therfore we ſhall name them vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to you in thys lytle treatice for the lernynge of the ſmall vnderſtanders.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio. 1.</note>The fyrſte is preſumpcyon / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is the bolnynge or ſwellynge of a proude ſpirite without dred of godes ryghtwyſnes / and of thys ſynne all maner of malyce and wretchydnes taketh rote that reygneth in mankynde amonge lerned and leude / <note place="margin">Qui non ti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>met non po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terit iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtica. 15.</note> for the wyſeman ſayth / that he that dredeth not can not be iuſtyfyed or made ryght<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe. For ſothe I ſaye in whome thys ſynne of preſumption hath no lordeſhyp in hym the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll is ouercome for he that dredeth the lorde ſhall do good thynges and agayne but yf thou holde thy ſelfe continually in the drede of god thy houſe ſhalbe ſone tourned vpſydowne / <note place="margin">Ibide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 27.</note> that is thy body and ſoull ſhalbe tourned from god into the deuelles ſeruyce.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Diſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. 2.</note>The ſeconde ſyn is Dyſperacyon or wanhope / that is ouer lytle truſt of godes mercy. Seynct Auſtyne ſaythe that the drede of godes ryght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſnes / and hope of hys mercy bene .ij. yates of lyfe / for by them we entren here into grace
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:8704:5"/>
and after into blyſſe / as the prophete ſaythe. Our Lorde is wel pleaſed apon them that drede hym / &amp; that truſt in his mercy / and againwarde preſumpcion &amp; diſperacion bene .ij. yates of deth by the which me entren into ſinne &amp; inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance / &amp; after into payne of hel.<note place="margin">Iohi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. 2.</note> Seyncte Iohan geueth vs lore agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt this ſyn &amp; ſayth. My litle ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes / theſe thynges I wryte to you / that ye ſynne not in the ſynne of dyſpayre / but yf it ſo be that any of you haue ſynned we haue an aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate agaynſte the father Ieſu Chryſte our iuſt Lorde / and he is the purchaſer of mercy for our ſynnes / not only for ours / but for the ſynnes of all the worlde. Ieſu / is for to ſay a ſauyour for he hathe plenty of medecyne to ſaue al man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde / yf they wyll take thys medecyne and be ſaufe.<note place="margin">Gregorius</note> For ſeyncte Gregory ſaythe He ſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yth him ſelfe that wyll not kepe the byddynges of hys leche.</p>
               <p>The thyrde ſyn is Obſtinacy or hardnes of hert that wyl not be contrite for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>punction / nor ſofte with pyte / nor moued with prayer / nor feared w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thretteni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges / it ſettith not by betinges but vnkynde agaynſte all the workes of God / vnfaythefull in councell / ferſe and woode in Iugement / vnſhamefaſt in ſynne / hardy in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yll a Cowarde in manhode / folehardy agaynſte god / forgetfull of tyme paſte neclygente in tyme preſente and inprouydente for the tyme to come and ſhortely to ſaye / <note place="margin">Bernardus 5. de. 9. Linco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ln<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 190.</note> thys is the ſynne that neyther dredyth god / ne ſhameth man / for thys ſynne one Lynconln<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teacheth a mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyne
<pb facs="tcp:8704:6"/>
ſayenge / that an harde hert wolde be bray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a morter of ſtone with an heuy peſtle: thys morter is the bodye of Chryſte penetrate / and wounded in hys paſſyon / the peſtle is the drede of dampnacyon / that foloweth after the ſynne. O thou harde harted wretche / nygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the to the bodye of Chryſte / and for drede of dampnacyon confyrme the to hys paſſyon. &amp;c. The .iiij. ſynne is fynall Impenitence / that is he that wyll neuer be penitent or ſorowfull for hys ſynne / but contynually leadeth hys lyfe after the luſtes of hys fleſhe / ouercommen with the deuell / the worlde and the fleſhe / for no man dothe very penaunce to god / but he that fully leuyth that ſyn / for the whiche he ſuffreth penaunce / thus ſayth Sayncte Auſtyn / but for they holden moche worſhyp to blaſe theyr name in erth they maken a fayned ſhryfte to a pryſte &amp; taken parte of ſacramentes they buylde chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches with other ornamentes / and fynde pryſtes to rede and ſynge / they releuen the poore ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy / <note place="margin">Math. 6. No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ala plus eſt <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>quam</ex>
                     </expan> eſca &amp; corpꝰ pluſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> veſtimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> and amenden places that be peryllous / but euer more they lye harde tongeled as froſte / in olde cuſtome and ſynne. To theſe vnrepenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or impenitent perſones ſpeketh Gregory / moſt ſharpely in hys Paſtoralles vpon Mathewe / whether is not the lyfe more then mete / and the body more than cloth / here thys doctour ſayth. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> geueth mete or clothe to the poore nedy and is polluted or defouled in wyckednes of bodye and ſoule / the thynge that is moſte he geueth to ſynne / and the thynge that is lefte
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:8704:6"/>
he geueth to ryghtwyſnes / hys goodes he ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to god / but hym ſelfe to the deuel / for he ſettyth more pryce by worldly rycheſſe then he dothe by bodye and ſoull / and loueth moſte that god loueth leſte / wherfore he is tourned to hate: god hathe gyuen vnto man .v. precyous gyftes / the leſte of them is wordly goodes / better then theſe is mannes bodye that god hathe endowed with kyndely ſtrength and graunted hym rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to vſe / thys worlde hym ſelfe to chaſtyce clothe or fede / aboue theſe twayne is mannes ſoull that berythe godes image and hys lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Lorde what proffyt were it to wyn thys worlde / and brynge thy ſoull vnto dampna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / and the body is a lotheſume careyn when the ſoule is departed therfrom. But godes grace paſſeth theſe .iij. for where hys grace fayleth / no wyſdome auayleth. Loke well that theſe thynges be not myſpente / nether worke thou any of them beſydes theyr ordre / but that the ſtreynght all to one ende to wyn vnto the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe and gyfte of god that is the bleſſe perdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.<note place="margin">Romanos. 1 An dinitias bonitatis, &amp;c.</note> But howe thou tourneſt thys ordre vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydowne. Seynte Poule aſketh a queſtyon of the. whether dyſpiſeſt thou the ryches of the goodnes of god and patience / and longe aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of thy god. Knoweſt thou nat that the good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of god ledyth the or dryuith the to penaunce truly after thyne hardnes and thyne vnrepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunt herte / thou treaſoureſt to the wrathe in the daye of wrathe / and reuelacyon of the ryght<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe iugement of god / that ſhall yelde to eche
<pb facs="tcp:8704:7"/>
man after hys workes.</p>
               <p>The .v. ſynne is Enuy agaynſte thy brothers grace as when thy neyghbour is wyſe well go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned / prayſed or borne vp / ryche welthy ſtronge / fayre or vertuous in great abundaunce of grace / then thys enuyous man ſklaundreth / vpbreydeth / repreueth / diſpyſeth / hatith / hin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dreth / ſcorneth &amp; purſueth / to defoule his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers grace / <note place="margin">Prouerbio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum. 14.</note> as moche as he may / as the wyſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth. A man walkynge in the hygh waye and dredynge the Lorde / is dyſpyſed of hym that walketh in the wronge way / whan Ieſu Chriſt had caſt out a deuel from a man that was dombe as it is wrytten in the goſpeles of. Math. xij. Mar. iij.<note place="margin">Math. 12. Marci. 3. Luce. 11.</note> Luce. xj. Anone thys man began to ſpeke to puplyſſhe thys myracle amonge the people. Than the Scrybes and Pharyſees en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyous ſectes / that were a falſe religyon ſclaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Chryſte ſaynge that he dyd thys myracle in Belzebub prynce of deuelles. Belzabub is to ſay a god of Flyes / or elles a god that maketh dyſcorde. Lorde ſythen they durſt ſaye thys of Chryſte / hed of al mannes ſoull / howe moche warſe (yf warſe may be) ſhall they auenture to ſaye of hys poore ſeruauntes prechers the truth of hys lawe / but Prelates and Fryers in theſe dayes ben accombred with thys ſynne agaynſte the holy goſte / and ſhamefully ſclaundren / her ſymple brether / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trauaylen through Chriſtes holy lawe to caſt yuel maners from theyr ſoules prechynge the goſpell to Chryſtes intente / to tourne the people to vertuous lyuyng / they ſay
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:8704:7"/>
Thys man hathe eaten a flye / that geueth hym lore of godes lawe / thys is more foly to eate a flye then be a god and chaſe theſe flyes / thus haue they brought theyr malice aboute / to ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der for heretyckes that ſpeke of god &amp; ſo dryue they the people from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth that they dare not wyrche ne ſpeke for ſclaundre. But truly they be not wordye Chryſte that feare barkynges of theſe houndes for none is worthy to be with his Lorde / that ſhameth his ſeruyce in well or in woo / and ſuche men ſhewe them ſelfes tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours to god / that with theyr deuelyſſhe la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gage defamen theyr brethern / and ſayenge / that the fende may and wyll make wyſe hys members that ſerue hym in ſynne but ſo wyll not Chriſt hys beloued ſeruauntes that lyuen in clennes to ſerue hym in vertue. O I praye the who harde euer a fouler blaſphemy / certaynly thys dyſpyte ſtretched into the godhede / to be po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhed in the daye of iugemente / for goddes lawe teachethe / forbede hym not that can doo well / but yf thou mayſt doo well / doo it. The preſte ſhulde not be letted to preache the truth / neyther the people to ſpeke of theyr beleue as it is taught in the booke of Numeri. vi.<note place="margin">Numer. 11.</note> where it is wrytten that Heldad and Medad propheſyed / al be it that they were not lycenced by Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Ioſue the Duke and miniſter of Moyſes / grutched agaynſt theſe men / and complayned on them to Moyſes. And Moyſes ſayde to Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſue. why arte thou ſo enuyous towardes me / who may lete or withdrawe that all the people
<pb facs="tcp:8704:8"/>
prophecye / if god gyue them hys ſpyrite. This maner of doynge is alſo confyrmed in the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of our lorde Ieſu Chryſte. Seynte Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Euaungelyſte complayned / to Chryſte ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge. Maſter we haue ſeen a man / caſtynge out deuelles in thy name that foloweth not vs / and we haue forbydden hym. Alas ſe then howe dare our byſſhhopes for ſhame offende agaynſte theſe both godes lawes / and doke theyr preſtes on euery ſyde / geuynge them charge on payne to do pryue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr offyce / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they preach not the treuth. But after the bely faſſhyon. And Seyncte Ierom co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendyth in preſtehode pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge the goſpel &amp; bleſſyng the people before the ſayeng of maſſe.<note place="margin">Diſt. 56. 1. Corin. 1. Non me mi ſit chriſtus baptizare ſed euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizare.</note> And Seynct Paull ſayth / that Chriſt ſent hym to preche &amp; not to baptyſe. So by this it apereth that prechynge the goſpel is the hygheſt feruyce that may be done to god. But here the enemyes of trouth obiecten and leyen / for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this text of Seynct Paule. How ſhall they preche / but yf they bene ſente with thys texte they blynden moche people cuttynge the ſentens frome the wordes.<note place="margin">Ro. 10, Quomodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>predicabu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t niſi mittan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> For Poull mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethe that preſtes ſhulde preache. For they be ſente bothe of god and of the byſſhopes for to do that offyce / as the Mayſter of the ſentence ſayeth in hys .iiij. boke / and the .iiij. and .x. Diſtinctyon. It is thoffyce of a deken to preche the goſpell / then by the more ſtronger reaſon it apperteineth to a preſte. For Seincte Ierom and Seyncte Bede accorden together ſayenge. ryght as thappoſteles is the forme of byſſhops / 
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:8704:8"/>
ſo in .lxxij. diſcyples is the fourme of preſtes. But Chryſte gaue charge / bothe to theſe / byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopes / and alſo to theſe preſtes ſayenge.<note place="margin">Math. 10. Ecce ego mitto vos.</note> Lo I ſende you as ſhepe amonge wolues. And Chriſte Ieſu aſſygnynge .lxxij. dyſciples / ſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>em to preche. Howe ſhall theſe byſſhopes maynteyne theſe conſtitucyons agaynſte god and holy ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes.<note place="margin">Luce. 10. Deſignauit 72. et mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit. &amp;c.</note> It ſhalbe more ſufferable to Sodom and Go<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer / than to thys people that thus dyſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den godes ordenaunces.</p>
               <p>The ſyxt ſynne / is fyghtynge agaynſte treuth that man knowith that is as when trouthe is tolde to the gyltye / that is not dyſpoſed to be amended / then he maketh blynde and vngroun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded reaſons with ſutle ſophiſticall damnynge / the truth agaynſt hys owne conſcyens / with a bolde face hauynge no ſhame / as the prophete Ieremie ſayth.<note place="margin">Ieremie. 3. Frons mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieris mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricis facta eſt tibi &amp; no luiſti erubeſ cere. &amp;c.</note> The face of an harlot is made vnto the / and thou woldeſt not be aſſhamed. But as Paule ſayth Ryght as Iambnes &amp; Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres agaynſte ſtanden Moſes in the ſyght of Pharao ſo theſe agayne ſtanden treuthe as men corrupte in theyr owne concyens. And yf thou wyll knowe what theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be / aſke of. Seynct Peter and he wyll tell the / for he clepethe them by theyr names / in hys epyſtle where he ſayeth / that they bene mayſter lyers that ſhall brynge in amonge the people ſectes of perdicy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / that is of loſſe and deth / though ye ryſen with Lucyfer / and maken your neſtes amonge the ſterres. Thenſe ye ſhall / fall and dyſſende
<pb facs="tcp:8704:9"/>
with the ſame Lucifer into hell there to be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally tormented in payne that ſhall laſte / and endure for euermore.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">☞Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. 11. Sume tibi vaſa paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ſtulti. &amp;c</note>☞The Lord ſayeth by the prophete zacharie. Take to the the veſſelles of a folyſſhe ſheparde for lo I ſhall ſuffre Antechriſte to be reyſed by in erthe / the whiche ſhall not viſite them that be forſaken / nor ſeke them that be ſcatred nor hele them that be ſeke.<note place="margin">☞Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos. 8. Qui no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet ſpiritu chriſti / nec eſt cuin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> O thou folyſſhe paſtor / Antechryſte Antechryſte god ſaythe thou arte an ydoll hauynge a byſſhops habyte. But ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertue / ſpirite / lyfe ne dede that longyth to a byſſhop. For Paule ſayth / that he whiche hathe not the ſpirite of Chryſte he is not his ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uaunte / al be it that he haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outwarde tokens And therfore ſayth ſeynct Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .v.<note place="margin">Apo. 16. Quintꝰ an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gelus effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</note> angell powred his crwette vpon the ſete of the beſte / and his realme is made darke / and they byten theyr tonges to gether for ſorowe / and they blaſphemyd god of heuen / for ther ſorowes and theyr woundes / and they dyd no penaunce for theyr dedes / that is to meane Archebyſſhopes and Byſſhopes bene the ſete of the beſte Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt for in them he ſytteth &amp; reygneth ouer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people in the darkenes of his hereſye / and in thys they delyten them magnifyenge with theyr tonges ther falſe ordenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces the which is ſorowe to them that bene of true vnderſtandyng and thus they put abake godes lawe / for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng of Chriſtes goſpell y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which bene ſorowes to them gendrynge ſynnes in theyr ſoules / that
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:8704:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
wounden him to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deth. And beyng thus woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſhall neuer do medefull penaunce of dedes / for the whiche they ſhalbe dampned. Lyncoln<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth. I dred. I quake &amp; hugely I am aferde: but I dare not be ſtyl / left peraduenture the ſentens fal on me that the ꝓphete ſayeth. wo to me:<note place="margin">Yſaye. 6. De in quia tacui.</note> that I haue bene ſtyll. The well / the begynnynge / and the cauſe of all ruine and myſchyefe is the courte of Rome.<note place="margin">Rome.</note> Nowe by thauctoryte of god / &amp; one accorde of holy ſaynctes ſhewyth an open concluſion ſadly grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in true beleue / that in the courte of Rome / is the heed of Antechryſt / and in archebyſſhopes and byſſhopes / is the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Antechriſt / but in theſe patched / and clou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted ſectes as Monkes Chanons and Freers / is the venemous tayle of Antechriſte / theſe .iij. partyes be verefyed of thapoſtle Iude ſayng. wo to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that walketh in the way of Cayne (theſe bene falſe poſſeſſioners) And wo to them that bene ſhade out for mede in the errour of Balam: theſe bene myghty nedleſſe beggers / and wo to them that haue peryſſhed in the contradiccyon of Chore. Theſe ben proude and ſtourdy mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teners. Howe this Antechriſt ſhalbe diſtroyed god hym ſelf teacheth by the prophete Danyel:<note place="margin">Danyel. 8. Sine manu conteretur.</note> ſayenge that thys Antechriſt ſhalbe dyſtroyed without hande / that is without the power of man. For Paule ſayeth. Chriſt ſhall ſle Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chryſt with the ſpiryte of hys mouthe (that is with the holy worde of his lawe) and the lorde ſhall dyſtroye hym with the ſhynynge of his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng / that is with tournyng of mennes hertes
<pb facs="tcp:8704:10"/>
by grace to his lawe a litle before his danie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But god taught more playnly this lord to Iob. 40 Lo (ſayeth god) the hope that Antechryſt hathe in riches / and in worldly fauour / ſhall brynge hym to nought / and all men ſaynge he ſhalbe throwen downe hedlyng. So that all the people ſhall make waylynges vpon him with greate lamentacyon / curſynge waryenge &amp; dampnyng him with al his falſe orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ What is Antechryſt in ſpecyall with .v. condicions. Capi. v.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt nowe at the laſte</hi> / we ſhall brynge to mynde holy Dauid the kynge that had geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to him the full ſpirit of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye / and he ſeynge the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge of Antechriſt / his lyuynge and his fall / marketh .v. hydeous aſſaultes that he ſhall haunte agaynſt the ſeruauntes of god Pſal. 9.<note place="margin">Conſtitue dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e leges<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latorem ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per eos.</note> The firſt aſſaulte of Antechriſt / is his conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucions / as the prophete ſayth. Lord ſuffre thou to ordeyne a law maker vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people in payne of theyr ſynnes for that they conſent not to the trought / that is thus to meane / Antechryſte vſith falce lucratyfe or wynnyge lawes / as ben abſolucions / indulgenſes / pardones / priuileges
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:8704:10"/>
&amp; all other heuenly treaſure that is brought into ſafe / to ſpoyle / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of their wordly goodes and pryncipally theſe newe conſtitucions / by whoſe auctorytie Antechryſte interditeth chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches / ſomeneth prechers / ſuſpendith receyuers: &amp; priueth them theyr benefice / curſyth herers / and taketh away the goodes of them / that fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren the prechynge of the trought ye thoughe it were an angell of heuen. But yf the preſt ſhew the marke of the beſte / that they haue properly tourned into a newe name callynge hit a ſpeciall lettre of lycence / for the more blyndynge of the people. The ſeconde Aſſaulte of Antechryſt / <note place="margin">Deſpicis oportunita tibꝪ i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacione. &amp;c.</note> is tribulacion / as the prophete ſayth. Antechryſte vexeth the people ouermyghtely / in huntynge the people on mawmetry / and doynge of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry / but euer Antechryſt maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to wene that they gone on pylgremage. And therfore he is warned of god by the prophete ſayenge.<note place="margin">Yſaye. 5.</note> wo to you that ſayen / good is yll / and yll is good puttynge lyght into darkeneſſe and darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe into lyght. Tornynge ſwete into bytter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / and bytter into ſwetneſſe. And thus dothe Antechryſte whan he tranſlateth vertues into vices / and vices into vertues / as pylgremage in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to outrage / and outrage into pylgremage / and for this wawarde intent god deſpyſeth Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt with all blyndefelde people / and lateth al theyr myſpended goodes in theyr moſt tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. The .iij. aſſaulte of Antechriſt is inquificio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophete ſayth / that Antechriſt enquyreth ſecheth and harkeneth / where he maye fynde
<pb facs="tcp:8704:11"/>
any man or woman that wryteth lerneth redith or ſtudyeth goddes lawe in theyr mother tonge: to leade theyr lyues after the pleaſynge wyll of god. Anon he catcheth them in hys ſenſures / and after ſmyteth as he may moſte hurte them / but he ſhall not make thys inquiſicion after the multitude or greatneſſe of hys wrathe. For god ſhall refrayne or abrydge the power of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice / ſo that he ſhall nomore do than god wyll ſuffre him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knoweth the meſour of his dedes to proue his ſeruauntes by the fornays of penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce acceptable. And Antechryſt with theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus herted in malice inexcuſable.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Inſidiatur vt capiat pauperem.</note>The .iiij. aſſaulte of Antechriſt is perſecucyon as the prophete ſayeth. That Antechriſt ſittyth in the eaſe of thys worlde with ryche men in theyr dennes. But the poore meke ſymple and lowly / them he eſpyeth and purſueth / he ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepeth and ouerronneth raueſſhynge them bothe bodely and goſtely.<note place="margin">Iob. 40.</note> For god ſayth vnto Iob / that hath a truſte and a trowynge that Iordan may flowe into his mouthe. And therfore he ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth hys dwellynge place in the herte of the ſee as our Lorde ſayeth by hys prophete / <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Eze. 20.</note> that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techryſte maketh hys boſte and ſayeth by hys prophete. I haue ſytten in the chayre of god in the hert of the ſee / whan thou arte but man &amp; no god. But euer in fatte countres walowynge &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bundyng of worldly goodes there is Antechriſt with his clerkes buyldyng theyr neſtes. And yf thou loke witterly aboute / thou ſhalt fynde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amonge woodes and waters / as ſeyncte Iohan
<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:8704:11"/>
ſayth / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſawe out of the mouth of the dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon that is the heed of Antechryſt / <note place="margin">☞ Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipſis. 10. Vidi de ore draconis et de ore beſtie et de ore pſeudo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete tres ſpiritus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundos ex iſſe in modu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ranarum.</note> &amp; out of the mouth of the beſte that is the body of Antechriſt and out of the mouth of the falſe prophete / that is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tayle of Antechryſt. Thre vnclene ſpirytes to haue paſſed out in the maner of frogges / ſyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge in holes by the water brynke / purchaſen of the grounde aboue &amp; on the erthe beſyde them but that that is vnderneth them they woll not her thankes neyther loſe ne leſe it. So theſe. iij. vnclene ſpirites crokyng in Couetyſe / Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony / and Lechery / betoken Antechryſte with hys .iij. partes for they purchaſen of lordes that bene aboue them moch parte of theyr good with the tonge of flattry and fayned Ipocreſy / and of the commoners aboute them / they wylen in theyr handes moche parte of theyr catayle / but that they haue wonne they holden faſte agayne thauctoryte of goddes lawes. And with theſe rycheſes they noryſhen wylde ſtourdy / &amp; law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les men / that purſuen them that woll ought ſay agaynſte this curſyd ſynne. But in thys perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon / the prophete comforteth the ſeruauntes of god ſayenge. God is our refuge and our ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue / god is our helpe in trybulacions the whiche haue ouer moche / or paſſyngly founden vs / wherfore we ſhall not drede whylles that men lyuynge after thys worlde bene troubled / and hylles ſhullen be borne ouer into the herte of the ſee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay. True men ſhall not be abaſſhed though proude fleſſhly men be comforted to An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>techriſte and helpen him in hys perſecutyon.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8704:12"/>The .v. aſſaulte of Antechryſt is execucyon / <note place="margin">Capere pau perem dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m attrahit eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> as the prophete ſayth. whan Antechryſt ſaith that he auayleth not in theſe forſayde tourmentes / than he executyth hys malyce agaynſte Chriſtes choſen / as ſaynct Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth. That the beſte of the erthe ſhall geue power to the beſte of the ſee / for in this tyme of execucyon. The vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous parte of the lay / ſe from the higheſt degree to the loweſt / ſhall conſent to execute the wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes of the vicious parte of the clergy. Than ſhal this propheſye be fulfylled pſal. 78. They ſhal ſhede out innocent bloude / and no man ſhall dare bury theyr bones / for they ſhall caſte theyr fleſhe to fowles of the ayer / and theyr careyns to beſtes of the erthe. Than ſayth the prophete that whan Antechryſte weneth he hath lorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp ouer al the ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of god reyſynge vpon them guiues of diuerſe tormetry then ſhal he fal to open repreue for euer more The full tyme of Antechriſte dureth .iii. yeres and an halfe / but that the goſpell doth remytte / and elles ſhulde nat all fleſhe be made ſaue / thys tyme was fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured vnder Ely the prophete. And kynge A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chab that wycked man / <note place="margin">Regum. 3. cap. 17. Iacobi. 5. Regum. 28 Danyel. 7.</note> there ſhewyth the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that the raine was ſtopped .iij. yeres / and .vj. monethes / ſeynct Iames bereth wytnes of this thinge in his canon epyſtle. The flyenge of Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyd from kynge Saule marketh this tyme who ſo taketh hede and rede that boke to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt ende. Alſo the leſynge of Hieruſalem dyſcloſeth thys tyme as Ioſephus telleth. Danyel taught this
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:8704:12"/>
nombre alſo i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time and tymes and halfe a time / and this is .iij. yeres and demy / as ſaynt Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom declareth in his boke &amp; ſeyntes of the mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye Macabeus vnder thys tyme made clene theyr Temple / wherfore ſaynte Iohan in his Apocalipſe / often times reherſeth thys nombre whan he ſpeketh of Antechryſte. And Chryſte kepeth thys nombre for the tyme of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge out take that leſte by vertue of hys paſſyon ſayncte Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cryſoſtom / vpon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewe ca. 57. ſaythe / by thre yeres and .vj. monethes / the ſacryfyce of goddes pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge that ſhulde be in mannes mouthe / the ſacryfyce of ryghtwyſneſſe that ſhulde be in mannes workes / and the ſacrafyce of peace that ſhulde be in tretynge of Chryſtes body / ſhalbe taken awaye from all faythfull through ſtronge woodneſſe of Antechryſte / then ſhall all true chryſtiane fle the face of Antechryſte / ſo that none ſhall nowe entre into the churche to doo due ſeruyce to theyr god / after thys the people ſhall tourne with all theyr myght bothe chryſtiane and Iewes / to the kepynge of goddes lawe and doynge of vertuous pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce as Paule wytneſſynge ſayth. Blyndnes fell by parte in Iſraell vnto the tyme that plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of hethen gentles ſhulde entre into chryſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.<note place="margin">☞ Ro. 11.</note> And then in thende of the worlde that is after the deſtruccyon of Antechryſte al Iſraell ſhalbe made ſaue.<note place="margin">Enocke and Ely become</note> No man loke after Enoke and Ely in perſone for than they maye lyghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
<pb facs="tcp:8704:13"/>
be begyled / but in ſpyrite and in vertue nowe they be come: to make mennes hertes redy afore chriſtes home / to whome be glory nowe and euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>¶What is the churche only appro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pried to god with theyr na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes / lykeneſis and condicions. Ca. vi.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O ſpek of holy church</hi> Fyrſt we take grounde of the goſpel where Chryſte ſayeth.<note place="margin">Math. 19. Porte infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri non pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualebu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus eam Nicholaus de Lira.</note> That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gattes of hel ſhal not preuayle nor haue myght / a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt holy church / vpon this texte Lyre ſayeth. That the church is not in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by way of power or dignite ſpirituall or tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall for many Princes / and high Byſſhopes &amp; other of lower degree: ſtate and dignite are foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to be apoſtates or haue gone backe from the fayth / wherfore the churche ſtandeth in thoſe perſons in whome is knowynge and very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſyon of fayth and trouth. But for the more clere declarynge of this matter / and auoydynge of obiections that may be put forth we ſhall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther bene .iii. churchis of the which goddes lawe ofte maketh mencyon:<note place="margin">Tres Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſie.</note> and moche they dyuerſen eche from other / to them that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken good hede: but here wytles foles bene accom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bred
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:8704:13"/>
that labour not to lerne to knowe theyr dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſytees. The fyrſt churche is called a lytle flocke as Chryſte ſayeth.<note place="margin">☞ Prima eccleſie. Luce. 12.</note> Drede ye not my lytle flocke / hit pleaſeth your father to gyue you a kyngdome / and thys churche is cleped the cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen nombre of them: that ſhalbe be ſaued as it is wrytten / that the ſonnes of wyſdome bene the churche of ryghtwyſemen / <note place="margin">Eccleſia. 3.</note> and the nacion of them is buxoume to god and louyng to hys euen chriſten.<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Ephe. 5.</note> This church is called a clene mayden as Paule ſayth. Chryſte hath choſen hym a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious churche hauynge neyther ſpot nor wemme or any ſuche other / <note place="margin">Diſtinc. 13.</note> but that thys churche may be holy and vndefouled to thys accordeth Lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayenge that holy churche of god is a chaſte virgin chriſtes glorious ſpouſe without ſpot or bleyne. The .iij. tyme thys churche is called chryſtes ſpouſe of thys mariage Paule beryth wytnes ſaynge. I haue maryed you to one man: that is not to an auoutrer / <note place="margin">Corin. 10.</note> but to a laufull man Chriſt Ieſu / that I may preſent you to god / a clene chaſte mayde at the day of dome / and thus we ſay in the dedycacyon of the materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all churche. Thys day holy churche a glorious ſpouſe is maryed to Chryſt her ſouerayne.<note place="margin">Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes. 6</note> This churche is lykened to a woman with chylde as Chryſte ſayeth. A woman when ſhe trauayleth ſhe hath paynes.<note place="margin">Apo. 12.</note> Thys churche is lykened to a woman clade in the ſonne / as ſayncte Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Thapocalips ſayeth / I ſawe a wounderfull ſyght and that was a woman clade in the ſonne Thys churche is alſo lykened to Peters lytle
<pb facs="tcp:8704:14"/>
bote beynge in the myddes of the ſee / this bote both ſanke and ſwame.<note place="margin">Math. 14 Mar. 6. Luce. 8.</note> But drowne myght hit neuer / ſo holy churche ſuffereth many perells / and ſome tyme bodely dethe by purſute of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes / but it ſhal neuer be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned. This church is lykened to Paradyce / <note place="margin">Eze. 30.</note> thus ſayth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete. Cedre trees were not hygher then he in paradyſe of god. wher vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaynct Auſten ſayth. Paradyce is holy churche the .iiij. flodes ben the iiij. goſpelles wryten of Mathewe / Marke / Luke / and Iohan / that were fygured in lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of .iiij. beſtes / that is a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / a Lyon / a Calfe an Egle / for theſe precheden Chriſt the whiche is to gether / man / knyght / preſte / and god / and by theſe .iiij.<note place="margin">Story. Allegory. Morall. Anagogical</note> we ben taught in ſtory what is done / in allegorye what we ſhulde beleue / in morall what we ſhall do / and in Anagogye what we ſhall hope. The trees that beren fruyte / bene good lyuers here in erthe. The fruytes of theſe trees / bene good workes of ſaynctes the tree of lyfe is the ſayncte paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge all ſaynctes our lorde Ieſu Chryſte. The tree of knowynge good and euell / is the free choyſe of mannes wyll. Thys is holye churche onely propred to god that ſerueth hym in vertue nyght and daye / but howe euer we ſpeken in dyuers maners or lykeneſſe of thys holye churche / they teachen not elles / but this one name that is to ſaye the congregacyon or gadrynge to gether of faythefull ſoules / that euer more kepen faythe / and trought in worde and dede to god and man and reyſen theyr lyfe
<pb n="xiiii" facs="tcp:8704:14"/>
in ſyker hope of mercy and grace and blyſſe / at theyr ende and helen thys buyldynge in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte charyte / that ſhall not fayle in wele ne wo / of thys ſpake ſayncte Paule / <note place="margin">Corinth. 3. Templum enim dei ſanctum eſt / quod eſtis vos.</note> to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rintheans and in them to all other ſayenge The temple of god is holy and that be ye ſo than by thys hit apperethe that the ſoull of euery faythefull of euery criſten man / is the ſete and very temple of god / wele oughte than euery man to be ware and wyſe that hathe the greate god lorde of Iſraell dwellynge in hys ſoull. And ſo ſayth ſayncte Auſten. O thou chriſten ſoull a wake / and yf there by any vertue of charyte in the that ſuſteyneth all thynges / folowe thou the ſteppes of thy lorde / take hede howe many thouſande marters haue made aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moche playne waye to the / there haue paſſed before the virgynes / chylder / yonge damme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelles and maydens / and yf thou dredyſte / aryſe thou ſoule for he ſhall leade the / that is the waye / the trought and the lyfe / the waye that errethe not / the trought that neuer begyled / and the lyfe neuer faylynge / waye in example / troughte in promyſſyon / lyfe in mede. And to thys entente / Cryſte lykened mannes ſoule to a woman with chylde / for in her trauayle ſhe hathe ſtronge paynes / but whan ſhe hathe borne the chylde into thys worlde / ſhe hathe no mynde of her payne / for Ioye of the chylde. Thus wandrythe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye churche / in erthe in prayers / faſtynges / 
<pb facs="tcp:8704:15"/>
and in waylynges / in abſtinens / in tribulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and in anguyſhe / in perſecucyon / in nede: and in pryſon / in colde / in hungre / and in heuynes / in bondes / in fetters / &amp; great dyſtres / in thyrſt in payne / &amp; in blame / in reproche / in ſclaundre / and in ſhame / in pacyens / pyte / and long aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng / in ſimplenes / lykenes / &amp; ſighes / in we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge / waylynge / &amp; in wo / in fortune / in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brenes and in chaſtite / in ſpedynes in largenes / and in charite. Theſe be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gronynges of mannes ſoull / that longeth in harte after Chryſte her ſpouſe / tyll ſhe haue brought forthe her ſelfe a chyld of god into blyſſe perdurable / &amp; than for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greatnes of godes rewarde / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more ſhe ſuffred y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more is her Ioye / for ſo ſayth ſeynct Paul y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the paſſions of this time bene as no paynes in re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>garde to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to come / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhalbe ſhewed in vs for tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhalbe endowed with .iiij. dowe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryes in our bodyes.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> Of the which ſeynct Paull ſpekyth / ſayenge that the body that is ſowen in corrupcyon / ſhall ryſe without corrupcion / in this church of god at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day of dome. And this dowre is cleped immortalite or vndedlynes / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> body that is ſowen vnworthy / ſhall ryſe in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: and this dowry is called clerenes / that body that is ſowen in infyrmyte or inſtablenes / ſhall ryſe in vertue / &amp; thys dowry is called Agilite or ſwyftenes. That body that is ſowen beſtiall ſhall ryſe ſpirituall / and this dowry is called ſubtylite. But there bene other foure dowryes of ſubſtanciall medes / with the which we ſhalbe
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:8704:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
dowred in our ſoul. The firſt dowry is called im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſſibilite / the ſeconde is tuicion / the .iij. perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall charyte / the .iiij. is fruytion. Or after this maner to ſpeke more playnly: the firſt is know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege without errour / the ſeconde is mynd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out forgettynge / the thyrde is wel without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiccyon: and the .iiij. is thus of the godhede and loue of god euerlaſtynge. O what a woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drefull ioye is thys / where the ſoul ſhalbe fedde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſyght of the godhed: &amp; certes / this is ioye without wrechydnes / reſt without buſynes / mirthe without heuynes / ſurety endeles / of al diſcorde lotheles. This is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte in al gladnes: of purueyans / careles.<note place="margin">Yſaye. 64 Corinth. 2.</note> This wytneſſith the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet Yſaye &amp; ſeynct Paule in his epiſtle ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bodely yie hath not ſene / ne eare hath herde / ne hert of man thought: what thynges they be that god hathe ordeyned or prepared to them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loue him.<note place="margin">P</note> Lorde who ſhall not auance his feble wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to thynke on that louely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in heuen the goodnes of thys inſcrutable godhede / father and ſonne and holy goſte. To begynne at Mary Chriſtes mother / quene of heuen / lady of therthe and Impreſſe of hell. Nyne orders of Angelles in glorious wyſe that dwellynge in theyr heuenly ſelles / to do the pleaſynge wyll of god: in heuen and in erthe / as theyr order aſketh. And patriarkes our elder fathers that ſtreytly kept the byddinges of god: there they reſten of all theyr trauayle in lond of life with double mede. Ther bene ꝓphetes that ſene in ſpirite the myſtery of Chryſtes incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon
<pb facs="tcp:8704:16"/>
they tolde the commynge of this lorde in hope abydynge mannes ſaluacion. Euangeliſtes ben there hygh in blyſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> walken with Chriſt and wryt his wordes. Apoſtelles ſent into all the worlde and Chriſtes diſcyples to preche the goſpell turnyng Iewes &amp; hethen me to Chriſtes lawe / there they ſitten on ſeetes vpon .xij. tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and ſhallinge with Chryſte in the dome the xij. tribꝪ of Iſrael Math. 19. There ben mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that ſhede there bloude &amp; ſuffered paynes to enlarge theyr ioye / and for they paſſed by fyre &amp; water they haue founde refreſſhynge to theyr ſoules / alſo ther be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſours y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> opened chriſtes lawe to thys worlde / and neyther for felony ne for ſhame wolde neuer deny / that bliſſyd lord / ther ben virgins in body and ſoull that kept the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in clennes from luſte of fleſhe. And to this bliſſe be taken both leryd &amp; lewde that done ther vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſte wyll to kepe goddes commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes no tonge may tel the ſothe as it is.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> But thus we ſeien to amende our deuotion that we myght haue that blyſſe in mynde / &amp; take a parte among theſe ſaynctes. But ſaynct Iohan when he was ledde in ſpirite ſawe in heuen a wonderfull ſyght and for to chere mankynde in erthe / he left it wrytten in his boke that is to ſay.<note place="margin">☞Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipſis. 13.</note> Sainct Iohan ſawe a woman clade in the ſonne / and mone vnder her fete / and a crowne vpon her hed of the .xij. ſterres / this woman betokeneth man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſoull / as we toke wytnes of Chriſt before / and certayne thys was a blyſſedfull ſyght to ſe the church in her weddynge clothes / the ſonne
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:8704:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that thys churche is cladde in / is that moſte worſhypfull garnement our ſaluacyon / that excellent and moſte commendable lyuerey our redempcyon / that holy and moſte precious cloth our chryſtendome / and our relygion / for thys Chryſte betoke vs when we were baptized as Paule ſayeth.<note place="margin">Gal. 13. Quicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> baptizati eſtis chriſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> induiſtis.</note> All ye that be baptyzed ye be clade Chryſte / Ieſu the ſon beryth lyghtneſſe of our baptym for certayne propertyes that it hath of the ſonne / other lyghtes borowe there ſhyni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / bothe mone &amp; ſterres in theyr due courſe and elles they ben ouerleade with darkenes / that may not comforte to nyght ne day. So all mannes warke in worde and dede borowith there lyght at Chryſte. Ieſu for he is the ſonne of ryghtwyſneſſe as Mardoche ſaythe in the ſpyryte of god .8. that is to ſaye Lyght and ſon is vpſprynge to vs and meke lowly men vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haunſed in hys ſaynctes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boke declareth what thys is to meane / <note place="margin">Pſal. 113.</note> lyght is vpſprongen to right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe / that wandren in darkeneſſe of his lyfe / and thys is our lorde Ieſu Chryſte that of hys owne mercy hathe ſhewed / the people. And thys we rede of true beleue in the ſtory of our bleſſed Lady / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay / Mary a virgyn hathe borne the ſouerayne ſonne of richtwiſnes that is godde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> heuen Chriſt Ieſu bothe god &amp; man / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> man doth that fayleth this lyght / it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> yndelinge and the doungi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on of hel / and whan thys ſonne ſhyneth in hys workes he growith by hete of grace / and rypeth
<pb facs="tcp:8704:17"/>
that ſhynen in thys crowne ben the .xij. artycles of the comon crede / that is to ſay. Credo in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. &amp;c. Thus ſhulde that ſoull be arayed that is choſen to be Chryſtes ſpouſe / and worthyly is holy church lykened to a woman / for a woman bryngeth forth bothe ſonnes and doughters of her wombe / but not without helpe and the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chynge of mannes ſede. So our mother holy churche bereth in her bely ſoules to be borne to the blyſſe of heuen / but neuer without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> helpe and worchynge of the grace of our lorde Ieſu Chryſte / <note place="margin">Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 16. Sine me no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poteſtis facere.</note> as the goſpell wytneſſhyth / ſayenge. without me ye may do nothynge / that is to ſay medefully or thankworthy. Here ſome men ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecten and ſayen / that the goſpell is not of auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torytie / but inaſmoche as the church hath auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toryſed &amp; chanoniſed it for they ſayen. No man knowith ſuche wordes to be goſpel / but as the church hath determyned in her determinacyon / this concluſion ſemeth to ſmacke hereſy / <note place="margin">Gene. 2.</note> by the wytnes of ſaynct Auſten ſayeng on this wyſe. Hereſy is falſe teachynge contrary to holy writ ful hardely defended moſt becauſe of worſhyp &amp; worldly wynnyng / &amp; ſithen al theſe ben fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den in this forſayd obiection it is full ſuſpect of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſye / for it is wrytten from the begynnynge that god ordeyned man to be hed and lorde ouer the woman. And agaynwarde the woman to be vnderloute &amp; ſubiect vnto ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Ephe. 5.</note> But Paule ſayth. This great ſacrament of knyttyng to gether a man &amp; his wyfe betokeneth the knyttyng to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Chriſt &amp; his church / ſhal not than mannes
<pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:8704:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſoull vnderloute to Chriſt in worde &amp; dede / in this ſpirituall maryage more perfictly tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this woman can or may in the ſacrament of fleſhe / ſaynct Iamys diſtroyeth this obiection ſayeng / <note place="margin">☞ Iaco. 1</note> that god hath wylfully &amp; of his owne wyl got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vs through the word of truth / that we may be ſum begynnynge of his creature / and thys creature is one paſſynge creature holy churche / that was choſen in the tyme of grace / by the wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of clenſynge by Chriſtes bloude of agayne byenge / and by the vertue of the holy goſte hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowyng were it not agaynſt reaſon. Ye and open hereſy to maynteyne that the worde of god that hath gotten this creature holy churche / <note place="margin">Cant. 6. Pulcra vt luna.</note> ſhulde not be of auctoryte without auctoriſyng of thys creature holy church / wherfore this concluſyon approued we graunt of beleue / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the churche is vnderloute to Chriſt &amp; his word in .iiij. maners. Fyrſte as the mone to the ſonne / the churche is fayre as the mone.<note place="margin">Yſaye. 55.</note> The ſeconde as therth to the fyrmament of whome it is made plentuous or watrede as dewe comythe downe from the fyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament and tourneth not thether agayne. But watrethe therth and makethe hit plentuous of fruytes ſo the worde of god noryſſhethe holy churche and makethe hit to brynge forth good fruytes. The .iij. maner as the fleſſhe to the ſpyryte / <note place="margin">Iohe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. 6.</note> of whome it is quyckened for it is the ſpyryte that quyckeneth and geueth lyfe.</p>
               <p>The .iiij.<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Ephe. 1.</note> maner as the bodye to the heed if whome it is gouerned for god the father hathe made hys ſonne Chryſte / the heed
<pb facs="tcp:8704:18"/>
of the church / <note place="margin">Collo. 1.</note> and efte ſaynct Paule ſaith Coll. 1. Chryſte is the heed of the body of the church / and euery choſen man and woman is called a ſon or a doughter of the churche / <note place="margin">☞ Ro. 12.</note> but all to gether ben the fullbody of thys church as ſainct Paule ſayth. we many ben one body in Chryſte Ieſu forſothe eche of vs ben others members / but ſome chylder of this woman ben ſymple labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers / and for that they parten and deuyden their true labour or trauayle / therfore they repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te the good loue of the holy goſte / and theſe dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the lorde and walken in the wayes of hys commaundementes / as the ꝓphete ſayth.<note place="margin">Pſal. 127.</note> Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be all labourers that drede the lorde &amp; wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in hys wayes / for thou ſhalt lyue by the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of thyne handes / thou arte bleſſed and wel ſhalbe to the / and this is the loweſt eſtate that we cal comons / ſome of theſe womans chyldren taken materiall ſwerde and ben made miniſters of Chryſtes godhed hauynge power and drede into wrathe / and vengeans of them that done yuell / and prayſyng of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> done wel / and ſo by thauctoryte of ſaynt Iohan baptyſt in the goſpell of Chryſt. Luce. 3. and of ſaynct Peter. 12. and of ſaynct Paule Rom. 13. and by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre of ſaynct Yſodore. 23. q. 5. Principes / it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteyneth to the order of knyghthode / to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende goddes lawe / to mainteyne good lyuers / and to iuſtifie or punyſhe miſdoers / and thys is cleped the ſeconde ſtate in holy church / but ſome chyldre of this woman ſtyren into hygh order of preſthode / &amp; ben miniſters of Chriſtes manhede
<pb n="xix" facs="tcp:8704:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and theſe haue wytte and wyſdome to open to the people the way of truthe / and thys eſtate repreſenteth the ſeconde perſon in trynyte / that is the wyſdome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father our lord Ieſu Chriſt For ſayncte Auſtyn ſayth. Knyghthode repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyng the power of the father / is the vyccar of the godhede / and preſthode repreſentynge the wyſedome of the ſon is the vyccar of the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hede. And theſe knightes techynge vnto vs / the drede of goddes ryghtwyſnes that punyſſheth obſtinate and open ſynners / turnynge from his lawe in ſhrewdnes of theyr hertes / and preſtes techen vs by way of offyce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue that god hath to hys people / that forgeueth them all theyr ſynnes when they come to hym and do very pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce / than helpe preſtes with ſacramentes to pleaſe god and wynne his loue / for Paule mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſhyth the preſt Tymothy and in him al other preſtes to take good intent to .v. thynges / <note place="margin">Tymo. 4.</note> in whiche fully theyr offyces ſtanden / ſayenge. Awake thou preſte in buſy prayer prayenge for the people deuoutly. The ſeconde is this. Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſt in the leſſons of holy writ ſtudieng goddes lawe / only. The thyrde is this Do thou the worke of the goſpell prechyng goddes lawe truly. The .iiij. is this. Fulfyl thou y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myniſtery mynyſtrynge the ſacramentes frely. The .v. is this. Be thou ſobye in worde &amp; dede / doynge &amp; ſuffrynge laſtyngly. Vpon theſe .iij. eſtates ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the church that is appropryd to god / and by the vertue of Chryſtes incarnacion hit growith in mede to come to blyſſe. As Odo ſayth / that
<pb facs="tcp:8704:19"/>
Chryſt Ieſu toke fleſſhe and bloude in the may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dene wombe and was borne bothe god and man to annex our kynde to hys godhed / for when he toke our manhede / he graunted vs his godhed. And in this tyme in ſpecyall maner he firſt gaue erneſt to thys churche / after thys was Chryſte Ieſu daptyſed in Iordan and tempted thryſe of the fende to lerne vs mekely to ſuffre tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / and toke the deth vpon the croſſe / by cruell iugemente of the Iewes. And than the churche was trought plyght to Chryſte / cleped by name hys fayre clene ſpouſe / and as ſhe had grace by deuocyon of fayth / ſo ſhe had worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of this name. But when thys church is gon to heuen / and reſtyth in blyſſe with Chriſt / her ſpouſe / than is thys maryage fully ſacred with deyntes euerlaſtynge delytes. whyles this lyfe dureth in erthe thys churche is cleped militant. And when ſhe ſlepeth in Purgatory then is ſhe cleped the church ſlopande. But when ſhe reſtith of all her trauayle then ſhe is cleped the churche triumphant. Or thus more playnely. A true ſoull here in thys lyfe / fyghteth agaynſte the waues of ſynne to fle thaſſaultes of theſe .iij. enemys the fende / the worlde / and the wanton fleſſhe / in purgatory ſhe clenſeth her ſelfe from ruſt &amp; corrupcyon. But in heuen ſhe holdeth the towre &amp; the victorye of all her enemyes / and hath wone the crowne of lyfe that god hathe graunted to his louers. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="xx" facs="tcp:8704:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶What is the churche materyall. Capitulo. vii.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſeconde church dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſeth</hi> from thys for it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge to gether of good &amp; yll in a place that is hallowed / far from wordly occupacyon / for there ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſhuld be trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted / and goddes lawe both red and preched. Of this churche ſpeketh the ꝓphete Dauyd ſayeng. Bleſſe ye the lord god in churchis / <note place="margin">Pſal. 67.</note> in this place our gracious god hereth our prayer in a ſpecyall maner / and bowyth his eare to his ſeruaunt in fourme as he grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted Salamo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſayeng.<note place="margin">☞ Re. 9. Parali. 7.</note> Myne eyen ſhalbe open / and myne eares ſhalbe lyfte vp to the prayer of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hathe iuſtely prayed in thys place / and this is cleped a materyall place / but it is made by ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes crafte of lyme / timber / &amp; ſtone / with other neceſſaryes that lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth therto / for mannes profyt thys place is made / but not ſo / man for the place.<note place="margin">Math. 12. Mar. 2. Luce. 6.</note> And thys Chryſt marketh in the goſpel for man ſhuld not be begyled ſayenge that the ſabot is made for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man / &amp; not man for the ſabot / for man by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of goddes word / hallowith this place / but this place may not hallowe man. But man be firſt in cauſe / as Ierom ſayth. The place hallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth not the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> halloweth the place. Alas then what wodenes is this to boſt of holy places / and we our ſelfes vicious foles. Lucyfer was in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt holy place / but for
<pb facs="tcp:8704:20"/>
ſynne he fell into hell / the place myght not holde hym. Adam was in paradyce / the moſte mery place / and for his ſyn was dryuen thens / the place myght not defende hym. Thou that arte not in heuen nor in paradyce / but in thys wretched worlde where wenyſt thou to fynde a place to hallowe the that leuyſt not thy ſynne. Be thou ſeker as god is in heuen it wyl not be / for god is in no place fayre ſeruyd / but there as his lawe is fayre kepte of hys people. Saynct Ambroſe ſayth. Adam that was the more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy was made without paradice in the vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyer place Eue that was the leſſe worthy was made within paradice in the worthyer place / moche people demeth a medefull warke to make amendes agayne with curious buyldynges / and many fayre muſters in the church / but Ierom forbedeth this thyng to be done / and dampneth hit vtterly for greate ſyn nowe in this tyme of Chriſtes goſpell ſayenge. Many buylden wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les / &amp; pillers of the church / they vnder putten with ſhyninge marble ſtones / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beames glyſtern all in golde / the aulters ben dyuerſly arayed with precious ſtones / but of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſters of god ther is no choyſe. No riche man bye to me the temple in Iury / bordes / lanternes / ſenſers / pannes / cuppes / morters / and ſuch other made of golde / for than theſe thynges were approued of the lorde whan preſtes offred hoſtes and blud of beſtes was remyſſyon of ſinnes / though all theſe thynges went afore in fygure neuertheles: they be wrytten to vs into whome the endes of
<pb n="xxi" facs="tcp:8704:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the worldes be come. Nowe truly Chryſte our poore lord hath hallowed the houſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche of our pouertye bere we the croſſe of Chryſte / riches accompte we as clay. Vpon this writteth a great clerke ſayenge that ſuche men ſemen to tourne the breade of poore men into ſtones / and in that they ben more crueller than the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll / that aſked ſtones to be tourned into brede. To thys accordeth ſayncte Barnarde ſayenge. O vanyte of all vanytees / and nomore vanite tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſmoch madder / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church ſhineth in walles: &amp; ſhe nedeth in the poore / her ſtones ſhe lappeth in golde / and her owne ſonnes ſhe forſaketh na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of the charges &amp; expe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the nedy is made a vayne ſeruys to the yes of ryche men. But our newe fayned ſectes / in thys be moſte to blame / that maken great buyldynges / there leſte nede were / as Monkes / Chanons / and Fryers / No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes / Syſters &amp; ſpytlers / for people ſhulde drawe to paryſſhe churches / and here the worde of god ther as god hath lymyted / and elles they ben to blame. Lorde what meaneth theſe waſte places of theſe hyd Ipocrytes / but to tell men by theyr ſynagoges where Satans ſete is / there lurken to gethers many rauyſſhynge wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpoylen the people with theyr falce ſines for reaſons of holy wryt declared of doctours ſhulde teche you of this great defaulte yf that ye wyll amende. But here me dredeth as Paule fayeth / that the god of this worlde that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Mammon / hathe caſte hys pouldre afore your eyen and blent your goſtely lyght / <note place="margin">Cor. 4.</note> that ye
<pb facs="tcp:8704:21"/>
may not knowe the goſpell to the true vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge / and that one payne of your greate ſynne / tyll this ſentence be fulfylled / eche cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible / or eche worke that is rotten in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rote ſhall fall in the ende / and he that is founder of ſuche vngrounded worke ſhall fall and worthe to nought therwith in the laſt ende. God pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted neuer theſe ſectes in neyther of hys lawes ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther approued ſuch maner of lyfe. Chryſt in his lyfe pulled them vp by the rotes / that were i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his dayes as Aſſeys / Saduceyes / &amp; Pharyſees and dampned theyr ordenaunce and ſayd when they growe agayn in Monkes / Chanons / &amp; Fryers that they ſhulde be drawen vp agayne by the rote / as the goſpell wytneſſyth where Chryſte ſayde. That eche plante that my father of heuen hath not pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted <abbr>ſhalde</abbr> rent vp by the rotes. For all ſynneful inuencyons in man or in place / that is amonge the people of the whiche god is not auctor / though it growe faſt for a tyme / it ſhal be diſtroyed. The fyrſt reaſon that we ſhal make is ſhewed in thys maner. Theſe ſectes ben ded from thys worlde / as they ſaye in worde / yf thys be ſothe / then ſhall they haue poore cotes of mournynge to tell in dede that thys dethe is true in them / and in theyr workes and fle the maner of thys worlde in ſuche ſterynge vanyte is as Paule teacheth in hys pyſtle vnto the Colloſenſes ſayenge. Ye that ben dead / from the maners of thys worlde / <note place="margin">Collo. 3.</note> your lyfe is hyd with Chryſt in god / therfore mortefy ye / 
<pb n="xxii" facs="tcp:8704:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and make ye deed your members that vpon the erthe the which ben fornicacyon of your mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers &amp; vnclennes of foule deſyres with corrupte lykynge of fleſſhely luſtes and foule couetyce of your hertes / and auarice of gredy gatherynge whiche is ſeruice of ydolles and very ydolatry. For theſe thynges comethe the wrathe of god vpon the ſonnes of myſbeleue / yf ye ſectes for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſake thys lore / the wrathe of god ſhall ſone aſſayle you. The ſeconde reaſon that we ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken agaynſte ſuche buyldynges is ſayde thus / buſynes aboute ſuche coſtely buyldynges with many afolde worldly occupacyons to reparell them / when they payren and to holde them vp. In the ſame fourme bryngethe in neclygens of goſtelye maners quenchynge of vertues / and good thewes. As Bernarde ſayeth. That holye monke / that ſued the ſteppes of Ieſu Chryſt / and wolde not vary from the goſpell to blame theſe ſectes that gon awaye / I ſe (ſayde he) that maye not be ſeen / without great ſorrowe / many after that they be entred into the knyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode of Chryſt / that is to forſake thys worlde and wilfully ſuffre payneful lyuynge / efte they be drowned in worldly couetous and ben wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped / with worldly nedes and buſynes / they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vp walles but they ben neclygent in good thewes. what profytith it to haue hye temples and the walles all gylte with golde / where the ſpyryte of god wantethe. Forſothe god hathe no delyte in ſuche wretched ſynful ſectes.
<pb facs="tcp:8704:22"/>
But god wyll that our temples / the which ben our ſoules / to be honored with holy vertues &amp; laſte to thende in good workes. The thirde rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is myghty and ſtronge that ſpryngeth with other in goddes lawe / that ſuche as parte them by them ſelfe from common lyfe of other men / ſhulde be algates in thys waye as ſtrangers that ben far from home &amp; pylarymes in there pylgre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.<note place="margin">Hebre. 13.</note> As Paule ſayeth vnto thebrues. we haue here no dwellynge place or cite / but we ſeken that is to come. Lord howe dare theſe ſectes for ſhame with poore mennes goodes and pyllage of lordes defende this foule apoſtacye agaynſte theyr god &amp; holy ſaynctes &amp; tell the lewde peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by wordes of ypocreſy / that thus they do to god worſhyp / and this is doble wyckednes for Bernardꝰ ſayeth. we that ben in pylgremage of thys worlde / as abiecte &amp; outcaſt / ſhulde make no waſte houſes for to dwel in as lordes of this worlde / but lytle cottes to ſerue in and ſone to leue them &amp; go to blyſſe / <note place="margin">Barnard.</note> we ſeruen in a ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge contrey we trauelen in a ſtraunge countre. Thus ſayeth Bernarde. The fourthe reaſon and the laſt is full lyuely / and on this maner. Godes lawe chargeth on all wyſe to loue thy neybour as thy ſelfe / but this loue is leſt made knowen by good enſample of worde and dede / in what thynges may theſe ſectes profyte that reuerſen here Chriſtes rule / and geuen enſample to their neybour in proude and in falſe couetice &amp; ſhewen them rycheſt and moſt wordly in mete / cloth / &amp; in curious buyldynge / but thys forbedyth the
<pb n="xxiii" facs="tcp:8704:22"/>
doctour Bernarde whome we haue ofte reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed / forſothe (ſayth he) lowly houſes and poore refraynen the couetyſe of other / and we owen rather to meruell the greate workes of god / in the ſyght of heuen than in the ſight of buyldyng of mannes handy worke / and moche more we ſhulde meruayle the great workes of god than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> werkes of dedly men that duren but a whyle / <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> all holy ſaynctes accordynge in thys that our churche materyall that is ordeyned for pharyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhens where they come to geder ſhalbe made with vertuous meanes and in an honeſt meaſur. But on all ſydes it muſt be flede that in thys church ther ſhewe no pryde nor outrage paſſinge the bondes of pouertye / neyther in ſtone timbre nor lede / neyther in glaſſe lyme nor playſter / neyther in bell / lampe / nor lyght / neyther in chalice / boke / nor veſtyment / neyther in ſteple ſeetes / nor payntynge / nor in other ornamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that longen to thys churche. And diligently thys muſt be kept that they bowe to pouertye to eſchewe vayne glory of thys worlde / and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryfye the croſſe of god. But thys worde of Chriſtes croſſe is foly to hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhulde be damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned / that tenten to ſignes as commyn hoorys and leſen the vertue of theyr ſoules. Paule co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendythe the commynge of Chryſte / and the lowe mekynge in hys manhode. Forſoth (ſayth he) to the Corinthians. Ye owen to knowe the grace of our lorde Ieſu Chryſte / for whan he was riche in all thynges he was made poore in man for vs that ye ſhulde be ryche in goſtely
<pb facs="tcp:8704:23"/>
thinges thoroughe this vertuous nede of Chriſt. Chriſte that blameth all wanton meanes in the ſeruyce of hys people / wyll not authoryſe it hym ſelfe ne defende it in hys owne houſe / as ſaynct Math. 24. Marke. 13. Luce. 21. accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to gether in this one ſentence.<note place="margin">Mat. 24. Mar. 13. Luce. 21.</note> That when Ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> went out of the temple theyr p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ized him his dyſcyples for to ſhewe him the buyldynge ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of and the curious worke in ſtones wenyng thus to pleaſe theyr mayſter in ſeyng ſo fayre a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But Chryſte / that had an inwarde ſyght howe the deuelles brekynge hys lawe went a way with doleful chere and taught his diſcyples of thynges to come howe thys temple ſhulde be diſtroyed and bad hym beware that no man be gyle them / and ſore Chryſte wept vpon thys cyte for mannes buyldynge ſtode full ſtronge / both body &amp; ſoul that he had made to his owne dwellynge place were fall from kepynge of his lawe in to the ſwolowe of ſtynkynge ſynne. But ſcrybes and phareſeis were in cauſe of this greate myſchefe as Mathewe ſaythe wherfore Chryſte warned them as hys greateſt enemyes &amp; all ther folowers to the worldes ende Chriſt ſayth Math. 23.<note place="margin">Mat. 23.</note> wo to you ſcrybes and phare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeys that clenſen clene all that is outwarde / but certes within ye ben replete with muche ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyne and vnclennes / ye bylden the toumbys of holy ꝓphetes &amp; wonderly honoren there graues and ye ſue your fathers ſteppes in purſuynge of ryghtwyſe bloude / and theſe ſectes doo the
<pb n="xxiiii" facs="tcp:8704:23"/>
ſame but with more malice in worde and dede. O ye edders whelpes howe ſhall ye flee the iugement of hell / thus ſaythe our lorde Ieſu Chryſte wherto make ye ſhrynes to ſaynctes &amp; yet ye drawen hangen &amp; brenne them that hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the way of Chryſt and wandren after thys holye ſaynctes / and you ſhewe not in your outwarde dedes / ye done thys ſlaughter in worde and wyll / as phareſeys with byſſhopes in the thyrde houre foriudged our lorde with there tonges / and after knyghtes after the ſyxte houre hanged hys bodye vpon the croſſe. So theſe ſectes gone before to ſmyte the people with tonge / and after knyghtes of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodes houſe bene full redy to make an ende / but the cauſe of thys purſuyte ben two vycyous extremytees. One is temporall poſſeſſyon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wrongefully ſtandeth in preſtes handes. The othere is ſynnefull beggerye of myghty men / with huge byldynge of many waſte places / and nedes they muſte be amended by charyte of god for to ſaue theyr ſoules. For tho that maynteyne theſe .ij. outſtrayes bene full of many ſclaunders by teachynge of the deuyll of hel / leſt his retynewe forſake them / for than we ſhall fynde peace in erthe whan we kepe Chriſtes ordenaunce / and care nought / though thou be ſlaundrede / and thou leade a iuſte and perfyte lyfe to righten this myſſe put to thyne hande / &amp; thynke what Chriſt behitith Marc. 8.<note place="margin">Marc. 8.</note> who that hathe loſt hys lyfe for me and for the
<pb facs="tcp:8704:24"/>
goſpell. He ſhall make hys ſoull ſafe in the blyſſe of heuen. <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>⸫<g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of good and euyll comynge to this materyall churche. Capi. viii.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter thꝭ we ſhal ſpeake</hi> of two dyuerſe partyes that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to gether to thys churche bothe of good and yll. Fyrſt we taken for our grounde Chriſtes holy goſpell where he ſpekythe in a parable to his owne dyſcyples.<note place="margin">Math. 13.</note> Math. 13. The realme of heuen is lyke to a net that is ſent in to the ſee &amp; gatherith to geder of al the kynde of dyuerſe fyſſhes / and whan thys net was full of fyſſhes the fyſſhers drewe it to the lande &amp; they ſyttynge beſyde the ſee brynke / choſe the good into theyr veſſelles / the yuell they ſente out and kept them agayne in the ſee. This para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is thus to meane after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyt of Ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt. Seconde churche here in erthe is lyke to a net ſenden into the ſee for as the ſee ebbith and flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth. So thys churche nowe ryſeth and falleth to prayſe / for as the tempeſtes of the ſee ben hydeous &amp; perylous for the nette.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">☞Pryde.</note>☞ So Pryde that wauith in thys worlde is full noyous to Chryſtes church. Of beawty of fortune / of goodes / of grace / all day men bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen in hyenes of herte.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">☞Enuye.</note>☞The ſee water is full bytter and full fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſſhe in the caſtynge / and thys worlde is full
<pb n="xxv" facs="tcp:8704:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of enuy that is full bytter for to taſt with hate as the ſoote that none vnnyth can acorde with other / and ouer the ſee cometh greuous ſtormes with pyryes that greuen ſore.</p>
               <p>☞And in thys worlde ryſeth wrath with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of herte that doth moche tene / <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> wrathe.</note> in the ſee no graſſe may growe neyther as farre as it maye flowe / but it waſtyth all the grounde &amp; maketh it naked without fruyte.</p>
               <p>☞ And in this worlde is vicious ſlowthe that ſtroyeth vertues in body and ſoule / <note place="margin">Slowthe.</note> and maketh man foltyd in hys wyttes in euery parte where ſo euer he ſtreche: the ſee ay purchaſeth with his waues / &amp; wynnith of grounde that he neghith / and is not apayed of the termes that god hathe ſette yf it myght ſcape.</p>
               <p>☞And in this worlde is couetyſe of them that purchaſyn with wrong theyr neyboures grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; catteles with ſleyght cautyls of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes lawe.<note place="margin">Couetyſe.</note> Thus they wynnen more and more / and wyll not wyſely ſpende theyr owne / neyther thanke god in due fourme tyll they be caught in the fendes ſnare. The ſee belchith vp moche fylthe and caſtyth from it moche corrupcyon / and that is full abhomynable and lothely to loke vpon.</p>
               <p>☞And in thys worlde is lechery that defou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth body and ſoull / <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>Lechery</note> it tourneth the precyous temple of god into the lodge of gryſely deuyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les / the people that haunteth this wretched ſyn ben maden as beſtes without lawe / and in thys beſtely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicyon they fyghten as beſtes without reaſon / &amp; there they walken and twynen away
<pb facs="tcp:8704:25"/>
all lothſumly to god and man. The ſee fell ſythes with his great tempeſtes drowneth man and alſo veſſelles / &amp; loſeth them or they come to londe. ☞ <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Glotony.</note>☞ And in thys worlde is glotony that drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the wyttes of the people tyll that they be vnreaſonable &amp; can not knowe when they haue wronge. Certes exceſſe of meate and drynke ſleyth many mo than dothe the ſwerde. For in diuers meates &amp; drynkes gredyly taken at mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les is none heale but ſickenes / as the wyſe man ſayth / both body and ſoul / we muſt eſpye to fle theſe perelles that ben in thys greuous ſee / and draw this net in water of wiſdome by vertuous lyuynge to the hauen of helth with cordes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ben of very mekenes / with pacience / and with long abydyng / ſaylynge with loue &amp; charyte in holy ſpede &amp; good occupacyon / largynge our handes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dedes of mercy &amp; pyte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> poore nedy may be our bedmen / ledyng our lyfe in diſcrete meaſure / in what y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhall take or leue / clad in clennes &amp; chaſtite.<note place="margin">Math. 28. Ero vobiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>m vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>quam</ex>
                     </expan> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ionem ſecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> And than ſhal Chriſt be al our comforte where euer we be by londe or water as he hathe grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by his goſpel Mat. 28. ſayeng I ſhalbe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you in wele &amp; wo / tyl this world be brought to an ende. The fyſſhes ſwymmen in this water be al the people that be in this world both good &amp; yuell in euery degree / of eche ſtate or dignyte. But as the great fyſſhes eaten y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmale ſo might<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty ryche men of this world deuouren the poore vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bare bone eatynge the morſelles that the beſt lyketh / as the wyſe man ſayth Eccle. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.
<pb n="xxvi" facs="tcp:8704:25"/>
The huntyng or the pray of the lyon is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fylde as in wylderneſſe / ſo the fedynge of rychemen ben poore nedy. And when the ſonne ſhyneth warme in a mery ſeaſon the great fyſſhes dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen nyghe the ayre / &amp; dryuen downe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmall / and yf ther come any hayle / ſtorme or any colde weder theſe great fyſſhes fallen to ground / and putten aboue the ſmal. So whan ryche me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeen any worldly wynnyg they ryſen hye aboue the clowdes in vauntyng of theyr riches / and alſo lacken the ſymple co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myns &amp; ſeye that they may not paye / wherfore do they entermete them / they ben but very beggers / but whan there co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>- a charge to the countre / as taxis or any other payme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / than the ryche man fallyth downe and fayneth hym ſelfe nedy / and magnifyeth the poore man that wonneth beſyde them ſayenge / he is a preuy man / and hydeth moche ryches. And thus ſayth almyghty god by the prophete Abacuc. 1. The ꝓphete ſayth i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpirite how ryche e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m waſten the poore nedy / he taketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voyce of great mone &amp; maketh his mournyng to hys god. Lorde what ſhalte ſuffre men to be made as fyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes that ſwymmen in the ſee / &amp; as they were crepyng beſtes that haue no leder here in erthe / and iugement is made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crueller / &amp; agaynſeyng the mightyer / wherfore the law is al to torne / and iugement commeth to no perfyt ende / for nought hathe the wycked wretche myght / to ouercome the wyſe man / and therfore paſſeth forth amonge mankynde weywarde iugemente
<pb facs="tcp:8704:26"/>
that diſtroyeth peace / but for that fyſſhes ben ryght quyuour and quycke in plenty of the water / &amp; dreden not the hydeous waues / whether they ryſen hye or low. In this place they ſhalbe taken as to ſyanyfye the true beleue of mannes herte. And to thys wytte ſpekith Chriſte in hys goſpell and ſteryth vs to pray.<note place="margin">Luce. 11.</note> Luce. 11. For ſothe (ſayth Chriſt) which of you aſketh my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a fyſſhe / whether nowe ſhall he geue them for a fyſſhe an adder? nay playnly. Chriſoſtome ſayth vpon this texte / that this fyſſhe is man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes fayth / and after this we ſhulde pray to our father that is in heuen that he wold ſtable vs in true beleue and in the articles therto / for than we ſhalbe dyſpoſed in the water of tribulacyon to do and ſuffre as pleaſith god ioyenge for this beleue / and though there ſeme peryls of dethe I conſcience ſhall nothynge abaſſhe / for ſocour is kept for al faythful in the treſure of Chriſtes paſſyon. The fyſſhers that drawen thys forſaid net are ſent afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dome / that ſhullen weyght<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly do goddes meſſage and brynge all folkes by fore the face of godallmyghty in to the vale of Ioſophat.<note place="margin">Iohel. 3.</note> Iohel. 3. The lorde god ſayth that he ſhal gather to geder al folkes &amp; he ſhal lede them into the vale of Ioſophat / &amp; ther he ſhall make with them a ryghtwyſe reckenynge vpon hys people / Iſrael / that is his owne heritage / and than ſhall Chriſte with his ſayntes departe the yll from the good Chryſt cheſith the good of his churche into the veſſell of blys / but the uyel are caſten out into the chymnye of fyre ther ſhalbe
<pb n="xxvii" facs="tcp:8704:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
wepynge for bytternes of ſmoke / and gnaſtyng of tethe for quakynge of colde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Of diſcrecyon to knowe good from yuell. Cap. ix.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O man deſcriuith theſe</hi> two partyes veryliche from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wandrynge in this ſeconde churche / for lykenes that they vſen / and alſo they haue in com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon many heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly thinges. For our lorde hath in his churche / labourers aboute hys vynetre / both faſters / prayers / and alſo wakers / almyſdoers ben in thys churche / with preachours / and reders of leſſons / and ſyngers trauelen here alſo / with miniſters of ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes with ſtudyers in goddes lawe / &amp; men that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken loue dayes / and lyke ſeruauntes hathe the fende in the thyrde churche / but they doo theyr ſeruyce in a ſtraunge maner / neuertheles they ben harde to knowe. Therfore we ſhall marke them howe wonderfully they varyen in theſe forſayd conditions / certes / faſters in Chriſtes churche abſteyne them from luſtes for to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the coragis of the rebell fleſhe &amp; kepe theyr body clene / chaſt / &amp; ſubiecte to there ſoule. For ſayncte Auſtyn techith this lore. Thy body le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyth of thy ſoule / the ſoule hathe her lyuynge of the god / the body liueth ryghtfully after the ſoule whan the ſoule lyueth after god / god is our ſouerayne good / and our ſoule a great good:
<pb facs="tcp:8704:27"/>
that lyueth bytwext the ſouerayne good / and our body a lytle good for it is goddes creature / therfore it is cleped a lytle good / forſothe the ſoule is not debytrice to lyue after the fleſſhe / but euen on contrary wyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe muſt nede be mortyfyed / and whan thou leueſt ſoule deſires than thy fleſſhe is mortyfyed. This is the dede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhall do. This is the offyce of our knyght<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hode.<note place="margin">☞Auſten.</note> Thus ſayth Auſten. But faſters i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſendes church faſten for vngrou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded cauſes. Some faſten for ipocreſye &amp; ſheweth them rufull to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſuche Chriſt blameth by his goſpel &amp; clepith them ſorowfull hypocrytes Math. 6.<note place="margin">Math. 6. Cum ieni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>atis nolite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eti ſicut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>pocrite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſtes.</note> For all the vayne prayſyng of mannes mouth they haue receyued all theyr mede. Some withdrawen from theyr wombe bothe mete and drynke / to ſpare theyr purſe. And Gregory ſaythe that thys faſtynge is for theyr ſachell / and not for god / and this is a carefull faſtynge to payne our fleſſhe and leſe our mede as the wyſe man ſayth Eccle. 6.<note place="margin">Eccle. 6.</note> He ſawe vnder the ſonne a nother yuel that is full ryue and commen amonge the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple / a man that god hathe gyuen ryches with catell and moche worſhyp / and nothynge fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth hys lyfe of all that he deſyeryth / but then wantyth grace and power to eate or to take hys parte therof / but a man that is a ſtraunger ſhall deuoure hit after hys day / but thys is a vanyte and great wretchednes. Some faſten for a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycyne to gete them bodyly helth / neyther for god nor for theyr ſoule / but for to clenſe theyr beawtye.<note place="margin">Ierome.</note> Saynct Ierom blameth this faſtyng / 
<pb n="xxviii" facs="tcp:8704:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and ſaythe. Abſtynence of body is clere to god whan the mynde faſtethe from vyces what profytyth hit to tere the bodye with hungre whan the mynde within ſwelleth with pryde. what faſtynge is thys to withdrawe / lyflode and to be wode in enuy or foole haſtyte. God ſaythe by the prophete Yſaye. Lo whan ye faſten ye make ſtryfe and debates amonge your ſelfes. Thys is not the faſtynge that I choſe ſay the god the Lorde / and ſythen the fende ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer eatythe ne drynkyth / neyther is lapped in precyous clothes / yet he ſhalbe euer in payne for them lackyth charyte. Than is thys an euydence / that all ſuche faſters bene members in the fendes churche in folowynge theer fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers prayers that bene in Chryſtes churche prayeng with deuocyon / with al theyr ſtrength of herte and of mouthe / accordynge / knockynge with a perfyte dede / after helpe of god / of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and forgyueneſſe of tyme myſpended / and after grace and gouernaunce for tyme that is preſent / and for good contynuaunce of tyme that is to come / freſſhely bryngynge to mynde the kyndeneſſe of theyr god / howe he hathe ruled them in thys lyfe / and kepte them from myſchyefe as thoughe he had no mo but one / ſo he ſaueth all that louen them. That they thynken of foule ſynnes and fele that they haue done bothe wyttyngly and wylfully agaynſte goddes wyll they haue ben recheles on his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices and that them rueth ſore / and whan they thinken on this world howe ſodenly it paſſeth / 
<pb facs="tcp:8704:28"/>
and of the tourmentes of hell / that dampned ſoules ſhall ſuffre / and on the blyſſe that god hath ordeyned for his trewe ſeruauntes anone they fynden a waſſhynge well that ſpryngeth from theyr herte and renneth forth from theyr eyen by many warme ſtremes / <note place="margin">Gregorye.</note> as Gregorye ſayeth. Than we fynden rendles of waters / when we wepen for all our ſynnes to waſſhe clene bothe body and ſoule / and clenſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from corrupcyon. But prayers in the fendes churche maken muche noyſe / mumlynge with theyr lyppes they rekkenen what / ſo that men prayſe faſt theyr fayned occupation as Chryſt ſayth in hys goſpel. This people worſhyppeth me with theyr lyppes / but theyr herte is farre awaye from me. Lorde whan thy body is in the churche &amp; thyne herte be in the worlde or cumbred with vnclene thoughtes &amp; with fantaſyes / and thy tonge with mynſtrelſy on lewde iangelynge / &amp; thy wytte ouercome with ſeculer nedes. Arte thou not then wrechydly dyuyded in thy ſelfe. Saynct Iames ſaith.<note place="margin">☞Iames.</note> Suppoſe not this vayne man / that he may take any thynge of the lord / he may in no wyſe be herde in prayer that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freth his herte to ſlepe in ſynne / and efte god ſayeth by Yſaye in generall wordes to wycked ſynners. wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye haue multiplyed your prayers I ſhall not here you graciouſly / and the cauſe why is thus / for your handes be ful of bloude / that is / your workes be ful of ſyn / that partyn you and me atwyne / thus ſayth the lord god / but wete ye welye vycyous preſtes that gone
<pb n="xxix" facs="tcp:8704:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
from the lorde in vycyous lyuynge and wyll not folowe hys holy ſteppes but tarynge them from day to day / therfore your prayers ben diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſed as Chriſt ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can not lye. Mat. 24.<note place="margin">Mat. 24.</note> wo to you ſcribes and pharyſes ypocrites that eaten the houſes of wedowes by longe prayers for thys thynge ye ſhulde take the larger iuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Vpon thys ſayth Criſoſtome / the ſleyght or the wyles of ypocrytes women may not only knowe / &amp; bycauſe of theyr relygyon / they wyl ſone bowe to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for they be neſſhe. Thys doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour makyth two ſpecyal cauſes why they dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen to wydowes howſes. One is for women y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ben wedded &amp; vnder the power of mannes daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger dare nat geue theſe worldly goodes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>outen cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayle of their huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. And other wedowes ben ful of pyty / to geue when they be petiouſly aſked / &amp; haue no man to werne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this dede for her good is at her owne wyll / &amp; for thys ende / theſe flaterynge gloſers moſt haunten wedowes howſes. Chriſte wyſſheth them wo / &amp; warneth our preſtes that they forſake thys ſynneful ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner / for it is a curſyd dede to hyde ſynne vnder paynted relygyon / and clothe wyckednes vnder ypocreſye / tyll it be trowed for very pety / and in the armour of Ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chryſte. They done the fendes workes of hell / whan they largen there longe prayers as nettes that bene ſprede abrode and with crafte they catchen awaye the goodes of theſe ſely wydowes. Theſe wydowes we ſhulde vnderſtande / both for woman and for me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wanten wyſdome of Ieſu Chriſt / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which
<pb facs="tcp:8704:29"/>
is ſpouſe of mannes ſoull. For Ieſu nowe here delytyth but in them that louen his lawe. wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers that ben in Chriſtes church / waken in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue &amp; deuout prayers / and auoyden all dyuyſes for they wyll not be negligent / but holden and waken there inwarde eye that faythfully ſeeth the workes of god / &amp; then riſeth vp. As ſayncte Paule ſayth. A newe man fourmed after god / &amp; ſhineth them in theſe thre vertues / rightwyſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / truthe / and holynes. This is wakynge to goddes worſhyp &amp; to theyr owne ſaluacion / &amp; to ꝓfyte of theyr euen chriſten. For thus meaneth Paul in theſe .iij. wordes. Thys watche ſo cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he fleeth from all ſuch wakers / &amp; hath no might for to noye body ne ſoule / as the wyſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth. The holſome watche of honeſty ſhal make the fleſſhe melte from ſyn / and buſy thought in this fayre watche ſhal dryue awaye vnleful dremes. Certes the thought of the fore knowynge turneth awaye the wyt from ſyn &amp; a great infirmite makyth a ſobre ſoull. But wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers in the fendes churche vſen a foule fleſſhly watche / for euer they ben ſlombryng when any good dede is gone / &amp; is ouercome with ſlepe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bryngeth them to myſchyefe / for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyſeman ſayth. Howe longe ſhalt thou ſlepe thou ſhlowe man / whan ſhalt thou ryſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy ſlepe? Thou ſhalt nappe a lytle whyle / thou ſhalt ſlumber a lytle whyle / thou ſhalt knyt thy handes to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der tyll thou fall into dead ſlepe / and than ſhall come to the nede / as a wayfayrynge man and pouertye ſhall ſtele to the as an armyd man / 
<pb n="xxx" facs="tcp:8704:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
nappynge / and ſlumbrynge / &amp; daed ſlepe ben y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fendes offycers. Than men nappen whan they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſenten to do the fendes ſtirynge / &amp; whan they wyrchen openly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fende deſyreth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyght of the worlde / than they ben in ſlombrynge. But whan they maynteyne boldly what euer they done amys / than they ben in deed ſlepe / &amp; waken in theyr ſynnes / changynge the nyght vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day / as horys &amp; theues trauelyng from place to place to reuel &amp; to rout / aſſayeng wher with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may leue tokenes of theyr ſyn. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſdoers in Chriſtes church releuen i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> due tyme w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the plenty of theyr catel them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuffren nede as ſaynct Paule ſayth. Loke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your habundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce fulfyll the nede of other / for ye thus doynge ſhallen receyue the bleſſyng of god / as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝓphete ſayth. Bleſſed be he that taketh hede on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nedy &amp; poore. Vpon this ſayth Bernarde. Not vpon the couetous man &amp; the proude / but vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nedy and poore / that is to wyte / thoſe that aſken conſtrayned with nede / &amp; take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thyr almes with ſhame geuyng tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes to god &amp; lyue poorely ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by. In foure thynges goddes ſeruauntes mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully done theyr almes. Firſt / they ſeken godes wil &amp; done it to his worſhip. The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of true goten good clerely in theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience. The .iij. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they knowe theyr brother lyue in gracious lyfe. The .iiij. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſuffreth nede w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>outen any fayning for yf any of theſe faylen / they leſe both good &amp; mede. But almyſdoers in the fendes churche feden many wretches / as ſtronge ſtyffe beggers y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtrykes ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lande / &amp; groners without cauſe than neden not of theyr good / ye to mynſtrels
<pb facs="tcp:8704:30"/>
iuglers and other vayne iapers / that they delen largely theyr goodes to &amp; cleppen it an almes / but trewe men ſeynge all a mys goodes thus ſpended / for it draweth them to heuen / as a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket into the well / and yf they do any thynge there as nede is / anone they ſeken vayne glory: &amp; leſe all there mede.<note place="margin">☞ Iſedor</note> For ſaynct Iſodor ſayth. whan the poore man is fedde bycauſe of vayne glory than is the worke of mercy tourned into ſynne / as Chriſt ſaith Luce. 11. yf thyne eye ben aweywarde / all thy body ſhalbe derke / thyn eye is thyn entent that ſhuld rule thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience / and this body is thy worke of entent taketh his lyght. Than it is thus to meane / whan thyne ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is not wel ruled thou geteſt no mede what euer thou do / prechours that ben in Chryſtes churche / commen frely amonge the people as Chryſte came from the toure of heuen and gaue this charge to hys diſcyples. Frely ye haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken your wyſdome.<note place="margin">☞ Paule.</note> Frely geue it agayne. Paul choſe rather to be deed / than any man ſhulde auoyde hys glorye for mede that myght be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen or taken agayne the goſpel of Ieſu Chriſt / and theſe preachours prechen to edifyethe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in vertues / as Chriſte commaunded on ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thurſday to hys diſcyples afore the ſtyenge / Mathewe vltimo.<note place="margin">☞Math. vltimo.</note> Ye goynge forth into all the worlde preche ye the goſpell to eche creature / that is to eche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is chefely eche creature / and they lyuen vertuouſly them ſelfe after their prechynge / for to ſtreyght theyr holy wordes / with the ſpiryte of life / whan they geuen a true
<pb n="xxxi" facs="tcp:8704:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
enſample in dede after theyr ſayenge / and thys is the techynge of Ieſu Chryſt in the goſpell of ſayncte Mathewe. Loke your lyght ſhyne ſo afore men of this world / that they may ſe your good workes and gloryfye not you but your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that is in heuen / of whome commeth all your grace. But prechers in the fendes churche prechen vnder colour for to take gyftes. But Gregory reproueth them ſayenge. who ſo euer preche for goodes of this worlde or to make a gatheryng for ſuch an heuenly office vndowted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they pryuen them ſelfe from the mede that is to come of euerlaſtynge rewarde / and they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chen cronycles with poyſes and dremynges and many other helpeles tales / that ryght nought auaylen. They clouten falſhed to truthe / with moche vngrounded mater tarynge the people from true beleue that they may nat knowe it / and theſe preachers waueren aboute in many fleſſhely luſtes as Iude ſaith.<note place="margin">☞Iude.</note> Theſe ben ſpottes in theyr meates / feaſtynge / and fedynge them ſelfe withouten drede / worſhyppynge the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones of men / for they wolde haue wynnynge / reders in Chriſtes churche reden holy leſſons / and tenden to theyr redynge with medefull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotyon as Iierom ſaythe. So rede thou holye wryt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer thou haue in mynde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tho wordes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou redyſt ben goddes law / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded it not only to be rede / but alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the readers ſhuld kepe it in theyr workes: what ꝓfiteth it to rede thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to be done / &amp; not to fulfyll them in dede? as a clene myrrour of life the leſſon of holy wryt is
<pb facs="tcp:8704:31"/>
to be reade &amp; had / that all that is good / may be made better / &amp; that this yuel may be amended / &amp; theſe reders reden dyſtynctly / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is treatable &amp; openly in ſcripture withouten interrupcyon / or any faynyd intermiſſion / without corruptynge or ouerhippyng of letter / worde / or ſillable &amp; they ſhal accorde in charyte &amp; do all thynges in ordre. But reders in the fendes church Iangle theyr leſſons as iayes chatteren in the cage / and wote not what they meane / ſtryuing with them for nought eche agaynſt other / for rules of ther ordynall and many vayne queſtions / and if they vnderſtanden the leſſon whan it is reade or any parte of godes lawe / whan it is declared ſone they treden it vnder the fote / and haten it in theyr workes / as Ieremy the prophete ſayth in wytneſſynge agaynſt all ſuche / howe may ye ſaye (ſaythe Ieremy) we bene wyſe and the lawe / and the lawe of the lorde is amonge vs. Certes the falſe ſtyle of the ſcrybes hathe wrought opyn leſynge / and your wyſe men / bene confounded and aferde / and caſte in theyr owne ſnare / they haue throwen abacke the worde of the lorde / there is no wyſdome leaſte amonge them / and efte god ſaythe by Ieremy to the veyne reders. Curſyd be he that dothe the worke of god fraudulently / that is to ſay-falſely or diſceyuable. And here ſayth Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Onely in goddes ſeruyce that man do no fraude that wakyth full buſyly in ſtudy of good dede and neyther boweth to medes of bodylye thyng / nor ſeketh the wordes of mannes lewde
<pb n="xxxii" facs="tcp:8704:31"/>
prayſynge / nor loketh after the fauour of a fou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les iugement. Syngers ben in Chriſtes church that ſyngen heuenly ſonges &amp; with theyr ſwete melody pleaſen god at the full / <note place="margin">☞Paule.</note> as Paule ſayth in his pyſtle to the Colo. Suffre ye the worde of god to dwell plenteouſly amonge you in all maner heuenly wyſdome / encreſynge you in vertue / techynge and moneſtynge your ſelfe / in pſalmes and ympnes &amp; goſtely ſonges ſyngynge in grace with feruent deuotion in your hertes to your god / and what euer ye ſhal do in worde or worke do ye that thyng perfytly in the name of our lorde Ieſu Chryſt / yeldynge thankynges to the fader by the ſame Ieſu Chriſte. And ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then he is bothe god and lorde and kynge of all the worlde. The prophete Dauyd counſeyleth vs that we ſhulde ſynge wyſely. For he that is occupyed in heuenly deſyres / though his tonge be ſtyll &amp; make no noyſe. He ſyngeth a ſonge / ſayth / ſayncte Auſtyne / that lyketh god beſt.<note place="margin">Auſtyn.</note> Ananye / &amp; Azarye / &amp; Mizael alſo ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gen bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſonge to the lorde in ſuche maner ſong when they weren in Babylon in the bournynge ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys. But ſyngers in the fendes church broken curyous notes / &amp; that is but a puffe of wynde / As ſayth ſayncte Bernarde wyſely / to pleaſe the people with lykerous voyce / and fyll theyr eares with veyne de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. But ſe what ſainct Gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gory ſaith which accordith with ſaynct Barnard whan fayre &amp; gloſyng voyce is ſought / parfyte lyfe is forſaken / and the people is ledde into
<pb facs="tcp:8704:32"/>
ſynne / <note place="margin">Ezechi. 33.</note> as god ſayth by his ꝓphete / Ezechiel. 33. My people ſytten afore the and heren thy wordes / but they do not after them / whan there backe is tourned / for the preſtes turnen them in ſonge of theyr mouth / and the hertes of the people folowe theyr preſtes auarice / and is to them as a ſonge of muſyke / that is ſongen buſyly / and meryly with a luſty ſounde / and they heren the ſermons / but they kepen them not / ſayth the lorde god / and efte god ſayth by hys ꝓphete Amos.<note place="margin">☞Amos.</note> Do away from me the pryde of thy chauntynge / and I ſhall not here y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonge of thyne harpe. Lord what may this meane that preſtes in theyr churche gyue them ſelfe thys moche to ſonge / and ſo lytle to prechynge / and in fewe places or none of the newe teſtamente ſhullen we grounde thys maner of ſonges / ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther among our doctours / but efte they ben char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged to preache / ye vnder great payne / and all gates that they haue good wyll to do that they may that the people were truly taught to lede a ſober lyfe. Therfore Gregory in hys decree ſmyteth them with a curſe that buſyen them in the courte of Rome aboute ſuche ſyngyng where ſhuld be vſed the office of prechynge / myniſters of ſacramentes that ben in Chriſtes churche be thynken them full beſyly of the great worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Howe theſe ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mmen of Chriſt / and of his holy paſſyon taken of his bleſſed body for treaſour of his churche / and they ben ſalue and medycyne for all the ſycke members tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wol ſhewe theyr great ſores / to goddes preſtes
<pb n="xxxiii" facs="tcp:8704:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of wyſe diſcrecyon / and vſe theſe ſacramentes in theyr kynde. As ſaynct Paule techeth Chriſt (ſayth he) is offered our paſke that noryſſheth vs with his ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / and therfore make we vs mery in this goſtely foode / not in angre and tene of malyce and wyckednes. But in the fayre pured paſt of clennes and of trouthe. Theſe two vertues techen vs to clenſe body &amp; ſoule / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that we ſhulde geue or receyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeuen ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes / baptyſme / confermyng / penaunce / ordre / Chriſtes body / Matrymony / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt anoyntynge. Theſe helpen vs in this fightynge churche agayne the ſeuen dedly ſinnes / that ben vij. cruell deuylles. The fyrſt is Lucyfer / that raignyth in his malyce / &amp; ruleth ouer the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of pryde. The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de is called Belzabub / that lordeth ouer enuyous. The thyrde deuyll is Sathanas / &amp; wrathe is his lordſhyp. The fourthe is clepyd Abadon / the ſlowe ben his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynewe. The fyfte deuyll is Mammon / &amp; hath vnder hym the auarous and the couetous. The ſyxt is called Belphagor that is the god of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons. The .vij. deuyll is Aſmodeus / that ledeth with him the lecherous. But tho .vij. ſacrametes caſten out theſe deuylles from the ſeruauntes of god that receyuen them medefully and ſtablen them in .vij. geftes of the holy goſte. But my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſters in the fendes church mynyſtren theſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes and treten them vnworthely / and al ſuche both lerned and lewde ben Iudas goſtely chyldren / for he toke the ſacrament at Chriſtes holy ſouper / where Chriſte dealed his body in
<pb facs="tcp:8704:33"/>
brede / as other apoſteles dyden &amp; dranke with them his blode in wyne / but with a vicious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience / wherfore the deuyll entred in them / &amp; he betrayed hys lorde. Thus it is with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fendes chyldren / whan they receyue the ſacramentes they gone to them vnworthyly / and ſo to theyr dampnacyon. Some with polluted handes and with a ſtynkynge careyne / as Pariſens ſayth / and reherſyth Auſtyne. He that is on the nyght a louer of Lechery / and on the morowe a ſacrar of the vyrgyns ſonne / god tourneth away hys eares from ſuch mennes prayers. Many fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full doctours forbeden ſtraytly to take any ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes of ſuche preſtes handes / but nowe it is and euer ſhalbe to the worldes ende. Fooles fynden conuentycles that haſten them to hell / ſome that ben as ſymondes heyres / that ſellen theſe ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / and ſome be redy with theyr money as chapeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in afayre to bye of theſe mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chans marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyſe / meryte / as ther wene / but both the byers &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſellers deſerue endeles payne Some ſayen / haue here my money for chriſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of my chylde. Some ſayen / haue here this money and aſſoyle me of my ſynnes. Some ſayen / haue here this money / and ſynge for me a maſſe. Some ſayen / haue here thys money for thou haſt made this maryage. Some ſayen / haue here thys money and ſacra me to preſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode. Some ſayen / haue here thys money for thou haſte ofte vyſyted me. Some ſayen / haue thys money / and good ſyr pray for me. Some maken letters for ſoteller ypocryſye / to ſell all
<pb n="xxxiiii" facs="tcp:8704:33"/>
theyr ſuffrages where euer they fynde theyr chapemen that wol pay largely therfore. Than is the bargayne made. Lorde howe ſtudyen theſe fendes lemes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> decre. Saluator? or godes law / or the Actes of the apoſteles where ſuche mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandyſe is dampned. For thus it is ſayed of cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed Symon. Forſothe when Symon Magus had ſeen that by touchyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſteles handes the holy goſte was geuen to the people / he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feryd them money ſaynge. Geue to me alſo this power y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> who ſo euer I touche with my handes may receyue the holy goſte. Forſothe than ſayde Peter vnto hym. Thy money be with the for vs / take it thy ſelfe to thy dampnacion for thou troweſt the gyfte of god to be ſette to ſale for money / there is no parte ne lot to the in thys ſermon of god. Than theſe that we haue marked afore in this ben the very heires of Simon / for they wene whan they haue money to graunt to the people theſe goſtely gyftes / and Symon is dampned and all hys folowers: howe moche more theſe curſed takers? For yf ſaynct Peter had taken thys money he had geuen leue to vſe ſymony. But Peter forſoke and blamyd thys man / and put a rule that ſhall laſte / and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſethe and dampneth bothe gyuers and takers for bothe partyes bene ſymonyake. Ones Iudas made a couenaunte with the Iewes / for thryttye plates / and ſolde hys mayſter / Ieſu Chryſte / betrayenge hys bodye into theyr handes whan he came chefely to dye / and hys dethe was our redempcyon / therfore hys
<pb facs="tcp:8704:34"/>
name is curſed Iudas / and well worthy for his falſe trayne. But his chyldren do moche more were that ſellen the ſacramentes / and that for leſſe pryce / that ben vndedely and mowt not ſuffer neyther any profyt cometh of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſale / but vengeaunce here or elles wher. Alas whan woll theſe wretches be ware? Studyers in Chriſtes church ſtudyen day and nyght in the lawe of the lord / as the prophete ſayth. Bleſſed be that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hath his wyll in the lawe of the lorde / for he ſhalbe as a tree that is wiſely plantyd beſyde the courſe of waters that ſhall geue frute in hys due tyme / and his lefe that is his vertue / ſhall not fall away / but all thynge that he ſhall do / in grace ſhullen be welthy. well is them that ſo may ſtudye to fynde theſe precyous vertues / to make fayre their owne ſoule with the flowre of holy wryt. Than Chriſt wyll take his reſtynge place in the chambre of theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences / for the wyſema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith. My flowers ben flowers of wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhyp and honeſtye. And therfore ſaynct Ierom / cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeyleth in his prologe vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byble. I pray the dere brother / <note place="margin">Ierome.</note> ſayth Ierome / that thou haue thy ſtudy / &amp; thy mynde amonge the leſſons that ben in holye wryt. Buſy the nothynge elles to knowe. Buſy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nothyng elles to ſeke / ſet thyne herte in holy ſtudye / and purſue after with all thy myght &amp; thou ſhalt fynde it in ſhort whyle more ſweter than the honycomb as the wyſema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth. Haue thy thought in goddes heſtes / and in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes be thou moſt buſy / and he ſhall graunte an herte to the / and a luſte of
<pb n="xxxv" facs="tcp:8704:34"/>
wyſdome ſhalbe geuen to the. But ſtudyers in the fendes churche / ſtudyen in theyr maden lawes / all for ryches &amp; for pryde and for theyr worldly worſhyp. Yea ſo ferforthe that vnneth any man is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den that abydeth in goddes law / clene without medelynge / but draweth them to mannes lawe for that ſmatcheth wynnyng / and theyr they ſtudyen ſad and ſore. But at theyr laſt ende this ſhalbe theyr payme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / as god ſaith by Ieremy.<note place="margin">Ieremy.</note> Curſyd mote that man be that ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyth his fayth in man / and puttyth hys truſte and ſtrength in mannes maden ordynaunces and ſuffreth theyr herte to departe away from hys lord god. Certes this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe as a brome that groweth in wyldernes / and he ſhall not ſe in inwarde ſyght / whan that good of the ſoul ſhal come to them / but he ſhall dwell in drynes in the londe of wyldernes / thus ſayth the lorde god. Such men ſclaundren Chriſte that is bothe god and man and hath halowed his bothe lawes with hys precyous dethe / and put in them the ſpyryte of lyfe by quyckenynge of his blode / to rere ſoules from deth / and brynge them agayne to lyfe as the goſpell telleth. Iohi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. 11.<note place="margin">Iohi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. 11.</note> where Chriſte ſayth. who ſo euer beleueth on me / yea thoughe he be deed / neuertheles he ſhall lyue agayne both in grace and glory. But this is not in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes lawe that may geue this power. Than is this afoule ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre of theſe wayward fooles that thus ſtudyen in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes lawe / and if it were the / and therfore ſuche frowarde thoughtes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parten their ſoule from god. Of al thoſe ſpekith
<pb facs="tcp:8704:35"/>
Ieremy / and ſayth of them full ſharpely. From the leaſte vnto the moſte all ſtudyen vnto coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe that is to vnderſtande of them that ben in the fendes churche / ferre from the preacher all worke gyfe / therfore they ſhullen fal amonge them that fallen / they ſhall fall in tyme of vyſitacyon ſayth the lorde god. God reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyth thys ſentence agayne / for we ſhulde take hede therto. But for they wol not amende their ſtudyes / and tourne theyr thoughtes to god. Therfore god wyſſheth them wo / and ſaythe this by the prophete Mycheas. wo to you that thynke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyng that is vnprofytable and wur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chen euyl in your ſtudyes. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morowe lyght / Peacemakers in Chriſtes churche mouen men to reſte / that Chriſt behyte to his dyſcyples whan he was amonge them.<note place="margin">Io. 14.</note> Iohi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. xiiij. My peace (ſayth Chryſte) I geue you / my peace I leue with you. His peace he lefte with vs whan he wente to heuen / his peace he ſhal geue vs / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the world ſhall haue his ende / hys peace he be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toke vs / to helpe vs in this world / his peace he grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to vs / to ſolace vs in bliſſe / he hath left vs his peace to be our truſty clothyng / for if we be clade therin / we ſhal ouercome our enemyes he ſhal graunt vs his peace / &amp; we ſhalbe ſuer to reigne without ende / without any enemyes / he hath left vs his peace / that we deme not falſely of our neyghboure in thynges that ben vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne / he ſhall geue to vs hys peace / whan he ſhall make open the preuytees of mannes herte / and than ſhalbe prayſynge to euery man of hys god / after he hathe deſerued. Chryſte
<pb n="xxxvi" facs="tcp:8704:35"/>
hath lefte amonge vs peace / that we ſhulde loue togeder / hatynge ſynne and louynge vertue / for thus he loued vs / for there is no charyte / but yf ſynne be hated &amp; rented vp by the rootes in vs and in all other / than ſhall Chryſte geue vs full peace / where we may neuer dyſcorde. Thus ſayth ſayncte Auſtyn vpon the ſame goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell / that is afore reherſed. Nowe grounde we it in our mynde / theſe Peacemakers for they wold haue thys very peace among them ſtanden armed at all pecys for dreade of theyr enemyes / in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> armour of Ieſu Chryſt. That ſaynct Paule techeth to the Epheſyans / in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyxth chapiter / wher he reherſyth ſyxe armours that armen the ſoule / fyue for to defende / with the ſyxt for to aſſayle. The fyrſte is a gerdle of chaſtite / &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by may we knowe that Paule vſyth the wyt of the ſoule / &amp; leueth bodyly armour. This gerdle gerdeth vp in theyr hynden &amp; ſaueth chaſtyte &amp; peace / &amp; the body fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lechery in theſe thre de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. In maydens / it kepyth virginite / in wed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded trew matrimonye / in wydowes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynence / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bodyly vncle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes. Take ye this gerdle in goddes name / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye may ſtanden ꝓfyte in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peace of your ſoul agayne al fleſſhely ſtirrynges. The ſeconde armoure is an haberyon of ryghtwyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that is thykke mayled for falſhoode ſhulde not entre for to greue god or man / or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thys trewe peace. The thyrde Armoure is a legge harneys and ſhoynge of affectyons in the goſpel of Ieſu Chryſt / and than they ben dyſpoſed to make peace amonge men / not
<pb facs="tcp:8704:36"/>
as the worlde aſkyth / but that they ſtonde ſure and perfytely in all aduerſyte with Chryſt and hys goſpel / to the deth day. The fourth armour is a ſhelde of fayth in which they ſhullen quench al the fendes brenning darth / that ben his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacyons. Certes there may no dedly dyntes ſtele in that man that hath the ſhelde of trewe beleue hangynge in his herte. Therfore he ledyth hys lyfe in peace and quarte fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al goſtely ſyckenes. The fyfte armoure of the ſoule is an helme of helthe that is cleped truſty hope / for it berethe of ſtrokes that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fende throwith at ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſoule with two diſpicious gynnes. THe one is obſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacyon or hardenes of herte. The other is deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peracyon or elles wanhope. But who that hathe the helme of hope / thoughe ſtrokes lyghten on them they ſhall in no wyſe braſte this palet ne ſynke into the ſoule / therfore he lyuethe peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in hope of goddes mercy. The ſyxt armoure of goddes knyghtes with whiche they done aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile / is the ſwerde of the ſpirite that is goddes worde / with this ſwerde Iudith the wedowe ſmote Holofernes / and cut his heed from the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy in ſauynge of her people. And in this ſwerde Ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſte aſſayled the fende of hell. whan Chriſt ſaid. Go Sathanas / anon he fled away. For thys ſwerde is full ſharpe and byteth on bothe ſydes / for it partyth at one ſtroke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule and body a ſondre / and it departyth in this lyfe vertue from ſynne / and it ſhal departe at domes<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>day y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good from the yuel / in this ſwerde kynge Solomon gaue true iugemente and dyuyded
<pb n="xxxvii" facs="tcp:8704:36"/>
truthe from the falſhode. God geue vs grace to take thys ſwerde of kynge Salomon with Iudyth / and with Ieſu Chryſte / and than theyr is no doute / for al that taken this ſwerde and ſtande on this armour / Chriſt our captayne bleſſyth them and clepyth them hys chyldren. Mat. 5.<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> Bleſſed be al theſe peace makers (ſayth Chriſt) for they ſhalbe cleped the ſonnes of god. And efte Chriſt ſayth Loue ye your enemyes / do ye well to them that haten you / and pray ye for your purſuers and your ſclaunderers that ye may be the ſonnes of your father that is in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. But peace makers in the fendes church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fedre them to geder in a falſe peace / after the maner of this worlde / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſtes goſpel damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth / where he ſayth. I came not to maynteyne vicious peace. But to ſende a ſharpe ſwerde to ſmyte ſynne from mannes ſoule / and this theſe ſynnefull wretches throwen vnder fete / faith / trouth / &amp; rightwyſnes they counten at no price for they ouer leden the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre after theyr owne luſt. Therfore the prophete Dauid ſorowith on this myſcheue. I haue (ſaythe he) ſorowed on wycked men / ſeynge the peace of ſynners / but Preſtes and knyghtes of this ſome ben moſte to blame.<note place="margin">Preſtes.</note> Preſtes that ſhulde be goſtely leches and reconſyle the people by good counſeyle to theyr god and hele them with hys lawe / what with couetyſe and many fleſſhly luſtes theſe preſtes ben ſo blynded that they knowe no wyſedome / for Iob aſkynge this queſtion.<note place="margin">Iob.</note> wher wyſdome may be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de anon he anſweryth with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite
<pb facs="tcp:8704:37"/>
of god / <note place="margin">Gregory.</note> not in the londe of luſty lyuers. And vpon thys ſaythe Gregory in hys Moralles. Theſe wordes of great ſorow to them that ben gylty. who that is fedde with pleſures or luſtes of this preſent lyfe without any doute that man is departed from the vnderſtandynge of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge wyſedome. And ſithen theſe preſtes be geuen to this fleſſhely luſtes they faylen goſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſyght &amp; and wyſedome / to ranſake any goſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſyckenes or to ſerche aboute the perell of a wounde / and yet they ben preſumpteous to pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer falſe medecyne / &amp; vndertake great cures for to make men hole / but they hurten them moche ſorer than they were before / as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde moueth by his ꝓphete Ieremy.<note place="margin">Ieremy.</note> Theſe preſtes helydden the contrycyon of my people with ſhenſhyp or with ſhame / that is with foule ſymony as we reherſed aforne. And they ſayen. Peace / peace / whan theyr was no peace / they ben worthy to be ſpent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue done abhominacyon moch rather in thys cofaſyon they ben not confunded / for they haue not ben aſhamed of theyr owne felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. Thus ſayth the lorde god / and efte he ſayth from the preachours that commeth defoulynge vpon all the erthe. Theſe thynges ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde wyll ye here the wordes of theſe preachours y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> prechen &amp; deſceyuen you. They ſpeken y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> viſyon of theyr herte / but not of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes mouth / they ſayen to tho that blaſphemen me. The lord ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyth that peace ſhalbe to you / and they haue ſayde to eche man that walkethe in ſhrewdnes of his herte theyr ſhal come none yll vpon hym.
<pb n="xxxviii" facs="tcp:8704:37"/>
And Gregorye ſaythe.<note place="margin">Gregory.</note> Yuyll preſtes ben cauſe of ruyne &amp; decaye of the people / &amp; no wounder for wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lyght is quenched that ſhulde ſhyne in preſtes / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is theyr moche ſtynke with wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked fauour / and blyndnes that cumbrith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leder &amp; the folower into the derkenes of hell as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell wytneſſyth. whan the blynde ledith the blynde / fall they not tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both into the dyke or lake? yes playnly. The former blynde is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wantith vnderſtandyng / for you haue the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne &amp; fayle in good lyuyng / than he is a blynd preſt of whome Chriſt ſpekith / as the commen gloſe ſayth / aboute nought he boſtith the kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng of godes law y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diſtroyeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lore with his wycked workes. The other blynde is man &amp; wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> truſten in ſuch preſtes to lede them in the way of lyfe / &amp; bryng them to ſaluacion. But Chriſt hath iuged both theſe partyes to fal into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dungyon. Of ſuch preſtes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth debate in all the world y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diſtrobleth very peace &amp; cryeth open vengeaunce. And theſe prechours ben no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chours but only in name / as a luſchborne is cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid apeny &amp; is nought worth.<note place="margin">Knyghtes.</note> Knyghtes alſo ben to blame y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> myſuſen theyr power &amp; wyl not rede is goddes lawe neyther lerne theyr office. And therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyſema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blameth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayeng. Here ye knyghtes &amp; vnderſtande ye knyghtes for power is only of the lorde and ſtrength cometh of them that is hyeſt that ſhall aſke rekennynge of all your workes / and ſhal ſerche fully the inwarde of your thoughtes. For whan ye were my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſters of godes realme neyther ye demed ryght<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully / neyther kepte ye his lawe / neyther ye
<pb facs="tcp:8704:38"/>
walked in the way after goddes wyll / but ye ſtrayed all away as yf it were wylde lyons / in oftyn takyng of moch meate that ſtyryth you to moch drynkynge / than ye lyggen longe in cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chis that draweth you to Lechery / &amp; ſometyme to ſpouſebreche and other foule vnclennes / and of this commethe ſtryuynge and fyghtyng euer anon that bryngeth you to enmyte and hate of eche othere. Howe ſhulde ye knyghtes mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne peace whan ye forſake it in your ſelfe / for with your greuous tirannye oppreſſion &amp; extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon your awe is lawe. who dare ſay nay / but as ye woll your ſelfe. But wete you well thys is the voyce of them that ſhalbe dampned as the wyſe man ſayth. Our ſtrength / our power / be it to vs the lawe of ryghtwyſnes. Here ye ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore howe dredfully it folowith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſentence ſayd afore if that ye wyl not amende you. Ferefully and ſone it ſhall ſhewe to you that moſt harde iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gemente ſhalbe to them that lorden or that hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den lordeſhype ouer poore bretherne / mercy is graunted to them that ben lowe in herte mighty men myghty ſhullen ſuffre turmentry / forſothe the Lorde ſhal not withdrawe the perſon of any man neyther he ſhalbe aſhamed of any mannes greatneſſe / for he hathe made bothe ſmall and great / and chargith ne one ne other / forſothe to the ſtronger is made ſtronger crucyacyon in payne. Thheſe forſayde preſtes and knyghtes throughe ſuch vicious dedes leden y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commennes on theyr rynge / and bolden them in ſynne / ſo that all this worlde is ſet in errour in batayle
<pb n="xxix" facs="tcp:8704:38"/>
and in warre. But nowe be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men to the preſte the wordes that god hath ſayde by the prophete Ieremy to teache his choſen ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes.<note place="margin">Ieremy.</note> Al theſe ben aduolterers and a company that breken the lawe / they haue ſtretched forth theyr tonge as a bent bowe to ſhutte leſynge &amp; no trouth / eche man at other / they ben comforted in the erthe / for they gone from yuell to yuel / and they haue not knowen me ſayth the Lorde god / eche man from his neybour kepe them ſelfe full wyſely / and in his owne brother he may haue no truſte / for eche brother in dyſſeyte ſhal begyle othere / and the man ſhall ſcorne hys brother and they ſhall not ſpeke truth / forſothe they haue taught theyr tonge to ſpeke leſyng / and for they wolde done wyckedly they haue ſore traueled / they haue forſaken in trechery to knowe me / ſaythe the lorde god / wherfore theſe thynges ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde of hoſtes. Lo I ſhall wele them to geder / and I ſhall proue them / what ſhall I elles do / from the face of my people an arrowe wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deng is theyr tonge / for it ſpekyth gyle / and he ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyth with his frendes / peace with his mouth / but pryuely he layeth for hym ſpyes to diſceue them. Nowe whether ſhal they not vyſyte vpon theſe thynges ſaythe the lorde god or ſhall not my wyll be venged vpon ſuche a folke? as yf he wolde fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. I ſhalbe venged / for as theyr wyl is to go from me ſo my wil is to be venged vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when I ſe my tyme / but happely here ſome woll ſaye god woll not take vengeans on hys chriſten people / god woll not leſe that he dere
<pb facs="tcp:8704:39"/>
bought with his precyous blode. To the fyrſte we anſweren by the mouthe of god.<note place="margin">Iere. 16.</note> Ieremy. 16 your fathers (ſayth he) haue forſaken me / and gone after goddes for to do them ſeruyce / and worſhyp them alſo / but they haue forſaken me and not kepte my lawe. But ye alſo done moche werſe than euer wrought your faders. Lo eche of you walketh after the ſhrewydnes of his euyl herte / that he here not me ſayth the lorde god / and I ſhall caſt yrou away out of this erthe / into a lande that is vnknowen to you and to your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and there ye ſhal do auarice to alyen god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des that ſhal gyue no reſt neyther nyght ne day. And to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de we anſweren as Chriſt ſayth in his goſpel. Frende howe entreſt thou hether not hauynge thy brydale clothes / &amp; he waxt domb. Than this kynge Ieſu Chriſte ſayd to his my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. Take this wretch / bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den hande and fote &amp; ſende him into vttermoſt darkenes / their ſhal be wepyng and gnaſtynge of tethe / vnderſtande thou by this / frende / both man and woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hath taken chriſtendome / and holdethe the name / but they wanten in theyr lyuynge the workes of treue beleue therfore Chriſt wardeth them in to the payne of hell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ How y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de church accordyth with the firſt churche. Ca. x.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="xl" facs="tcp:8704:39"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere ſhal we tel howe the good of the ſeconde church accordeth with the fyrſte churche appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pred to god / Faythe / Hope / &amp; Charite / as we haue ſayde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forne knytten togeder god and man in one heed of this church. Thys knotte is knytte ſo ſekyrly that it ſhall neuer more fayle neyther here ne elles where as the wyſeman ſayth. The thre folde corde is ful lothely burſton. For to make this thre folde corde we muſt haue thre lynkes / &amp; eke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forth perfyte tyll this corde be wrought / by whiche this church ſhalbe drawen vnto the holy Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite. Theſe ben the fyrſt thre / a chaſt body / a clene ſoule / and goddes truly dyſpoſed than it ſhalbe eked with good holy thought &amp; a perfyte dede / more ouer we muſt large forth ſhryfte of mouthe ſorowe of herte / &amp; amendes makynge / after this it aſkyth prayer / faſtynge / &amp; almyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dede / than muſt we put to / nombre / weyght / &amp; meſure. Alſo we muſt eke this worde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> minde / wyll / &amp; reaſon / and helpe forth to thende with Faythe / Hope / &amp; Charite / than we ſhal neyghe to our god thorough grace / mercy / &amp; ryghtwyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / tyll we ſe god in Trynite / Fader / Son / &amp; holy Goſte. Euery me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of this churche hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pith / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may to wyrche one parte of this corde for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men ꝓfyte as ſayncte Auſten ſaythe. Holy churche is a ferme of all ryghtwyſeneſſe / that is to ſay a comen accorde of al good thinges and thys churche prayethe in commen / and
<pb facs="tcp:8704:40"/>
wyrcheth theyr workes in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men. For without felowſhype of thys generall churche baptiſme may not profyte neyther the dedes of mercye / but it be that the paynes of hell be leſſe / all the members of a man trauelyn in theyr ordre eche for to ſocoure othere / none for to hyndre / but for to do theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn helpe to the profyte of the body. Thus it is of the members that ben in Chriſtes churche / for it is a godly body that growith with theyr me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers / theyr one fayleth an othere helpeth tyll the corde be made. Some haue moch of wyſedome / to knowe holy wryt. Some haue fayre eloquence to preche it to the people. Some haue moch of goſtely ſtrength to ſuffre tribulacyon. Some haue pety and releuen theyr nedy neybours Some tenden vertuoſly to miniſter ſacramentes. Some ſtyen hyely to reſt in heuenly thynges or lykynges / but all ſuche thynges ben in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men to them that ſhalbe ſaued / as the prophete ſayth. Spekynge in the perſon of the generall churche. Lorde I am par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tener of all them that fere or dreden the / and of all that kepe thyne holy commaundementes. Thus teacheth alſo the commen crede in an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tycle of the ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> muſt nede be grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted whiche is / the communion of ſaynctes. For what that euer be done in Rome or in any other places / yf that thynge be couenable in the ſyght of god / than it is couenable to all theſe members that ſeruen god in vertue to helpe them to their ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ioye as we haue ſayde afore / <note place="margin">Ierome.</note> herto accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyth ſaynct Ierome vpon this texte of Chriſtes
<pb n="xli" facs="tcp:8704:40"/>
goſpell. Math. 16.<note place="margin">Math. 16.</note> Chriſt ſayd to Peter and in him to all his folowers / to the and to all ſuche as thou arte I ſhal gyue the keyes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realme of heuennes is this church here in erthe.<note place="margin">Ierome.</note> Ierom ſayth / and the mayſter of the ſentence reherſeth this. All myniſters of the church in byſſhopes and preſtes haue the iudiciary power as ſaynte Peter had / but therfore Peter ſpecyall toke of god this power that all men may vnderſtande that who ſo euer departeth them from vnyte of ſtedfaſt fayth and felowſhyp of this church / he may neyther be aſſoyled fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bondes of his ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes neyther he may entre into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blyſſe of heuen. Se nowe here both leryd &amp; lewde how prayers ben in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn and all other ſuffrages to thys goſtely church. whence cometh tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this out crye that is ſet on broch / ſale / kene / in euery church to ſell theſe goſtely thynges with ſuffrages and ſoyleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / &amp; many yeres of pardon? &amp; a plena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye indulgence A pena et culpa / but moch rather it ſhulde be ſayd / a glorie et pecunia. Certes they come from byneth of the fendes temptynge &amp; ben borne all about of his curſyd members / to poyſon the people in myſbeleue as ſainct Ierom ſayth and parte them from goddes felowſhyp by wytneſſe of ſaynct Auſten / &amp; dryue them to theyr endeles payne / as we haue ſayd aforne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of ioye in tribulacyon. The .xi. chapitre.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8704:41"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt for that we repreue theſe ſynnes thys yuell parte grut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyth and purſueth with ſtrong hande to pryſon and to ſlee / therfore muſte we lerne thys lore of Chryſtes holy goſpell. Math. 5. Ye ben bleſſed whan men haue curſed you / <note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> and haue purſued you / &amp; haue ſayde all yuell agaynſt you lyeng for me / ioye ye and be ye mery / for your mede is moche in heuennes. And alſo ſaynct Peter ſayth. whan that ye ſuffren any thynge for ryghtwyſneſſe. Bleſſed mote ye be / ſaynt Paul affirmeth this ſentence y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> goddes ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſhullen haue payne in this lyfe to kepe them in vertue. 2. Thimo. 3. All that euer wol lyue mekely in Chryſt Ieſu ſhal ſuffre perſecucyon.<note place="margin">☞ Luke.</note> And ſaynt Luke ſayth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of Paule in dedes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſteles. Act. 14. By many tribulacions it behoueth vs to en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tre into the realme of god. And thus ſaythe the ꝓphete. Many ben the tribulacions that fallen to the ryghtwyſe &amp; fro them al / whan tyme co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth god ſhall delyuer them. Chriſt behyght the maner of lyfe / to his owne diſcyples / and gaue them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte that they ſhulde haue a gracyous delyuerance for than ſhall blyſſe be moche the ſweter whan they comyn therto.<note place="margin">☞ Io. 6.</note> Io. 6. Truly I ſay vnto you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trouth / that ye ſhulde ſorowe and wepe / forſoth the worlde ioye / &amp; ye ſhulde be full heuy / and after this your heuynes ſhalbe tourned into ioye / and your ioye ſhalbe ſekyr that no man ſhall take it from you / and for this
<pb n="xlii" facs="tcp:8704:41"/>
ioye ſhulde ſauour well to them that ben his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers he ſendith them tribulacion / as ſaynt Gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gory ſayeth. God ſhewith to his choſen / ſharpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes in this iourney / leſt by hap yf they delyted them in this dedly way / they myght forgeyte thynges that ben in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre / tribulaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> briſen vs downe in this wretched world / they conſtrayne vs to go to god / that they light<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly myght be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned / for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eyen that ſynne clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyth / payne maketh open / &amp; many that haunten theft with many other ſynnes if they were lame blynde / or croked of godes viſitacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhuld ceſſe &amp; ſerue theyr god / &amp; do penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ful trewly as Cryſoſtome ſayth. Omeli. 3. The ſoule is a ſpirite (ſayth he) and dredeth ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all paynes of the fleſſhe. And therfore ſaynctes dyſpyſen the paynes of this worlde / &amp; drede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt iugement where ſpyrytes ben tourmented / forſothe the fleſſhe can not drede goſtely paines to come / but he dredith in this life to ſuffre any paines / ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yuel ceſſen not to do ſyn / but if iugement of the fleſſhe conſtraynen them to be ſtyll &amp; for this cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde ſhal ſende vpon his ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſore punyſſhyng to theyr fleſſhe &amp; other tribula<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions. The luſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſſh may be ſweled from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> couetynge of yuell. we muſte nede breke the nut yf we wyl haue the cornell we muſt nedes ſuffre trauell / yf we deſyren reſte. So muſt we nedes ſuffre payne yf we wyll come to blyſſe. He is a falſe cowarde knyght / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleeth &amp; hydeth his hed whan his mayſter is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> felde beten amonge his enemyes / but our lord Ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt was be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en of
<pb facs="tcp:8704:42"/>
the Iewes / and after dyed in the felde on the mounte of Caluarye to pay our raumſome / he toke his deth for that he was nothynge gylty / and hys body whan it was offered / made at the full for redempcyon of mankynde. Therfore the wyſeman ſayth. Eccle. 20. Forgete thou not the kyndenes of thy borowe / forſothe he hathe geuen for the his life. This borowe is our lorde god that without mede came from heuen in to this worlde to borowe his people / &amp; in takynge of fleſſhe &amp; blode of the virgyn mary / he ſhewed vs grace and kyndenes both in worde and wyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge. But in geuynge his lyfe / he leyd his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy in pledge / yea to the deth he woll not ſpare to ſuffre extreme payne / ſo moche he loued his people / yf that fayth be in vs thys maye not be forgoten. Some forſaken ſynnes and ſuen Chryſte in vertue and this is a great kindenes / though they ſtyen no hyer. Some do wake in abſtynence and ſtudyen holye leſſons / thys is than a greatter kyndnes / yf thou fle from ſyn. Some ben redy whan they ben called of the holy goſte to ſuffre dethe for Ieſu Chryſte / and wytnes of his lawe / and whan they haue cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes in lyuynge / this is the greateſt kyndenes as the goſpel ſheweth. Io. 15.<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Io. 15.</note> A greater loue or charite may no man haue than to leſe his lyfe for hys frendes ſoule / we were dere and leffe to god whan we toke the baptyſme / but we haue moch dere worthyer whan we done the workes that god hath bydden in his lawe without any grut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge / and yf we maynteyn this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="lxiii" facs="tcp:8704:42"/>
not go therfro / neither become rennegates for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paynes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may fal / but thinke on Chriſtes paſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſwageth al heuynes / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ben moſt dere worthy / and worthy hyeſt meryte / &amp; therfore ſaynct Paule ſayth to the Galathies. Fere be it to me / to make any glorye but in the croſſe that is the paſſyon of our lorde Ieſu Chriſte / by whome this worlde is crucyfyed to me / and I am crucyfyed to the worlde. Some ben not cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyed to the worlde / but the worlde is crucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed to them / for they deſpiſen the world / but the worlde not them. Some ben crucyfyed to the worlde / but not ſo the worlde to them / for though the worlde deſpyſen them / they diſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen it not againe. Some ben neyther crucified to the world / ne the worlde to them / for neyther they diſpyſe the worlde / ne the worlde them. In the fyrſte degree were the apoſtels. And in the ſeconde degree ben other good lyuers. But in the thyrde &amp; fourth degre / bene tho y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhulde be dampned / &amp; therfore we ſhuld vnderſtande that ſome ſuffren payne for to ſaue the people / and ſo dyd Ieſu Chriſt / whan it myght not ſaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe / &amp; ſhewed his great kyndenes. Some ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fren payne to purge them of theyr ſynne that they haue done i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time afore / &amp; cryen god mercy. Some ſuffren payne to kepe them from ſyn that they ſhulde be combryd with if no payne were / but ſome ſuffren payne for they haunten ſyn / and for they maken none ende. Ioyne than the croſſe of Chryſt vnto our bare fleſſh / that our parte may be founden amonge theſe holy ſaintes
<pb facs="tcp:8704:43"/>
that wylfully forſoke them ſelfe / and ioyed in trybulacion as ſaynct Iames ſayth. Ia. 1. My brethern hope ye all ioye whan ye haue ſlyden amonge dyuerſe temptations knowynge that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prouynge of your fayth / wyrchyth pacience / forſoth pacience hath a parfyte worke / that ye mowe be perfite / in ſoule and hole in body / and in nothynge faylynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the fendes cautyles by the which he purſueth in his members the kepers of goddes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes. Ca. xii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He yuel parte of thys churche ſhall neuer ceſſe with the malyce that they may to purſue good leuers: but for his choſen chyldren god ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bregge the dayes of ther wodenes &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal men wel knowe as Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church &amp; geuith it good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort. Apo. 2. Drede thou not tho thynges which thou arte for to ſuffre / Lo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl is for to ſende of you i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pryſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; ye ſhal haue tribulacion ten dayes by dene: be y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> faithful to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deth / &amp; I ſhal geue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a crowne of life / he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath eares of heryng / here he / what the ſpirite ſayth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churches / who y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſhal not be hurt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeconde deth / vnderſtande y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> by this deuyl all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> curſyd people y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal purſue good lyuers vnto the worldes ende / ſomtime more / ſomtyme leſſe / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diuers paynes of tourme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try / &amp; vnderſtande thou by theſe ten dayes / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ten co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes for they ben light of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes wyt / in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> derkenes of this worlde / as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day paſſith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb n="xliiii" facs="tcp:8704:43"/>
nyght in his clere ſhinyng. Of theſe ten co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fende fayneth his accion to troble the good of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church &amp; ſende them to pryſon / &amp; here it ſemeth ſpedyer to tell y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fendes cautyles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he vſeth in his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers agaynſt godes heftes / &amp; as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cloude in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day ſo marrith he ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes wites. The firſt heft of god is this. Exo. xx. Math. xxij. Mar. xxiij. I am y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde thy god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue lad the out of Egipt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the houſe of thraldome / before me thou ſhalt haue none alyen goddes / thou ſhal not make to the any grauen thyng / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in heuen aboue nor in erthe beneth or of tho thynges that ben in waters vnderneth I am the lord thy god a ſtrong Ielous louer viſytyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyckednes of fathers vpon ſonnes into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thirde &amp; fourth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haten me / &amp; I doynge merry into thouſandes to them that louen me &amp; kepen myne heftes. Agayne this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fende hath leyde two ſnares / &amp; in them he catcheth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may not ſcape: but ether they muſt grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ten to his wyl / or elles they ſhuld to priſon The firſt is cleped obedyens y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fende chalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth chiefly for to be done to him / or to his leef tenauntes / as to prelates or to preſtes that ben his officers / &amp; aſken this obedyence / what euer they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſymple me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obey to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; hye &amp; low. Al this world crieth loude after this obe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dience: &amp; ſayen what euer thy ſouerayn biddeth: y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt obey therto. Here we grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ten of beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we owen obedyence to our ſoueraynes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> techen vs to knowe god &amp; drede him / ye whether they that ben miniſters in the ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all parte or officers
<pb facs="tcp:8704:44"/>
in the temperalty / we muſt obey to them in that they obey to god / and lerne vs obedyence / for thus is wryten. 1. Reg. 15. No whether wyl the lorde brent offerynges or ſacryfyces / and moch better it is to take to lawe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to offre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fatnes of rammes / for it is as the ſyn of wytchcrafte / to fyght agayne god / &amp; as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> felony of Idolatry: not to conſent to goddes worde for this cauſe / therfore that thou haſt caſt awaye the worde of the lorde / the lorde hath caſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> away that thou be no longer kynge. And to this the wyſeman accordeth and ſayth. Moch better is obedyence than ſacryfice of fooles / for yuell folkes wote not what they done. And ſaynct Paule teacheth an open rule of this maner of obedience with the cauſe of ſouerantye and knyttyth them both to geder. Obey ye (ſayth he) to your ſoueraynes &amp; vnderlowte ye to them / and the cauſe why / is this. Forſothe they waken perfyttely as for to yelde a rekenynge for your ſoules yf thys cauſe be taken away / obedyence ceſſyth there alſo as the philoſopher ſayth / whan the cauſe ceſſyth / the ſpede therof ſhal alſo ceſſe. But ſaynt Peter teacheth obedyence that we ſhuld done to lordes &amp; that in more larger maner than we owen to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergy. Seruauntes (ſayth he) be ye ſubiectes in all drede to your temporall lordes / not only to good and eaſy lordes / that is to ſay in loue / but alſo to tyrantes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay in pacyence / but fendes lymmes faynen them to be on Chryſtes ſyde and to do corrections after Chriſtes wil / &amp; ſeyn / they aſke obedyenee to amende ſoules
<pb n="xlv" facs="tcp:8704:44"/>
whan they do thys thyng in dede that they here ſpeken than we ſhal obey to them / and elles we ſhall anſwere as Peter ſayde to preſtes &amp; byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopes / of the law. Act. 5. It behoueth more to obey god than man. Sayncte Ierom ſayth.<note place="margin">Ierome.</note> Yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prelate or the Lorde bydde any thynge that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordeth with goddes wyll / obey thou then to them / yf they bydde the contrary to god and to hys lawe than ſay thus / I muſt rather obey to the lorde of the ſoule / than to the lorde of the body. For Chriſt ſayth Mat. 10. &amp; Luce. 12.<note place="margin">Math.</note> wil ye drede them that ſlayne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body / forſoth they may not ſlee the ſoule / but rather drede ye hym that may ſlee bothe body and ſoule / into hell / thus I ſay to you drede ye him. And ſaynt Gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gory ſayth. This forſayd rule of obedyence ſhal be ſtreytly kept. In chyldren to theyr parentes. In ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes to theyr lordes. In clerkes to ther mayſters. In preſtes to there prelates. And yf we paſſe this rule in doynge of obedyence / than we were vnbuxum to god / and folowers of Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfer. The ſeconde trappe of the fende is clepyd pylgremage / but moch rather it ſhulde be ſayed the outrage of fooles. For pylgrimage in dewe fourme is euermore good. The payntours ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kith an ymage forged with dyuers colours tyll it ſeme in foles eyen as a lyuely creature that is ſet in the church in a ſolempne place faſt bounde with bondes for it ſhulde not fall. Preſtes of the temple begylen the people with the foule ſyn of Balaam / in there open prechynge they ſayen that goddes power in wyrchyng of his miracles
<pb facs="tcp:8704:45"/>
lowyth downe in one ymage / more than in a no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther / and therfore commyth and offrith to this: for here is ſhewed moche vertue. Lorde howe dare theſe fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des for drede thus blaſpheme theyr god and vſe the ſynne of Balaam that goddes lawe hath dampned? Sithen Chriſt and his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyples forſoken this / the welthe of this worlde and lyueden a poore lyfe / as our beleue techith: why gadren ye preſtes rycheſſe with your pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ymages to make your ſelfe worldy ryche in ſpoylynge of the people / and yet ye done moche worſe / and for ye and your conſentours / thus doynge bene very Idolatrers / <note place="margin">☞ Paule.</note> as ſayncte Paule ſayth Corinth. 1. This people (ſayth he) ſayeng them ſelfe to be wyſe / they bene mad fooles / for they haue chaunged the glorye of god that maye not be defouled / into the lykenes of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes image that maye be defouled. And Paule ſaythe when they knewe the ryghtwyſnes of god / they wolde not vnderſtande that they that done ſuche thynges bene worthy of dethe / not onely the doars but alſo they that conſenten to the yuell doers / for god ſaythe thou ſhalte neyther worſhyp ne lowte them for thou ſhalte neyther do ſacryfyce to image ne offerynge and that meaneth god when he ſayth / thou ſhalt not worſhyp them with no godly worſhyp / but / yf they be paynted truly as nye as man maye to brynge to mynde as Gregory ſayth the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of Ieſu Chryſte / <note place="margin">Gregory.</note> &amp; marterdome of ſayntes as lewde mennes bokes. But ſayncte Auſten ſayth vpon all wyſe they haue deſerued to erre
<pb n="xlvi" facs="tcp:8704:45"/>
that ſeken god not in bokes / but in paynted wowis / he alſo ſayth thou ſhalt not vowe to theſe ymages / thou ſhalte not ſeke theſe yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / thou ſhalt not ſwere by them / neyther knele to them ne kyſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / neyther put fayth / ne Hope / ne truſte in one ymage / more than in another / and thus menyth god whan he ſaythe thou ſhalt not loute them. But true pylgrymage is done on .vj. maners. Fyrſt we ben pilgrimmes when that we ben borne / as the commyn gloſe ſayth vpon Geneſis. Euery cytezyne of the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly countre is a pylgreme of thys worlde / for all tyme of thys preſent lyfe / and whan we trauelyn ſore to kepe goddes heſtes tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we done our pylgrimage / as the prophete ſayth.<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.</note> Pſal. 118. Lorde thy commaundementes weren my ſonges in tyme of my pylgrymage. The ſeconde tyme / we ben pylgrymes when we gone to the churche as it is wrytten. Luc. xxiiij.<note place="margin">Luc. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Tu ſolus peregrinus es in Ieruſalem, &amp;c,</hi> whan we done in the churche in fourme as god hathe taught vs / than we done our pylgrymage. For thus ſayth ſayncte Luke. Luc. 2. <hi>Cum ſanctus eſſet Ieſus annorum duodecim. &amp;c.</hi> The thyrde tyme we ben pylgrymes / when we vyſyte the nedye / and whan we delen almyſdede / we done our pylgrimage. Luc. xiij.<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Luc. 13.</note> Go thou forthe anone into ſtretes and wayes and brynge in to thyne houſe theſe thre maner of people / poore feble / poore blynde / &amp; poore lame. The fourth tyme Preſtes bene pylgrymes that ſtudyen ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye wryt tyll they haue plenty in theyr mynde
<pb facs="tcp:8704:46"/>
of this heuenly wyſedome / and than they hyen them faſt about in all the brode worlde to dele this goſtely treaſour amonge the wyttles peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that is in poynt to ſpyll for hunger in wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge goſtly teachyng as it is wrytten. Io. 4. Dere frende thou doſte ryghtfully what euer thou doſte into our brethern / and namely into pylgremes that prechen the goſpell / and bene apayde where they come with poore ſymple ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flode. The fyfte tyme tho ben pylgrymmes that wonnen in a towne where is neyther preſte ne lorde to teche them / neyther to rule them / and than they gone vnto the place where they may be taught and ruled vnder gouernaunce. This is pilgrimage as it is wryten. Gene. 12.20. and. 26. There is no other pylgrymage that maye pleaſe god out take this that we haue ſayd / and all holy wryt berythe wytneſſe / for whan the body is layde in graue and the ſoule forth paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyth to blyſſe or to payne wether that it be than the ſyxte pylgremage is ended. The ſeconde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente of god is thus. Exo. 20. Thou ſhalt not take the name of thy god in vaine. And Chryſte ſayth in his goſpell.<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> Math. 5. Forſoth I ſay vnto you / not to ſwere in any wyſe / ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by heuen for it is the trone of god / neyther by the erthe / for it is the ſtole of his feete / ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Ieruſalem for it is the cyte of a greate kynge / neyther by thyne heed / for thou mayſte not make a heare whyte or blacke / forſothe be your worde / ye / ye / and nay / nay / with herte and mouth accordyng agaynſt this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb n="xlvii" facs="tcp:8704:46"/>
the deuyll in hys members conſtraynen men to ſwere and leyen there handes on bokes / &amp; than he puttyth them to open ſhame / and if they leue his byndyng he ſayth by lawe they ben relapſe / and than they ſhalbe brent. And thys is an hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous clowde vpon this ſchynefull day to payne men for kepyng of goddes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. For ſaynte Auſten ſaith vpon the goſpel. Chriſt hath taught that thynge that is of more perfection / that thyng that is of infyrmyte he hath ſuffred: that thynge that is ſuperſtycyous he hath cutte away / it is of perfeccyon / not to ſwere in any maner / it is of infyrmyte for to ſwere conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned / but it is of ſuperſtycyon to ſwere vaynly. For the wyſeman ſayth. Sap. 14. Swerynge is no vertue but payne of ſynners / eyther of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wyll not gyue credens / but yf men ſwere / or elles of them that ſweren withouten cauſe. And therfore Criſoſtome blameth preſtes for they bryngen forth bokes / to compell men to ſwere vpon them / &amp; aſkyth this queſtion. whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is not he that ſettyth an houſe on brenning gylty of this brennynge? whether is not he that bryngeth a ſwerde with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which man ſlaughter is done / gylty of this manſlaughter? So they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bryngen forth bokes on whiche me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forſweren them ben gylty of this ſwerynge / and he ſayth. Yf the people wyll ſaye the ſothe without any othe / wherto ſhulde they ſwere? And yf they ſuppoſen they wolde ſay falſe / why ſhulde they be compelled to forſwere them ſelfes? and the greatnes of ſynne ſtandyth greatly and chyeftly
<pb facs="tcp:8704:47"/>
in ſuche ordynaryes / eyther ſecler or ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all as this doctour proueth / nought exceptynge pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion without ſuch othes / and of this ſweryng cometh wyckednes / and goddes greuous ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance / as the wyſeman ſaythe. Aman moche ſwerynge ſhalbe fulfylled with wickednes / and vengeaunce ſhal not go from his houſe. Yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes purſuen agayne this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / &amp; ſayen that Chriſt him ſelfe ſwore / &amp; his ſayntes alſo. Swere by this boke thou obſtinate ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or elles thou ſhalt to pryſon / thou ſhalt ſwere in our courte bycauſe of thyne infyrmyte as ſaynctes hath taught when thou arte conſtrayned to thys we ſeyen that Ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt forbedyth on al wyſe ſweryng by any of theſe .iiij. thynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hym ſelfe reherſeth / that is to ſay / heuen / or erthe: Ieruſalem / or by thyne owne hed / &amp; wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe foure ben out taken / with al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in heuen / ye ſhal not grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de your vicious ſweryng / tyll that heuen befallen. To this y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſayncte Auſten ſayth. Thou ſhalt ſwere compelled / we grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ten wel a fore a iuge / if elles me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyl not trowen vs / but neyther on bokes ſhulde we ſwere / neyther by goddes creatures but after the fourme that god hath taught by Ieremy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝓhhete Ieremy. iiii. Thou ſhal ſwere. The lorde leuyth in trouth &amp; dome / and rightwyſnes. The lorde lyueth is to mene / by god or by thyne holy dome / or by thy trouth. Thus ſhalt thou not ſwere but with thre condicions. The fyrſt is trouth in the conſcience of them that ſwerith without any gyle. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde / that it be done in dome / to exclude al ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="xlviii" facs="tcp:8704:47"/>
of idle and vayne ſwerynge. The thyrde that it be in ryghtwyſnes / and in no maner of deceyte / ne hindrynge to our neybour / ne dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghtwyſnes of god / but we may in no cauſe ſwere by bokes / as we haue ſayde afore / neyther by lyfely creatures / as by ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes or by any ſuch other. For the wiſeman ſaith Cuſtome not thou thy mouth to ſwere by names of ſayntes for Chriſoſtome ſayth. Omeli. 12. He that ſweryth by a creature / doth ydolatry / he that ſwereth by creatures / ſynneth double folde / ye though it war ſo / that ſweryng were leful / ones / for he ſwerith / a nother tyme / for he makytſt him ſelfe a falſe god / for what ſo euer it be that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſweryth by / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thyng he ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth his god / lorde how mony me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; women ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falſe goddes / ſythen welnye all this worlde hath cuſtome to ſwere by one ſaint or by another. Certes theſe forſaid enemyes ben cauſe of this blaſphemus ſweryng / what with theyr ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dres &amp; ſomtyme with their ſore punyſſhing &amp; freyl people cannot ſtande / but yelde them to this fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des temptynges. The thirde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god is this. Exo. xx. Haue mynde to halowe thyn holyday. In ſix dayes thou ſhalt wyrche &amp; do all thyne owne werkes / forſoth the ſeuenth day is the ſaboth of the lorde. Thou ſhal not do any ſeruyle worke. Theſe ſyx ſhal kepe this ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyday. Thy ſon &amp; thy doughter / thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / &amp; thyn hande mayden thy beeſt / &amp; thy ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in thy gates. In ſix dayes god made heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; erthe / &amp; the ſee / &amp; al thynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ben in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; he
<pb facs="tcp:8704:48"/>
in the .vij. day. Therfore god blyſſed the day of the ſaboth / and made it holy. Agayne this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente the fende in his members gyueth leue to chapeman to bye and ſell. Ye within the ſentuary / on the holy ſounday. And vytellers of the countre holden commen marketes / yet ſe thou more what ſynnes a gaynſte this hefte of god / great fayres of the yere for the moſt parte ben ſette on the ſaboth day by the fendes coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell. God toke full hydeous wreche vpon the chyldren of Iſraell when they wrought ſeruyle worke vpon the ſaboth daye as it is wryten. Eccle. xxxj. Halowe ye my holyday / forſothe it is holy to you who that hath defouled it / he ſhalbe deed / &amp; he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doth any ſeruyle werke ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in / hys lyfe ſhall peryſſhe from the myddes of his people. And ſo for gatherynge of ſtyckes on the ſaboth day / a man at goddes byddynge was ſtoned to the deth. Therfore Nemias a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that dreade god wyl ſuffre none to bye ne ſell on the ſaboth day within the gates of Ieruſalem / ney ther aboute the walles / and charged all vytel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers that they ſhulde ceaſſe / and yf they wolde not take hede they ſhulde fele his handes / for he thought for to warre on them as on goddes enemyes / but yf they wolde obey to god in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowyng of his ſaboth day. This proceſſe is wry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten in the boke of Neemias in the laſte chaptre. Lo howe ſtreytly the Iewes kepten goddes byd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge / and god ſmote them with bodely payne wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they dyd forgete. But chryſten men maken theyr boſt howe they be more parfyte in ſeruyce
<pb n="xlix" facs="tcp:8704:48"/>
of theyr god / then euer were the Iewes who that euer mekely proueth his worde in dede tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may he ſay boldely that this tyme of grace is of more parfeccyon / by vertue of the ſacremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and fredome of the goſpell than was Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes lawe / and thou a more parfyte man in ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge this perfeccyon / but &amp; thou be in apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in brekyng goddes heftes than is thy payne moch the more / as paule ſayd to the Romaynes <hi>Ro.</hi> 11. Forſothe thou ſtandeſt in the fayth / nyl thou be proude / ne bere the neuer the hyer / but abyde thou mekely in the holy drede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde. Forſoth ſyth that the lord ſparyd not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly or naturall braunches / that is to ſay / the Iewes that he choſe to be his kyndely heyres / beware leſte be hap he ſpare not the that ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt out of the hethen ſtocke / and arte planted in by grace of Chriſt and of his goſpell. Se now thyne apoſtaſy thou vnkynde wretche and the falſeneſſe that thou vſyſt agaynſt Chriſtes goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. Math. 21 Mar. 9. Luce. 19. Io. 2. Ieſu en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in to the tempell of god / and he caſt out all ſellers and byers in the tempell / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bordes of money makers / and he tourned vpſydowne the chayres of them that ſolden doues / and ſayd vnto them as it is wryten. Iſaye. 6. Myne houſe is cleped an houſe of prayer. Forſothe ye haue made it a denne for theues. Chriſte forbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyth the layte the vſynge of theyr marchandyſe eyther in towne or in churche on the holydaye / and he dampneth more ſtreytly among theſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious preſtes byenge of theyr benefyces / and
<pb facs="tcp:8704:49"/>
ſellynge of theyr ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctour O do ſayth / vpon the ſame goſpell / they ben ſellers of doues / that ſellen ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all thynges / &amp; though they crye not with there mouthes neuertheleſſe they ſayen with Iudas. what wyl ye geue / and I wyll betraye hym to you? Thus cryen our Monkes &amp; other baſtarde religyon that ſellen / as they may take therfore: their habyte / &amp; theyr ſuffrages / and other preſtes done alſo wyckedly that treten deuyne ſeruyce / and ſuche ben nowe multiplyed in the church of god / therfore where as thou weneſt that the houſe of prayer is / ther ſhalt thou redely fynde a denne of many theues. Forſothe al that entren not by the dore / that is Chriſt / but by money or by ſeculer fauour: they ben nyght theues &amp; day theues that entre in by a broken wall vnwetynge Ieſu Chryſte / for he proueth not theyr dedes / and that is vnkno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wynge. For that is the churche nowe all to bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken downe / whan the vnable is auaunced to the churche benefyce / eyther for prayer / eyther for pryce / eyther for vndewe ſeruyce / ſythen our lorde Ieſu Chryſte ſayde to his dyſcyples that one of them was a deuyll / and mente it by Iudas / be not theſe apoſtates that done as yuel as he / worthy to be clepyd deuylles / by the ſame reaſon they be great queſtyoners &amp; aſkers of the lawe / but they wolde not do ſo moche as put therto theyr fynger / and they bepen charge on othere more than they may bere. They bene prayfers of ſayntes / and nothynge theyr fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers / they bene herers of the lawe / but
<pb n="l" facs="tcp:8704:49"/>
nothyng the doers / they bene alwaye lernyng / and neuer wylbe parfyte. Thus they boſten in the lawe with worſhyp and with wynnynge / but by brekynge of the lawe they done dyſpyſe theyr god. The fourthe commaundemente of god is thys Exod. 20. worſhyp thou thy fader and thy mother that thou mayſte be longe ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge on the erthe the whiche the lorde god ſhal gyue to the / and it ſueth of thys commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that they that worſhyppen not there pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes ſhullen haue ſhorte lyfe here in erthe / and after the londe of myſchyefe. And therfore Thobye. taught hys ſonne a lytle afore hys dyenge. Thobye. 4. Sonne bery thou my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye / and thou ſhalt haue worſhype to thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all the dayes of her lyfe. Thou oweſt for to haue in mynde what parell and howe many ſhe hathe ſuffred in her wombe for the. Some counten it no ſynne to take from theyr parentes ſuche thynges as they haue bycauſe they bene theyr chyldren. But certes thys ſynne paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thefte / and more it greuyth god / as the wyſeman ſaith. Prouerb. xxviij. who that with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>drawyth any thyng from his fader and moder / and ſayth it is no ſynne / he is pertener of man ſlaughter / for worſhyp of our pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / ſtandeth in worde and dede / bothe to teche and to rule them yf they be lewde or poore / and it longeth to theſe pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes to gouerne wel theyr children: &amp; ordeyne not only for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodes of this world but moch rather dyſpoſe theyr lyfe towarde the bliſſe of heuen / as the wyſema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth / prouerb.
<pb facs="tcp:8704:50"/>
xxiij. wyll thou withdrawe techynge from the chylde for though thou bete him with a yerde / he ſhal not dye theron. Thou betyſt them with a beleſſe / and thou ſhalt delyuer hys ſoule from hel / he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſparyth the yerde / hatyth his chylde / forſoth he that loueth them woll teche them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyly / for a wyſe chylde gladdeth the fader / and afeltyd childe is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſorow of his mother / againſt this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundemet the fende with his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers / what with ypocrytes / that is fayned holynes / what with blynde pyte / that regnyth in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clers he hath encombred Chriſtes churche with moch worldly mucke / and euer lad our mother with temporal poſſeſſions that ſhe may not ryſe to heuenly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templacyon / therfore theyr owne chyldren waxen wylde &amp; wanten / and wyl ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther take awe ne lawe / alas this is a greate ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe but our father that is in heuen to whome nothynge is hyd ſeynge his ſonnes ſo frowarde: is ſteryd all to wrathe though y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he abyde longe and differ his vengeaunce / ſufferynge from day to day yf that they wold amende for he forbade to preſtes of the olde lawe to take ſuch poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on amonge other trybes / but holde them payde of his parte / for he wolde be theyr herytage / for they ſhulde prynt thys lore / and neuer go therfro. Thre times it is reherſed / though ones myght haue ſuffyſed. Fyrſt in the boke of Nume<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry .xviij. The ſeconde in deuteromij .xviij. The thyrde in ezechiell .xliiij. And Chriſt in his goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell twyſe forbedyth his preſtes to haue thys
<pb n="li" facs="tcp:8704:50"/>
temporall lordeſhyp / &amp; reygne euen as worldly kynges. Ones in his wyrchynge he forſoke it hym ſelfe. Io. 6.<note place="margin">Io. 6.</note> And alſo in hys techynge that enemyes ſhulde not ſay who may lyue as Chriſt dyde? And neuertheles Gregory ſayth.<note place="margin">Gregor</note> Omeli. vij. Our lorde Ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt ſomtyme with wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſomtyme with dedes techyth vs. Forſothe his dedes ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes for when he doth any thynge ſtyl in that he maketh knowen to vs what we ſhall do / and notwithſtandynge that Chriſt forbedyth ſuche poſſeſſyons by worde to his preſtes. Math. xx. Mar. x. Luce. xxij. And if enemyes wil not accept god in his both lawes neyther obey to theyr father / for his worde ne for his dede / to whome heuen erth &amp; hell knelen on theyr knees / but ſtanden ſtyll obſtynate as yuel wyly traytours to clenſe theyr mother ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly church owyth not to take of this foule corrup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Then ſhullen we ley forth holy ſayntes / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpeken of this matter / and ſaye whether they wolde accorde to wordes that they haue ſayde / and ſo ryſe vp to goddes worde / by theſe ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Saynt Auſten ſayth. The churche owyth not to take tho thynges that ben profered to her of hym that hathe none heyre. Therfore who that euer wyll make the church his eyre / ſeke he another that may take it / but on no wiſe ſayth Auſten but by the mercy of god he ſhall fynde no man. And Ierome ſayth. From y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme that the church grewe in poſſeſſions / ſhe hathe leſſed or dwyned in vertues / but Bernarde for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bedyth theſe poſſeſſyons to be in preſtes handes
<pb facs="tcp:8704:51"/>
and ſpekyth vnto Eugeny the Pope in theſe wytty wordes. Li. 1. Chalenge thou theſe poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions by a nother reaſon / but thou may not chalenge them by the apoſteles ryght. Howe myght the apoſtele gyue that he had not? that he had he gaue / beſynes vpon churches no whether ſecler lordſhyp? here what he ſaith / neyther lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergy: but made in fourme to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte of the flocke / and not only in mekenes trowe thou this to be ſayd / but alſo in trouth of dede. As Chriſt ſayth in his goſpell. Kynges of the erthe lorden ouer them / forſothe ye not ſo. It is playne to the apoſteles that this lordſhype is enterdyted / howe dariſt thou than take thys lordſhyp vpon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> / eyther lordynge apoſtle hede / eyther apoſtle hede to lordſhyp? Playnly thou arte forbodden the one for yf thou wylt haue both / thou ſhalt leſe both y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſthode &amp; thy lordſhyp / or elles thou ſhalt ben except of this nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre / of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which god pleyneth him. They haue reygned / but not by me. They haue bene prynces / but I haue not knowen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / nowe yf auayle to raygne without god / than haſt thou ioye but anemptyſt god / &amp; when preſtes holden this enterdityng / hear they then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes crye / he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is more among you be ye made as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers / &amp; he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is the forgoare / be he made as the maſter. This is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſteles lyuinge. Seculer lordſhyp is forboden / but miniſtryng &amp; ſeruyng is boden. wel we weten of beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god &amp; his law bene euyn accordyng to gedre / &amp; theſe with them / than lay beſides your poyſons / and
<pb n="lii" facs="tcp:8704:51"/>
your hethen tales: with al other ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geled lawes &amp; confirme you to god to clenſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church &amp; bryng it agayn to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former eſtate / &amp; lyue ye on chriſtes parte / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes might haue ther lordſhip agayn. But yet ye maken purſute with money greate ſhowres / &amp; ſayen that ſaint Silueſter toke this poſſeſſion / &amp; ſaynt Swithune / &amp; ſaynt william with many other ſaintes. To this we ſeyne that Silueſter with ſuch other folowers weren ſain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. To this we ſeyne / in this talkynge of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall poſſeſſyons / as was Peter for ſakynge Chriſt / &amp; Paul purſuyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of god. Peter &amp; Paule dyd very penaunce &amp; ſuffreden deth for Chriſtes ſake / yf theſe men dyd the ſame / thus ben they very ſayntes. The firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of god is this. Exo. xx. Thou ſhalt not kyll or ſlee / neyther in malice with purſuynge / ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in worde with backbytynge / neyther with dede in vnlefull ſhedyng of bloude. Of the fyrſt ſpekyth. 1. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 3. He that hatith his brother / <note place="margin">1. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 3.</note> is a manſleer / ſome haten ſynne in man and this is a parfyte hate. Pſalmus. 118.<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.</note> I hated them with a parfyte hate. &amp;c. Some haten ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in man and they be manſleers / for who that ſaythe he loueth his god and hatith thus his bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther / he is a lyer &amp; ther is no truth in him. Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſpekith the ꝓphete &amp; ſayth. Pſal. 13.<note place="margin">Pſal. 13.</note> The mouth of a backbyter is ful of curſidnes &amp; bytter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / &amp; his fete ben ſwyfte to ſhed out blode. For ſaynt Bernard ſayth. The backbyter &amp; the wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful herer either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> berith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl in ther tong &amp; this backbyter ſleeth thre at ones / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay:
<pb facs="tcp:8704:52"/>
his owne ſoule / the wylfull herer / and them that they falſely ſclaunderen. Of the thyrde it is wryten. Gene. 4. Howe that curſed Caym ſlewe his innocent brother Abel / and howe his bloude cryeth to god from the erthe. For ſaynte Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth. Apoc. 6. I ſawe vnder the aulter the ſoules of them that weren ſlayne for the worde of god / and wytneſſe that they hadden / and they cryed with a great voyce ſayeng / holy lorde and true / tyll whan ſhalt thou abyde or thou wylt iuge and venge our bloude on them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dwellen in erthe and it is ſayd vnto them / that they ſhalbe ſtyll yet a litle whyle / tyl theyr fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes be comyn / and theyr bretherne that bene to be ſlayne / as they ben the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe. Vnderſtande thou that god forfendyth all vnlawful ſleynge. As Cryſoſtome declareth Omeli. To ſmyte is vnyuſtly to ſmyte forſothe who that ſmyteth for the cauſe of ryghtfulnes / he is not ſeen to ſmyte / by tytle of goddes lawe / forſoth he ſmy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth not to venge his owne wretchefull herte / but to do the wyll of god / and to ſaue his neygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bours ſoull / as iuſte wrath is no wrath / but a feruent diligence / ſo is rightwyſe ſmytynge no ſmytynge / but agaynſt amendynge. For by ſuch a feruent loue / Phinyes ſlwe two lecherous / &amp; tourned the wrathe of god from the chyldren of Iſrael / as it is wryten. Numeri. xxv Alſo god ſende his hoſtis. Tytus and Vaſpaſyan two and fourty wynter after that Chriſt was ſlayne for to venge Chriſtes dethe vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> curſed Iewes / as it is wryten. Math. xxij. Fyue thynges men
<pb n="liii" facs="tcp:8704:52"/>
muſt auoyde whan they ſhullen go to batayle / for they ben agaynſt this heſte. And thus ſaythe ſaynt Auſten. Couetyſe of noyenge. Cruelty of auengynge / vnpeaſeablenes of mynde / ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of fyghtynge / luſt of lordſhyppynge / and what ben like to theſe: for theſe ben tho thinges that of ryght ben blamed in batayle agaynſt this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the fende in his members ſettyth watche / &amp; beſy ſpye / where that he may fynde any people that woll rede preuy or aparte god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des lawe in englyſſhe that is our mother tonge: anone he ſhalbe ſumnyd to come afore his iuges to anſwere what is ſayde to them / and brynge his boke with hym / and eyther he muſt forſake his boke and redynge of englyſſhe / and algates he ſhall forſwere to ſpeke of holy wrytte. They ſeyne / lyue thou as thy father dyd / and that is ynowe for the / or elles thou ſhalt to preſon as yf thou were an heretyke / and ſuffre paynes ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny and ſtraunge and lykely the dethe / but thou wylte reuoke thy worde and make an open won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derment at thy paryſſhe churche at home: or in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commyn place / and with this they priſon many an hungry ſoule. wherof groweth in this realme a greuous goſtely morreyne / for who dare nowe in theſe dayes talke of Chryſte or of his dome? and certes the body cannot lyue without bodely foode / no more may the ſoule without goddes worde. As ſaynt Auſten ſayth.<note place="margin">Auſtyn.</note> The ſoule dyeth for hunger but yf it be fedde with heuenly brede &amp; this brede is goddes word. As Chriſt ſayth in his goſpel. Math. 4. Deut. 4. Mar. 1. Luc. 4.
<pb facs="tcp:8704:53"/>
A man lyueth not only in bodelye brede but he lyueth a better lyfe after his ſoule of eche word that paſſeth from the mouth of god. God taught longe afore this hungre / for to come that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taught men ſhulde aſke this brede / and no man ſhulde geue it them / as he ſayth by the mouth of the ꝓphete Amos. Loo dayes commen ſayth the lorde / and I ſhall ſuffre hungre to be ſent into the erthe / neyther of brede ne of water / but of herynge the worde of god / than men ſhullen be moued from the one ſee to the other / and from the northe / to the eeſt / ſekynge the worde of god / and they ſhall not fynde it / ſayth the lorde god. For there ben many prechours but theyr bene fewe trewe prechours / and yf any preche the trouthe / the multytude ſhal agayne ſay him / and thus me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abyden ſtyl in theyr goſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hungre for they wete neuer whom to folowe: theyr prechynge is ſo wonderful / ioynynge in theyr curyous wordes the trouth to the falſhede who that hauntyth to thys brede for to ſleke hys hungre thoughe he were ſo holye as euer was ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the baptyſt he ſhulde not fayle to be ſclaundrede for a curſed lollarde / and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued as an heretyke of theſe cruell enmyes. But in this they bene moche worſe than the hethen folkes / that trowen in theyr mawmettes for wantyng of byleue / but theſe haue receaued the fayth / and falſely gone therfro / and alſo dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen beeſtly men / to pynde them in theyr pound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde / without goſtely meate and drynke / tyll they ſterne for hungre. But we reden y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary
<pb n="liiii" facs="tcp:8704:53"/>
of an hethen kyng for he dyed moch beter to the chyldren of Iſraell. 4. Reg. whan the chyldren of Iſraell beganne to dwell in ſamary they dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den not the lorde / and the lorde ſent amonge them lyons that ſlewe them / and than it was tolde to the kynge of Aſſyre / and ſayde. The folke that thou haſte tranſlated and made them to dwell in the cytees of ſamarye / they knowe not theyr lawfull thynges of the god of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erthe. Forſothe the kynge of Aſſyrye commaunded / ſayeng / ledeth thether one of the preſtes that ye haue brought into this thraldome that ye may go and with them dwell / and teche them the lawfull thynges of the god of the erthe. God graunt our chriſten kynges to marke well this ſtory / that they mouen paſſe this hethen kynge in thys forſayde matter / than ſhulde lyons / that bene ſynnes / ſone be dyſtroyed / yf all men had the lawe wryten in theyr hertes. As the lorde ſayth. Ieremy .xxxi.<note place="margin">Iere. 31.</note> I ſhall gyue my lawe in the bowelles of them / and I ſhal wryt my lawe in the hertes of them. O ye preſtes ye bene moche to blame that taken from the people the lawe that god hathe wrytten hym ſelfe in the myddes of theyr hertes. So thorowe you theſe foreſayde lyons nowe bene commen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge vs / that all to teren Chryſtes ſhepe / and murtheren them to the dethe Certes ye ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer lerned thys lore in dedes of thapoſteles / for thys it is wryten. Acte. viij. Lo a clene chaſte man the quenes treaſourer of ynde / thoughe he weren and hethen man and had not taken
<pb facs="tcp:8704:54"/>
the fayth / yet he rad in Eſaye / ſyttyngr in the chayre. Philip toke not away his boke / neyther he warned hym to rede therin. But what than? Philip declared him the prophecye / and taught him for to vnderſtande it / tyl he beleued on Ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt to be goddes ſonne of heuen. what betyde than of Philyp by ſtyryng of the ſpyryte. whan this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beleued / confermed in Chriſtes name / &amp; gaue to him the baptyme. Howe do ye Preſtes parfourme Chryſtes heſtes and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſteles lore that ſtoppen trewe chriſten men from workes of theyr chriſtendome. The apoſteles vſed not that maner whan they went aboute to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple and to mennes houſes prechynge and teachyng both to Iewes and to the hethen men the lawes of Ieſu Chryſte. Act. 5. Forſothe eche day in the temple and aboute houſes / they ceſſed not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge and techynge Ieſu Chryſte. The ſyxte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of god is this. Exo. xx. Thou ſhalt do no Lechery / neyther with thyne eye / in lecherous lokynge / neyther with thyne hert: in luſty thynkynge / neyther with thy body in dede doynge. And thys ſynne is forboden. In ſengle. In wedded / and in wedowes. Of the fyrſt ſpekyth ſaynt Auſten and ſaith. An vnchaſt eye is the meſſanger of an vnchaſt herte. Of the ſeconde ſpekyth Chriſt in his goſpll.<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> Math. 5. who that hath ſeen a woman to do his luſt with her / anone he hath done lechery with her in hys herte. In this techyth Chryſte howe the rote of ſynne ſpryngeth from the herte. Of the thyrde ſpekyth Paule. Ephe. 5. Forſoth knowe ye this
<pb n="lv" facs="tcp:8704:54"/>
vnderſtandynge that neyther fornycatour ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnclene fylthy / neyther auarous wrethe that is ſeruage of ydoles / hath herytage in the realme of Chriſt and god. Howe euer thou luſt to trete the members of thy body agayne the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of thy ſoule / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou arte a lecherour / and therfore ſhulde bothe man and woman lerne to kepe theyr body in clennes and in vertue to the worſhyp of theyr god / and not in foule bren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge deſyres as folkes that knowen no reaſon. And ſaynt Auſten ſayth.<note place="margin">Auſten.</note> God hath geuen to the power by the holy goſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou holde thy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers from paſſyng of reaſon / luſt ryſyth / holde thou thy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers nyll thou geue thy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers / armour of wyckednes to ſyn / arme thou not thyne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary agaynſt the to thyne owne harme holde thy fete that they go not to vnlawful thynges / luſte hath ryſen / witholde thou thy members / holde thyne ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des from al felony withold thyn eyen / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they tende not to yuell witholde thyne eares that they here not the tales of lecherye / witholde all thy body / holde thy ſydes holde hye / holde lowe / what can luſt do? Ryſe it can: ouer come it can not. Agaynſte this commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement the fende in his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers holdeth a courte (as he ſaith) of holy church lawe from one weke to a nother / for to correcte ſynners / and ther they clepen by name the lecherour &amp; his feere / that ledyth theyr lyfe in horedome to ioyne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to theyr penaunce. That is to walke thre mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket dayes aboute the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men market / bareheded in theyr ſhertes / without hoſen and ſhoen / and
<pb facs="tcp:8704:55"/>
other thre ſondayes aboute theyr paryſſh church with a taper in theyr hande of a pounde of waxe and go before the paryſſhe preſte to beten them with a yerde / alſo ſtandynge on theyr fete tyll maſſe beſayde / and than offre thre candeles to the hye aulter. The ſumner is full buſye in all this meane tyme / to rowne in theyr eares &amp; byd them aſke grace / for ye ſhal haue better grace / do by my cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeyl / pay downe money from your purſes to my lorde / &amp; ye ſhall fynde him graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to releſe your penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Than they take their leue both / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ben taxed to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynue ſtyl in theyr horedome / as they deden toſore / ye tyll theyr deth day: ſo that this rent be payd. Certes this is a curſed ſyn that our byſſhopes vſen for to maynteyne lecherours in theyr owne howſes: and maken them theyr ordenaryes that letten ſyn to great hyre for theyr lordes almes. Here ye what god ſaythe to you. Ezech. xliiij. Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foce they to you / houſe of Iſraell / all your greate felonyes / that ye vſen amonge you by cauſe that ye brynge in alyen ſonnes vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſed in herte / and in theyr fleſſhe alſo / that they bene in my ſentwary / and defoule myne houſe / and ye offren my loues / my blode / and my grece / but ye vndo my couenaunte in all your foule felonyes / and ye haue not kepte in dede the byddynge of my ſaynctwary / but ye haue ſette the wardeyns of my ſeyntwarye and obſeruauntes to your owne auauntages theſe thynges ſayth the lorde god. Thys is the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> morall wyte of this forſayde ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tence: hye pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates
<pb n="lvi" facs="tcp:8704:55"/>
of the churche ſhullen thynke theron / of theyr owne great ſynnes to gyue a rekenynge afore god at domeſday / and they wolde well auyſe them though they dyd not ſacre to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> order of preſthode vnclene men in body and ſoule that ſeke to be preſtes neyther in vertue / neyther in ſpirite / but for to lyue in luſtes / theſe polluten Chriſtes churche / his fleſſhe / and his blode / &amp; cauſen why that goddes lawe is taken for theyr falſe courte / not chriſten lawe but curſed lawe / is holde amonge the people. This was not theyr couenaunt at one dayes tyme whan they hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten fayth and trouth to ſue Chriſtes ſteppes and kepe his byddynges in them ſelfe / and alſo to teche them to othere men / but nowe they ſetten ordynaryes for theyr wordly profytes that he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen their purſe with money of many foulde ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / but the ſoules that god chargyth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with: to haue cure on / and brynge them to the blyſſe of heuen as ſhepe vnto the folde / they chare not whether they ſynke or ſwymme / ſo they may reygne as lordes. Thus ben all thre eſtates enfected with Lecherye / from the lewde man vnto the clerke &amp; none amende other / &amp; therfore the lorde ſayth. Ieremy. 5. I haue fed them and they haue done lechery / they haue ben horeles / <note place="margin">Iere. 5.</note> in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men bordle houſe. They ben as fiers on women / as horſes ben on mares / and they ben made ſtalowens that ſeruen for that office / eche man waxyth wode after hys neybours wyfe vpon theſe thynges I ſhall vyſyte ſaythe the lorde god / &amp; vpon theſe folke I ſhall venge my
<pb facs="tcp:8704:56"/>
wyll / ſayth the lorde god. The .vij. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of god is this. Exo. xx. Thou ſhalt do no thefte / neyther Knyghtes by tyranny / neyther preſtes by ypocreſy / neyther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myns by ſtelthe or robbery. Of the fyrſte it is wryten. Yſay. 1. Thy prynces ben vnfaythfull / and felowes of theues / al they that louen gyftes they folowen rewardynges / they deme not ryghtfull dome to the moderles chylde / the cauſe of the wedowe entryth not to them. Of the ſeconde ſpekyth Chriſt in his goſpell .x.<note place="margin">Io. 10.</note> He that entryth not by the doore into the folde of ſhepe / but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myth in a nother way / he is a nyght theſe / and a day theſe / this is expounded in the thyrde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement.<note place="margin">Paule.</note> Of the thyrde ſpekyth Paule. Ephe. 4. He that ſtale / ſtele he nomore / rather trauayle eche worchynge with hys handes that thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is good / that we may haue wherof to dele to him that ſuffryth nede. Lorde yf they ſhulde be dampned as the goſpel ſayth. Luc. xvi. that ſpenden not the true goten goodes after the fourme of Chriſtes techynge wher ſhall they than be punyſſhrd that waſten theyr owne / or hyden theyr owne / &amp; falſely ſtelen other men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Saynt Paule ſayth. 1. Corynt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Theues ſhall not poſſeſſe the realme of heuen / and in this be contayned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> threfolde ſtelynges / but ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then that god hath ordeyned al thyng in numbre weyght / and meſure / as the wyſeman ſayth. who that falſyth any of theſe thre / or falſely vſeth them he is a thefe and worthy payne as the wyſeman ſayth. Prouerb .xi. A trecherous
<pb n="lvii" facs="tcp:8704:56"/>
or a falſe balance is abhomynacyon enemptyſt god / an euen weyght is the lordes wyll as it is ſayd. Leuitic. xix. wyll thou do any thynge vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinly in any of theſe foure / In dome / In rule / In weyght / In meſure. Loke thy balance be iuſte / and thy weyghte euen. Loke thy buſſhell be iuſte / and thy meaſur euen / I am your lorde god. Agaynſt this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement the fende with his cautyles hath whyled into the church many ſtraunge theues that done ſtele bothe nyght and day &amp; yet they ben not hanged / but god hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned for them galowes in hell / &amp; they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ben ons hanged theer / ſhal neuer be delyuered / but they that hangen on ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes galowes by iugeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this world / oftyn by this ſhameful deth &amp; by very repentaunce ben ſaued from endeles payne and ſo was the thefe that hanged on Chryſtes ryght ſyde in tyme of his paſſyon / but they that fallen bacwardes and mowen not ſe theyr fall / they hangen on Chriſtes lefte ſyde in peryll of theyr ſoull / from whom Chriſt tourneth / hys gracious face. As the prophete ſayth / ſpekynge by the mouth of Chryſt to theſe forſayd theues. Iſay .lix. Your wyckednes hath made a deuorce betwyxt the lorde and you / &amp; your ſynnes haue hyd away from you his gracious face / that he ſhulde not here you whan ye cryen vpon hym. Forſothe your handes ben ful of blode / &amp; your fyngers bene ful of ſyn. Your lyppes haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken leſynges and your tounge ſpekyth wycked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / the face of god is take here for his grace in mannes mynde in another place it is taken for
<pb facs="tcp:8704:57"/>
Chriſtes incarnacyon / and in another place it is taken for the glory of god in hys euerlaſtynge maieſtye / and theſe thre ben tourned away from theſe forſayde ſpoylours / and the cauſe why / the ꝓphete ſayth. Bene theſe two thynges theyr handes: and theyr fyngers ben ful of bloude and wyckednes vpon this ſayth pariſiens. who that hath eyther by thefte or robberye / eyther by ſtreynght or tyranny / eyther by fraude or gyle as ypocreſye tho thynges of whiche the poore owed to be nouryſſhed he hathe his handes pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted in poore mennes blode. And who that clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyth hym with ſuch goddes or fedyth him with ſuche goddes / or reryth vp buyldyng with ſuch goddes than is he clad in poore mennes bloude / than is he fed with poore mennes bloude / than groundeth he hys buyldynge on poore mennes bloude. Some men ſayen it is no ſynne to take what men wyll gyue them. Some ſayen they woll ſpende theyr goodes there they haue moſte deuocyon. Some morteſyn / howſe lande / wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and wode into ded handes. To you we aſke this queſtyon. what profyteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hande without the fyngers / or the fyngers without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hande? Yf we may ſay that eyther of them may wyrche hys werke without other to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ꝓfyte / than may ye ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuocyon may ꝓfyt without diſcre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion &amp; elles not / for thus it is wryten. Cant. 5. Myne handes haue dropped myrre / &amp; my fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers moſt ꝓued myrre / theſe ben y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of a true ſoul. Vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ſayth ſaynt Bernarde. Deuo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out diſcrecion lyeth voyde &amp; doth no good: deſcrecyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out deuocion throwyth downe hede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng
<pb n="lviii" facs="tcp:8704:57"/>
he is bleſſed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tith neither of theſe: loke what it ꝓfytith to haue Chriſt in manhode w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out his godhede / or to haue a body without a ſoule: or to haue fayth in word without any dede / or to haue letter w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding: or to haue a lampe without oyle / ſo ꝓfiteth deuocion with out diſcrecion. Some men yet beſy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne this thefte &amp; ſayen / theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ye mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ben deuoute prayers / &amp; good prechours / &amp; algates among them god is fayre ſerued. As to theyr prechynge Chriſte anſweryth and ſayth. Math. 7. Luc. 12. Many ſhal come to Chriſt / &amp; ſay to hym in the day of dome. Lorde / Lorde / haue we not preched in thy name. Saint Auſten ſayth. The lorde ſhall not deny this. For who ſo euer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> precher be / a deuoute herer may wyn hym mede. But Chriſt ſhall knowlege to them and ſay / for I knowe you neuer / that is to ſay. I approued neuer your werkes / go ye from me: all ye that wroken wyckednes / and as to theyr prayers ſaynt Auſten ſayth in a boke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he made of monkes lyfe. It ꝓfitith not to pray / &amp; lete y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land lyg lay &amp; as to theyr fayre ſeruice / as it is ſaid afore: god is now here faire ſeruid / but ther as his law is fayre kept: but in theſe .iii. they diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyuen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of ther beleue / &amp; robben the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ther vertue / &amp; alſo ſpoylen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theyr goodes as it is wryten. Miche. 4. Theſe thynges ſayth the lorde god vpon prechours that diſceyuen my people as with theyr prechynge that byten with theyr tethe / as for theyr prayenge / and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chen peace / as for theyr fayre ſeruynge / &amp; who that wol not geue ſomwhat to the mouthe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8704:58"/>
they halowen batayle vpon hym / therfore the lorde ſayth. Nyght ſhalbe to you for your vyſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / and derkeneſſe for your dyuynacyon. Theſe woll be meke without dyſpyte / poore without defaute / well clade without beſynes / dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cately fed without trauayle / whyly flatterers to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they begylen: yuyl whyly traytours to them that they haten / haſtye purſuers of them that they ſclaunderen ſore byters as dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / dyſceytefull as foxes / proude as lyons / enuyous as adders / without forth as ſhepe / within as rauyſſhynge wolues / they woll be iuges without authoryty / and at the laſt falſe accuſers / and waſtynge all vertue / &amp; therfore the wyſeman ſayth. Prouerb. 6. That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde both hatith &amp; loueth them that ſoweth dyſcorde amonge neybours. Theſe ypocrytes wyll not fuffre any darte of coreccyon to thrylle them / but in eche ſyn that they done / they leyen forth the bokeler of proude defence / and whan any of them is blamed of his wyckednes / he wyll not thinke anone how / he may amende it: but he ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyth beſyly helpe howe he may defende it. The viij. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god is this. Exo. xx. Thou ſhalt not ſpeke falſe wytneſſe agaynſt thy ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour / neyther for geftes takynge / ne for man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſteryng / neyther thy ſelfe in ſynne exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge. Of the fyrſte it is wryten. Iſaye. 5. wo to you that iuſtyfyen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / for geftes / and take away the ryghtwyſnes of a iuſte man for he may not pay. Of the ſeconde ſpekyth a wyſe man. Prouerb. xix. A falſe wytnes berer
<pb n="lix" facs="tcp:8704:58"/>
ſhall not be vnponyſſhed / and he that ſpekyth lyes ſhal peryſſhe as the prophete ſaith. Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.</note> Lorde thou ſhalt leſe all tho that ſpekyn leſyng. For the wyſeman ſayth. Sap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. The mouthe that lyeth ſleeth the ſoule. And therfore Chriſte ſayth. Io. viii.<note place="margin">Io. 8.</note> Ye lyers bene the ſonnes of your father the deuyll and ye wyll do the deſyres of your father. He was a manſlear fro the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge / for he ſtode not in trouthe / for trouth is not in hym / whan he ſpekyth leſynge / he ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyth of his owne authorytye / for he is a lyer &amp; father of lyenge. Of the thyrde ſpekyth the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phete. Pſalmus. 14.<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.</note> Lord put thy warde to my mouthe / and odour of circumſtaunce to my lyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes / bowe thou not my herte into the wordes of malyce / to excuſacions to be excuſyd in ſyn. For the wyſeman ſayth. Prouerb. 2. They that maken mery whan they haue done yuell &amp; ioyen in worſt thynges be they punyſſhed with endeles paynes. Agayne thys commaundement the fende with his cautylles hath gyue leue to. xij. men for .xij. grotes to paſſe forth on a queſt agayne ryghtwyſe blode / and ſay a falſe wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe / that the man is gyltye and anone he ſhal be ded thoughe it wer Chriſt him ſelfe. In this the fendes members grounden them on Iezebel. iij. Reg. xxi. For ſhe ſent letters in the name of Achab ſealed with his ſignate to Inreours of the countre and charged them that they ſhulde ceſſe two men ſonnes / that myght ſay falſe wyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe agaynſt the knyghte Nabothe that he had both waryed god and the kynge / and by thys
<pb facs="tcp:8704:59"/>
falſe wytneſſe they ſlowen this gyltles knight. Certes ſo in our dayes who that medyth thys Iurours that ben the ſonnes of belyall and queſt mongers / he may ſlee / and he may ſaue. Thus falſe wer neuer the Iewes / for whan the two olde preſtes that brent in lechery of the woman Suſan. As the ſtory tellyth. Danyel .xiii. And ſhe wolde not conſente to do theyr foule luſte / than they gaue a ſentence of her falſe wytneſſe / wherby ſhe was iuged worthy to be deed / &amp; as ſhe was lad to the fyre / ſhe made her deuoute prayer / and than god reryd vp / the herte of a yonge man that was clepyd Danyell / and he reuoked her dome / &amp; repreued theſe olde preſtes of theyr falſe wytnes / ſo that godes angel with a ſherp ſwerde ſlewe them for theyr falſe dome in ſyght of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people / &amp; they prayſed god al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty of this fayre delyuerau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Howe ſhulde ye Iurryours ſcape the fyre of hell / that (for a lytle money) wol dampne ye reckneuer whom / and dyſheryte trwe heyres of theyr iuſte hery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage / for tho / that wollen not ſay the truthe / but yf they taken mede / ſellen Chryſte / that is truthe / and bene worſe then the Iewes / for they ſlowen him whan he came to dye / but now he reygneth vndedly / wher ſhal tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your payne be? that woll ſay falſe wytnes for to catche a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntage of worldly wynnyge? ye ſel your ſelfe your body &amp; your ſoule into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des ſeruice / yet may we ſe more encu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des wirchyng for ther is none offycer temporal nor ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all but that he is redy whan he may to take gyftes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb n="lx" facs="tcp:8704:59"/>
poore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myns / and pyll them euer amonge and elles they ſhall no peace haue / from greuouſſer oppreſſynge / as is taken of theyr beaſtes with corne and other vitayles and other payment get they none / but a whyte ſtycke / tyll they haue loſt halfe on halfe with moche more trauayle. Lorde yf ye marked well that Ietro ſayde to Moyſes. Exo. xviij. Sonne ye ſhulde amende this / or elles ye ben vncurable. Ietro counceled Moyſes that he ſhulde wyſely ordeyne myghty men that dreden god in whome was very trouth and that hated auaryce with al his curſed bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and they ſhulde haue offyce in rulyng vnder Moyſes / Moyſes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſented and wrought after his counſeyl. Therfore / peace / welthe / &amp; grace raigned in hys dayes. Rere vp your wyttes ye Prynces and lordes of this worlde / &amp; ſe howe Kyng Ioſephath charged to his offycers. Paral. xix. Ioſephath ordeyned iuges in all the cytees of Iurye / and gaue them the byddyng / beware what ye do / forſothe he ſaythe this dome that ye haunten is not the dome of man / but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dome of god / &amp; what that ye demen ſhal tourne vpon your ſelfes loke the drede of god be amonge you and dothe all thynges with dylygence / forſothe anemptyſte god is no wyckedneſſe / neyther ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptynge of parſons / neyther couetyſe of geftes and he chargyth preſtes and decans that they ſhulde make knowen al the doubtes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe / left that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people ſynned. Yf this lore were wel lerned of our chriſten prynces and lordes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hard ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of Antechriſt ſhuld be al to broken: chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8704:60"/>
people ſhulde haue leue to do theyr offyce truly: and eche man his fredome to ſerue god in vertue then wer this good gouernaunce and ſauynge to the realme in peace / in welth &amp; in euery eſtate / as Preſtes Knyghtes and commyns. For thus ſayth Cryſoſtom. Omeli. 1. It is to note that who that of kynges hath pleaſed god they haue reygned the longer and they haue ben welthy / &amp; god hath lowed theyr enemyes vnder the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For ſoth as many as haue done wyckedly they haue ben cut vp haſtely both from their raigne &amp; from theyr lyfe with a better deth / &amp; god hath lowed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder their enemyes thraldome. The .ix. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of god is this. Exod. xx. Deut. 5. Thou ſhalt not couyte the houſe of thy neybour In the .vij. commaundement / god forbedeth the vnlefull takynge of other mennes goodes and ſo in that he refrayneth deſyer of mennes dede / but in this commaundement god forbedyth the couetyſe of vnlawful takynge / and in that he refrayneth the vnordynate appetite of mannes deſyre namely in all tho thynges that bene vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable / that is to ſay that mowen not moue them ſelfe by theyr owne myght from one place to another / as bene houſe / londe / golde / and ſuche other lyke to theſe and this vicious coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe yf it be conceyued groweth to dethe of the ſoule / from the rote of mannes herte / for whan the wyll hathe conſented to do that thynge that god forbedyth though the dede folowe not after in outwarde ſyghte of mannes dome / and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge lettyth to do the dede / ſaue wyll may
<pb n="lxi" facs="tcp:8704:60"/>
not as it wolde / than the ſoule is dede goſtely within the houſe of the body / and this deth is ſignyfyed by a parſons doughter that was dede within her fathers houſe / &amp; Chriſte by myracle gaue her lyfe. Math. 9. Mar. 5. Luc. 8. Some noryſſhen theyr couetyſe tyll it ſprynge into a dede / as a carreyne opynly dede / that lyeth by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way effectyng the people / and this is taught in the wedowes ſonne that was borne deed on a bere without the gates of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cyte for to put him in his graue. Luke. 7.<note place="margin">Luke. 7.</note> Chriſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ered him by hys myracle / and gaue hym agayne to hys moder. Some feden theyr foule couetyſe with luſt and delectacion / in thought / in word / &amp; in werke / and this moſte abhomynable / for it waa ſhewed in Lazarus. Io. xi. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lay .iiii. dayes in hys graue. And Chriſt by myracle / <note place="margin">Io. 11.</note> to tourne the Iewes rered vp his body and gaue him the ſpirite. All theſe thre ben agaynſte thys commaundement of god / and ben worthy endeles payne / but yf god thorough his gracious mercy moue them to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and to very penaunce / that ben deed in theſe forſayd foule couetyſes / that is to ſay / in coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe of hert / of dede / and of cuſtome. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the wyſeman ſayth. Eccli. xviij. Go not away from thy god after thyne owne couetyſes. Lorde howe ſhulde he kepe hym from a vycyous dede that doth not out of hys herte the couetyſe therof? Certes it is as impoſſyble as to ſaue the houſe from brennyng that thou ſettyſt afyre with thyne owne ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. A wede may not be diſtroied but yf it be drawen vp by the rotes. No more
<pb facs="tcp:8704:61"/>
may ſynne be lefte / but yf the delectable coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe of ſynne be pulled out of the herte. For yf theyr abyde any parte of this foule couetyſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawen vp in herte / anone theyr ſpryngeth vp therof / thefte / falſe purchaſe / and ſuche other. And therfore ſayde Moyſes vnto the chyldren of Iſraell. Deut. xix. Thou ſhalt not take / ne thou ſhalt not paſſe the termes or the bondes of thy neybour the which thyne elders haue ſet in thy poſſeſſyon that thy lorde god ſhall gyue to the / for who that takythe away his neybours grounde / that is to ſay / lande or place / wode or water / corne or graſſe / in fylde or in towne: thorough any of theſe forſayd couetiſes he ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in that a curſed of god and hys lawe / for thus it is wryten. Deut. xxvii. Curſed be that man or woman that paſſyth the bandes of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meaſure betwene theyr neyboures &amp; them. Agayne this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement the fende with hys cautyles hath larged this couetyſe to all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that vnneth any man takyth hede howe that he come by good that he were ryche. Commyns haue purchaſed at Antechriſtes proctour to be fermours of the churche and all for couetyſe of wynnyng / &amp; by this paryſſhons ben brought in many cuſtomes / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dyſtroyen peace / &amp; noryſſhen debate / and quenchen goddes lawe / but who ſo euer ſayth or byddeth beſydes goddes wyl / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is not ꝓued in holy wryt / &amp; openly declared / he is a falſe wytneſſer / and doth curſed ſacrilege / &amp; ſo ſayth ſaynt Auſten. whan the lorde god hathe ſayed in his goſpell. I am trouthe / he ſayd not
<pb n="lxii" facs="tcp:8704:61"/>
I am cuſtome. Than whan the trouth is ſhewed cuſtome muſte nedes geue ſteed to trouth. Peter that circumcyſed conſented to Paule prechynge the trouth. Therfore ſithen Chriſt is trouth we owen moche more to ſewe trouth than cuſtome / for euermore reaſon and trouth ſhullen exclude cuſtome whan reaſon and trouth excluden theſe fermoures and all theyr falſe cuſtomes he is a very membre of the deuyll that maynteneth the contrary / and makyth the houſe of Ieſu Chriſte the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men ſhoppe of marchandyſe. But lordes here ben more to blame that ſhulde chaſtyce this ſynne / for ſome bene fermoures them ſelfe / and fauoren for theyr couetyſe that the perſon ſhall haue leue in grutty places as an hogge in the myre / and leue hys cure vnkepte. The lordes in theſe dayes bene ſo ſmytten with couetyſe that they holden falſe goten goodes agaynſte theyr owne conſcyens / and fele ſythys reren ſtronge hande armyd in ſtronge wodeneſſe to call men bothe ſlepynge and wakynge to encreaſe theyr lordſhypes. Kynge Acab for couetyſe of Nabothys vineaerde that he deſired to haue had agayne this knyghtes wyll / layd him ſelfe gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng on his bed and wolde not taſte any mete / for Nabothe ſayed he wolde not chaunge ne ſell hys kynde herytage. But zezebell the wycked quene gaue the kynge ſuche counſayle that they caſten this knyght deth by a falſe ſclaundre / and thus brought them to an ende and reioyſed hys vyneaerde. God ſente worde to Achab &amp; Ieze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell by the ꝓphete Hely / that for they had thus
<pb facs="tcp:8704:62"/>
couetouſly agaynſt his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ther blode ſhulde beſhede on the erthe / and handes ſhulde lyke it. And more god toke vengeaunce for gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſynne vpon the ſede that came of them into the thyrde and fourthe generacion / and yf that we toke hede howe lordes haue ſlayne eche other / in ſhedynge of theyr blode in the fylde for couetyſe of lordynge / we ſhulde not wonder though godes hande be ſtretched ouer his people to ſmyte with vengeaunce as he dothe / and no man may auoyde it.<note place="margin">Couetyſe of lordynge hath / is / &amp; ſhalbe cauſe of moche bloude ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge.</note> And yf thou wylte wete what is this vengeaunce. God ſaith by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete Oſee. iiii. That his vengeaunce is whan he withdrawith hys chatyſynge and the yerde of amendyng and ſuffrith his enemyes to raigne in theyr ſynne tyll theyr deth day / and after to dampne them body and ſoule euer without ende. And to this accordyth ſaynte Gregory in hys moralles vpon. Iob. God ſparyth to ſome in thys lyfe that he may ſmyte them withouten ende. And Iob ſayth .xxi. why lyuen wycked men auaunced and comforted in rycheſſe? The ſede of them dwellyth before them / and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panye of nye frendes and coſens in theyr ſyght: theyr houſes bene ſekyr / and the yerde of god that is cleped his chaſtyſynge / is not vpon them theyr eekfare conceyued / &amp; caſt not her frute or tyme / theyr ko<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e bare her frute / and was not berafte the profyte of her womb. There ſtrepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges gone afore them as flockes of beaſtes / &amp; theyr youngelynges ioyen in pleys &amp; in ga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes: they holden the tymbre and the harpe / and they
<pb n="lxiii" facs="tcp:8704:62"/>
ioyen at the ſounde of the Organne. They le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den theyr dayes in goodes / that is to ſaye / in helthe and in welthe / and in worldly worſhip / and ſodenly in a poynte they dyſcenden or gone downe to helles / but agaynwarde. Salomon in his prouerbes .iii. And ſaynt Paule to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues .xii. Sayen that god reproueth &amp; chaſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all them that he loueth / and receyueth to blyſſe. And therfore ſayth Iohan. 2. Math. 6. It is a token of great goodnes not to ſuffre long tyme ſynners of theyr wycked purpoſe to ſue theyr owne foly / but ſone put to them merciful chaſtyſement / forſothe the lorde doth not ſo with his choſen as he dothe with an alyen na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / that is tho that he forſakyth thorough theyr deſeruynge / and caſtyth them out of hys ſyght / whom he abydeth paciently to punyſſhe them at the full in domeſday / forſoth he hathe not ordeyned ſo to ponyſhe them whome he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyth / but he chaſtyſeth them pacyently &amp; after receyueth them to his gracious fauour and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye. But preſtes in thys couetyſe moſte greuen theyr god / for they bene authours of this ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that we haue ſayde aforne. They ſeyen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue a lawe that they clepen them ſelfe / fredome of holy churche / thoſſe it be boundage of the deuyll / and by this they may purchaſe out of the ſecler hande / ye all theyr lyfelode yf they myght wynne it by one meane or by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / and what they wynne into theyr power theyr may no man wynne it or redeme it agayne into the handes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeclers / fro holy fredome / 
<pb facs="tcp:8704:63"/>
and who ſo dothe ſhalbe ſuſpended from holye churche ryght / and a curſed by theyr lawe / tyll he reſtore it agayne / thus they vndo ſecler par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye with theyr fayned holynes / in clepyng ther ſory churche / holy church / &amp; theyr thraldome / fredome / and magnyfyen theyr ſermons aboue the lawe of god / ſo that lay men ben oppreſſed vnder theſe preſtes / as farre as the Iewes we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren with Scrybes and Pharyſees. The deuell whan he tempted Eue made a fayre ſemblante for to ſtyrre her to couetyſe to breke goddes byd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng in etynge of the appell wherby deth ſhulde entre. This woman ſawe the appell that it was good in beholdyng / and fayre in ſyght / and alſo lykerous in ſmellyng / ſhe ete therof and gaue to her huſbande / he bote therof / than bothe were dedly &amp; loften the ioye of paradyſe. The mayſter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſentence ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this apple is ſyn that god forbedyth / than after the wyt of allegory / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is thus to meane / whan that ſecler men formen ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>al offyce / &amp; whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſtes bowen downe to take temporal lordſhyp by temptyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl in theyr foule couetyſe / than theſe two partyes as Adam &amp; Eue / and they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſentours ben dryuen out of the blyſſe of heuen with the ſharp of goddes worde. Balaam was caught in this co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uetyſe / &amp; his owne beſt repreued hym &amp; hurt his fote agayne a wal for his iourney pleſed not god but this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wold not beware / &amp; therfor he was ſlayne amonge the hethen people. Numeri. xxii. This couetyſe ſtyred Giezi to take mede of Na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aman for a ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>al benefyce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god him ſelfe hathe
<pb n="lxiiii" facs="tcp:8704:63"/>
wrought by his ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Helyſy in clenſynge of his meſebry / &amp; therfore Giezi with his genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon were ſmyten for euer with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leper of Naa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man .iiij. Reg. 5. Anany and Saphir his wyfe ouercommen with thys couetyſe layd in theyr conſcyence afore ſeynt Peters preſence / &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore they dyed both in the ſyn of wanhope. Act. 5. who that redyth this blyſſed lore that is our fayth and goddes lawe / but he leue this coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe / he ſtandyth in peryll of his ſcule / as god ſayth by the ꝓphete Eſaye. 5. wo to you that ioynden houſe to houſe / and couplen fylde to fylde vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> terme of a place / whether no ſhuld ye dwel alone in myddes of the erthe / ſayth the lorde god. In this god forbedith the vnleful co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetyſe that we haue ſayde aforne. For yf thys couetyſe catche not roote in the herte / it ſhall neuer growe to the dede / as it is ſayde afore. And therfore ſayth Paule. 1. Corinth. x. Be we not coueting of yll / as ſome of your elders haue coueted / &amp; we prayen for charytee loke in theſe places / and ſe what hath fallen for this ſynne of couetyſe. Geneſi. iii. Numeri. xiij. xvi. and .xxij. iiij. Reg. 5. Acte. 5. This .x. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god is thys. Exo. xx. Thou ſhall not deſyre thy neyhbours wyfe / ne hys ſeruaunt / ne hys handemayde / ne hys oxe / ne his aſſe / ne thyng that is hys otherwyſe than thou wylt he ſhall deſyre thyne / after reaſon &amp; the law of Chriſtes goſpel. In the .vi. commaundement god forbyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyth the outwarde dede of lechery / &amp; in that he refrayneth the vnlefull treatynge of thy body / 
<pb facs="tcp:8704:64"/>
but in this forbyddeth the inwarde conſent of the herte and in that he refrayneth all vnlefull deſyre or wyll namely in tho thynges that bene immoueable / that is to ſaye that haue no might in them ſelfe to remoue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one place to another for the deſyre and wyll that reſtyth in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde man / makyth merite or ſynne more or leſſe in the preſens of god / for charitable wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes that bene in theyr owne kynde myghty and great ben done ſomtyme with a frowarde wyl / and than they wanten mede / as Chriſt ſayth in his goſpell.<note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> Math. 7. Not eche man that ſayth to me lorde lorde / ſhall entre into the realme of heuennes. A man ſhall not be only ſaued for his good workes ne hys good dedes / wherfore than? But he that dothe the wyll of my fader that is in heuennes / that is to ſay / after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre that a man hath in worde &amp; dede to do the pleſynge wyll of god / he ſhalbe after that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded in blyſſe and by this greatneſſe of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes good wyll thoughe it werke / but lytle in kynde / is aſkyth greate rewarde in blyſſe. And therfore the aungelles ſongen in Chriſtes byrth Luc. 2. Peace be in erthe to men of good wyll / for ſuche a good wyll traueylethe to pleaſe god in worde and in dede / and whan it may no fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtreche / this wyll is counted for a dede / as the maſter of ſentence reherſeth. Saynt Auſten ſayth that this mother ignorance / that we cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen vncunnyngnes / hath thre doughters. The fyrſt ben all tho that myght lerne and wyll not: The ſeconde bene all tho that wolde lerne and
<pb n="lxv" facs="tcp:8704:64"/>
may not. The thyrde / bene all tho that taken none hede. The fyrſte ſhall algates be damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. The ſeconde ſhullen algates be ſaued / be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe that theyr wyl anſweryth for the dede. The thyrde accordyth with the fyrſt / but yf it ſo be that they ſhulde haue leſſe payne in hell / &amp; therfore yuell wyll that a man hath to wynne him goſtely ſtrenght / or to haue knowynge of very beleue / to do the pleſynge wyll of god / is the werſt yuell that cometh to man / and ſtraung lyth him with deſpeyre in the houre of his deth. But yet we ſhulde vnderſtande that the wyll of the godhede ſtandyth in thre thynges accordyng to the trynyte / and we muſt do our vtermoſt to confyrme our wyll to hys. The father of hys royall wyll commaundyth that ryghtwyſneſſe were done. The ſon of his wyte wyll / ſuffreth the leſſe yuyll / the more to be fled and abydeth ſynners long by vertue of his incarnacyon. The holy goſte af his charitable wyl forbedith al vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clennes / than we be confourmed to do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers wyll and byddyng / and whan the wyſedome of our wyll is tourned to vertuous mercy bothe to our ſelfe and to other / than ſue we Chryſtes ſteppes / but whan the loue of our wyl ſpedythe in due ordre bothe in heuen and in erthe / as we haue ſayde afore / than dwellyth the holy goſte in our inwarde man / yf thys knot be truly knyt: in wyl of our ſoule / there is no entre for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll to trouble vs from vnyte. As ſaynt Ierom ſayth. The deuyll fyghteth not agayne vs with
<pb facs="tcp:8704:65"/>
open face / but with gyle: for he vſeth agayne vs our owne wyll / he takyth hym ſtrenghte of our owne conſent / &amp; weryeth vs with our owne ſwerde / he may neuer ouercome vs / but tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough our owne wyl / therfore for the deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / remedy agayne this deuyl is ſtudy in holy wryt. And to this entent ſpekyth the wyſeman Prouerb .vi. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes ben a lanterne / and the lawe is lyght / and the way of lyfe / &amp; a monycyon of lernyng / that it may kepe the from an yuell woman / and from the ſmothe tounge of a ſtraunger. Loke thyne herte co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyte not the fayreneſſe of her. Is it poſſible for a man to hyde fyre in hys ſhert and not brenne his clothes? or elles walke in the brennynge cooles / and not brenne the ſooles of his feete? So he that hathe entred in to hys neyghbours wyfe / ſhall not be clene whan he hathe leche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly touched her. For he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is an aduoulterer by the foule gredye deſyre of hys herte / ſhall leſe his ſoule / for he gatheryth to him vnclen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and ſhame / and hys ſclaunder ſhall not be done awaye / for the zele and wodeneſſe of the man ſhall not ſpare in the day of vengeaunce nor he ſhall not ſpare for prayours of any man / nor he ſhall take no gyftes for hys redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon. For ſayncte Ierome ſaythe. A gloton hathe hys herte on hys wombe / A wanton man on hys lechery / A couetous man on hys wynnynge / Any garde on his holdynge. And therfore ſayth Salomon. Prouerb .iiij. with all
<pb n="lxvi" facs="tcp:8704:65"/>
dylygence kepe thyne herte / for lyfe paſſyth from it. And ſaynt ſhewe ſayth. In all creatures that bene occupyed vnder heuen in mannes va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nytees / there is nothynge hyer than mannes herte / there is nothynge founde lyker to god / wherfore god ſekyth nothynge of the but thyne herte. Agaynſte this commaundement the fende with his cautylles moueth dyſcorde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hertes of them that bene wedded / tyll the deſyre haue departyd the one from the other. Than the man fayneth a cauſe to go from the woman / and in thys they ben accurſed / as the wyſeman ſaythe Prouerb .xviij. he ſekyth occaſyons that wol go awaye from his frendes / at all tymes he ſhalbe acurſed and worthy rebuke. Neuertheles a fole wyll not receyue the wordes of techynge / but yf thou ſay to hym ſuch thynges as his hert deſyreth / and therfore he rennythe forthe in wodnes of his herte for to procure a diuorce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene hym and his wyfe / he comyth anone to the churche that is cleped lawles / not for the churche but for the offycers / for they ben law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. Anone he chuſythe hym a notarye / and payeth hym hys wages to make hym an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of hys forged leſynges / than goyth he to the mayſters that ſytten on theyr ſeates with furred hoodes / and fonde heddes / and gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uethe them money greate plentye / and prayeth them to be his aduocates that thys dyuorce wer made / for he wylbe redy at the lawles day to brynge forth his twelue handes afore the iuge / 
<pb facs="tcp:8704:66"/>
ſyr Symont and make good with all the courte that he hath no ryght to the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for dedes done afore / than ſyr Simont ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth dome / to dyſſolue trewe wedlocke / and authoryſeth lechery to theſe bothe partyes for to lyue in horedome from that day forthwarde and ſendythe them forthe at the dores departed eche fro other. But lo what Chryſt ſayth. Mat xix. Marc. x. Luc. xvi. For matrymony a man ſhall leue father and mother / and he ſhall holde him to his wyfe / and they ſhalbe twayne in one fleſſhe that is for theyr dwellynge ſhalbe to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Alſo they bene not than twayne / but one fleſſhe that is by vertue of the ſacrament / wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that thynge that god hath ioyned / ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may not departe. I ſay forſothe to you that who ſo euer hath lefte his wyfe excepte for the cauſe of fornycacyon / and yf he wedde another he is a lecherour / and who that weddyth this woman that this man hathe lefte / he ledyth his lyfe in lechery / as longe tyme as he holdeth her / ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then that god ioyneth neuer but in lawefull ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how dare ye purſue this dyuorce in a lawles church? Saynt Paule ſayth to the Romayns in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeconde chapytre. whoſoeuer ſynneth without lawe ſhal periſſhe without the lawe. For &amp; they weren blynde and knewe not the lawe / they myght happely the eaſelyer be excuſyd: but now they ſayen they knowe the lawe / and done full hardely agaynſt the lawe / they haue not excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacyon. And therfore the wiſeman ſaith. An hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome remedy agaynſte thys ſynne of the herte.
<pb n="lxvii" facs="tcp:8704:66"/>
Eccli. xviii. Be thou tourned from thyne owne wyll and obey thou to goddes wyll / and than (ſayth Bernarde) thou ſhalt neuer come in hel / and therfore whyle thou arte hole and ſounde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wauer not aboute in thoughtes of dyuerſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours / from god and from vertue. Bryſe downe not only ſuch vnleful couetyſe / but alſo al ſuper flue &amp; vnſtable thoughtes / and ſuffre them not on any wiſe to growe to dede ne to cuſtome. And thys ſemeth to be the ſentence of the prophete where he ſayth. Pſal. 136. Blyſſed is that man that ſhall holde / and hyrt his youngelynges at the ſtone / as the werkes of man bene his yonge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges / or ſonnes or doughters / after the goſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſence / ſo tho thoughtes of the inwarde man bene hys yongelynges. Than he hyrtyth hys yongelynges at the ſtone of ryghtwyſnes / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he dyſtroyeth theyr ſoden crepynges / in thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of the lyfe of our lorde Ieſu Chriſte. For ſoth this is a ſpecyal remedy to with holde wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thoughtes / deſyres / and wylles that they flowe not to depely withinforth / neyther that they flee to fer without forth / and ſuch trauey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les thryuen tho y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god hath choſen: for they wyl not in any dyſeaſe be ouercome neyther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſente to theſe cautyles of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl / by which he enpry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoneth goddes ſeruauntes for they kepen theſe .x. foreſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / but ſaynt Hyllary ſayth. This propartye hath Chriſtes churche / whan that it is purſued / it floryſſheth / whan it is bryſed downe / it growyth: whan it is dyſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it profyteth / whan it is hurte / it ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myth
<pb facs="tcp:8704:67"/>
/ whan it is blamed / it ſhyneth / and then it ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth moſt ſtrongly whan it ſemyth in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes eye to be ouercommen. Thys churche is a trewe ſoule / as we haue ſayde afore / ſome that ben tendre &amp; feble for to ſuffre cryen with abachuc / and ſayen to god. Lorde howe longe ſhal I crye / and thou ſhalt not here me? Lorde tyll whan ſhall I call vpon the thus ſuffrynge ſtronge trybulacyon / and thou ſhalt not make me ſaufe? why haſte thou ſhewed me wyckednes and traueyle / and ſuffreſt thefte agaynſte me and vnryghtwyſneſſe? why beholdeſte thou theſe dyſpyſers / and arte ſtyll? the wycked man defoulynge him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> iuſter than he? Saynte Ierome ſaythe in hys prologe / that theſe bene the wordes of mannes impacyence / and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyth an enſample of a ſycke man ſwellynge in the feuers and aſkynge colde water ſayenge to hys leche / I ſuffre wo / I am all to tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentyd / I am full nye dede / howe longe ſhall I crye (leche) and thou ſhalt not here me? The wytty and the moſte mercyfull leche anſweryth to him / I wote in what tyme it behouith me to gyue to the that thou aſkyſt / I haue no ruthe on the nowe / for thys mercy were cruelty and thyne owne wyl makyth agaynſt the. Alſo our lorde god knowynge the weyght and the meaſure of hys mercye / ſometyme he heryth not the cryer anone / that he maye proue and more ſtere hym to praye / and as examyned
<pb n="lxviii" facs="tcp:8704:67"/>
by the fyre / that he maye make hys ſeruaunte bothe iuſter / and purer / to receyue grace / and mede. ☞: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: ☜</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>¶What is the fendes church with her propertyes. The .xiii. chapytre.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O ſpeke of the thyrde churhe enpropryed to the deuyll the whiche is the nombre of them that bene encombryd to ſerue hym after hys tyſynge agaynſt goddes heſtes. Fyrſte we ſhall take our grounde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophete Pſalmo. 28. I haue hated y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of malyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Theſe bene they that ſtrayen away after theyr owne deſyers / walkynge in the waye that ledyth them to hell / neyther they wylbe gouerned by law ne by grace / neyther they wyl for drede ne loue ceſſe and go from ſynne / by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe thys worlde is full of luſtes and profer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryth hys louers a ioye ſone paſſynge / but they that traueylen after blyſſe here they ſuffren payne / therfore fooles withouten nombre ioyen with thys worlde / as Chryſte ſaythe in hys goſpell. Mathewe. 7. Entre ye by the ſtrayte gate / for large is the gate and brode is the waye that ledythe to dampnacyon / and many entren therin. But O lorde howe paynfull is
<pb facs="tcp:8704:68"/>
the gate / and ſtreyt is the way / that ledyth to lyfe / and fewe theyr bene that fynden it: For ſaynt Iohan ſayth. All the worlde / that is / all tho me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and women that ben ouercome with this worlde / ben ſet in malyce / that is brennyng in the fyre of foule couetyſe / for all thyng that is in this worlde / eyther it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> couetyſe of eyen / other elles it is the couetyſe of the fleſſhe / or elles it is the pryde of thys lyfe / and therfore thys churche is grounded vpon the deuyl in the grauel of falſe couetyſe. As Paule ſayth. The roote of all euylles is couetyſe / the which ſome deſyrynge haue erryd from trewe byleue / and haue ioyned them ſelfe to many ſorowes / the rerynge vp of this church is in glotony / and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery as the wyſeman ſayth reherſyng the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of them that ſhalbe dampned. Go we (ſaye the fendes lymmes) fyll vs with precyous wyne and oyntementes / and ſuffre we not the flowre of our fayre bewty to paſſe awaye from vs / crowne we vs: with roſys of iolyte or that they walken away / there may be no medowe but yf our lechery paſſe therby / none of vs may be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles / of our lechery / euery where leue we to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyns of our gladneſſe. The helynge of thys churche / is pryde and hyenes of life / as the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phete ſayth. Pſal. 36. I haue ſeen the vnpety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous / &amp; the wycked man enhaunſed &amp; vp lyfted as the cedres trees of Lyban / and they bene the hyeſt trees of the worlde / but as ſmoke ryſeth ſodynly / and ſone vanyſſheth to nought ſo they proude ben prayſed for a tyme / and than they
<pb n="lxix" facs="tcp:8704:68"/>
fallen away / and we weten not wher they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come / of the buſynes and occupacion that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of this church vſen / ſpekyth the prophete. Nyght &amp; day wyckedneſſe ſhal compaſſe aboute thys churche vpon theyr walles / and trauayle in myddes of it / and vnryghtwyſnes &amp; Okyr. Iuglynge / and Trechery / hath not ſtynted in the wayes of her. Of thys church with his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of buyldyng ſpekyth Chriſte in his goſpell. Math. 7. Luc. 6. who that heryth my wordes and dothe them not / is lyke a folyſh man that hath buylde his houſe vpon the grauell of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe and myſbeleue / and rayne of glotony and lechery came downe on this churche / and ferly thys forſayd ſynnes fallen in to this church and dryuen it downe / and the fall of her was great: for ſhe fell from grace and glory to payne &amp; miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chefe without ende / as ſaynt Auſten ſayth. For ſoth that is not the body of the lorde / that ſhall not be with him withouten ende / for ypocrytes ben not ſayde to be with hym though they bene ſeen to be in his church. Certes the deuyl is hed of all wycked / whiche ben on ſome maner / hys body / to go with them in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tourment of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge fyre / for whan they token baptyſme they hyghten fayth &amp; trouth to kepe goddes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes / as the ꝓphete ſaythe ſpekynge in the parſon of the generall churche Pſal. 118. Lorde I haue ſworne and ordeyned to kepe thy commaundementes / and vpon this couenaunt Chriſte toke him to his mariage / with the ryng of ſtedfaſt fayth he ſacred the holy ſpouſayle / 
<pb facs="tcp:8704:69"/>
but nowe they leue this chaſt loue our lord Ih<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Chryſte / in brekynge of this couenaunt / and haue choſen an hore mayſter the fende that is a ſpouſe breker and lyggeth in auoutre with her like ſpoyles. For ſaint Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſoſtome ſaith. Forſothe euery ſoule it is Chryſtes ſpouſe / or elles it is an aduoultereſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl for Chriſt and the deuyll may in nowiſe reſt to geder in the bed of mannes ſoule / for they ben ſo contrary that what ſo euer the one byddyth / that the other forbyddeth. Chriſt ſekyth ſaluacion / the fende dampnacyon / Chriſte loueth vertue / the fende loueth ſynne / Chriſt gatheryth to geder / and the fende ſcateryth abrode. And Paule ſaith ii. Corinth. what pertycypacion is ther of ryght wyſnes with wyckednes? what felowſhyp is there of lyght with darkenes? what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munyon is there of Chriſt with bely al? or what parte is ther of a faithful ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: with an vnfaythful ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? or what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple of idoles with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of god? Certes none / for eche of theſe agayne ſayen other after there owne wyrchyng. Nowe ſhall we tell what they ben that dwellen with the fende for to ſerue him in hys church that is the temple of idoles. waryours / curſers / chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders / ſclaunders / and blaſphemers / ther bene vylayne ſpekers / lyars / gloſers / backbyters / mottrars / ſwerars / and forſwerars / there ben alſo mychers / robbers / extorcyoners / tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / and oppreſſers / there ben vntrwe tyllers / vnfaythfull ſeruauntes / recheleſſe hyred men / rebell dyſcyples / and vnprofytable labourer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> /
<pb n="lxx" facs="tcp:8704:69"/>
there bene lecherours / fornycatours / aduoulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers / inceſtours / that is / defoulers of theyr owne kynne / and vnclene men and women that ben within the ordre of perfeccion there ben ypo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crites / ſodomytes / ſacrylegers / &amp; ſellers of the holy ſacramentes / there ben al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayen ſeruen or geuen gyftes for churche or ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all offyce / or benyfyce / all falſe poſſeſſyoners / all myghty wylful mendynners and al ſtourdy maynteners. There ben all tho men that boſen ther breſtes / pynchen theyr belyes partyn ther hoſys: crako<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyn there ſhoys: &amp; al diſguyſers of theyr garna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. There ben tho that ſterchen or poppen theyr faces / that brydelen ther hedes with gyg halters y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſetten aboue honykombes with moche other atyrynge / to make them ſelfe ſale kene to ſynne / and ſetten abrode there pappes to catche men with theyr lymes yardes. There ben falſe lawe makers / goddes lawe haters / offynders of cuſtomes / diſtroyers of vertue / and auctours of ſyn / in this churche alſo bene mawmotres / heretykes / idolatrers / ſortylegers enchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tours arriolers / charmours &amp; rerers of the deuyl / &amp; al tho y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> trowen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> helpe may come of vſynge godes worde / that we clepyn writtes only hangyd or borne on ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ben medycynable to body or ſoule ſo honged or ſo borne / there ben mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des / chapmen / vytellers: vynteners tauer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers / byers: ſellers / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vſen dyſceyte: in weyght / nombre / or meaſure / there bene in this church vſurers / okerers: iuryours / queſt mongers / and all falſe wytnes berers there ben
<pb facs="tcp:8704:70"/>
pleters / lawyers / ſequeſters / commyſſaryes / offycyalles / dens / ſumners / and all that ſellen trouth or ſynne to make money / theyr ben alſo audytours / receyuours / treaſurers and proc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours / iudges / and all that excepten parſon for a cauſe impartynent. Thys churche whan it is beten / it waxeth harder / whan it is blamyd / it waxeth the duller / whan it is taught / it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lewder / whan it is done well to / it is the ſhrew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der / and than it fallyth downe / and cometh to nought / whan it ſemeth in mannes eye moſte ſtronge to ſtande ſaynt Auſten ſaythe. Chryſtes church purſueth yuell lyuers in charyte by way of amendement. But the fendes churche pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth the church of Chryſte in malyce / by way of ſclaunder and ſleynge / and thys cayme that falſe enuyous man ſlewe his brother Abell that blyſſed and ſymple innocent man as the fyfty expoſitours ſayen in a prologe on this Pſalme. <hi>Quid gloriaris in malicia.</hi> That Cayme was the begynnynge of Babylon and Antechryſte ſhalbe the ende / and Abell was the begynnynge of Ieruſalem / and Chryſte ſhalbe the ender. Forſoth Iſmael purſued Iſaac but not ſo Iſaac Iſmaell / Eſau purſued Iacob / but not ſo blyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Iacob curſed Eſau / for by counſell of hys moder he fled in to Meſopony from the wrathe of hys brother / tyll that it was ſwaged. Thus our moder holye churche counſeyleth her chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to fle from the malyce of the fendes church tyll that it be ſlaked. Math. 10. Forſoth yf the fendes churche ſhall purſue you in thys cytee / 
<pb n="lxxi" facs="tcp:8704:70"/>
flee ye tyll another / but thys muſt be done by dyſcrecyon for hurtynge of our brothers conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyens. Chryſte purſued not the Iewes but the Iewes Ieſu Chryſte / hethen men ſlewe the apoſtelles but not the apoſtelles hethen men / ſe nowe frowardnes of thys worlde that hathe bene from the begynnynge. whan Iſaye the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prophete prophecyed and preched vnto the people / they wolde not here is wordes ne ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fren hym on lyue / but the people that ryſen af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hys dethe radde hys bokes and ſayden / yf we hadden lyued in hys dayes / he ſhulde not haue bene dede / and yet they ſlewen Ieremye that with the ſpyryte of god tolde thynges to come / and taught them very trouth / his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours token hys bokes and radde them in there temples / and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eyled hym for an holye man / but they ſlewen Ezechyel and other mo / than the Iewes maden fayre the tombes of theſe prophetes / as were ſcrybes and pharyſes and ſayd in ypocryſy / yf they had ben in their dayes they ſhulde not haue ben ſlayne / but they gaue the counſell that Chriſt ſhulde be deed / the hed of all ſayntes with moſt <abbr>dyſpytyous</abbr> deth. The fendes churche in theſe dayes / prayſen aboue the clowdes Chryſte and his holy ſayntes with wordes and with ſygnes / but they purſuen to the deth the louers of hys lawe. And thus ſayth Chryſte in his goſpell. Ryght as ye done nowe / ſo dyd your fathers to the prophetes in theyr dayes. And therfore wo to you hell houndes for Chryſte ſayth / in thys worlde ye ben ryche
<pb facs="tcp:8704:71"/>
fatte fed laughynge in purſuynge of eche other / wepe ye and make ye ſorowe for your payne is moche in hell. O theſe ſhall haue a dredefull day whan they be arrayned at the barre of iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemente whan Chryſte ſhall rere vp hys croſſe the baner of hys paſſyon. Of thys day ſpekyth the prophete Sophonias. The great day of the lorde is nygh / and faſt beſyde / and hyeth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde wounders faſte / it ſhall not longe tary / in that day ſhalbe troubled he that is ſtrong and myghty / for the voyce of the lorde is bytterful to the dampned. That day is a day of wrath / a day of trybulacion. That day is a day of hungre and ire / of extremyte and wretchydnes That day is a daye of darkenes and of thycke ſmoke. That is the day of the trumpe / and of hydeous noyſe / for than they ſhall ſe theyr iudge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue them ſtyrred to wrathe / than ſhall they ſe hell open bynethe them / and aungelles on the ryghtſyde haſtynge them to hell / ſayntes approuynge goddes dome / and all the worlde accuſynge / and theyr owne conſcyens as opyn as a boke / in the whiche they ſhall rede theyr owne dampnacyon. Theſe wretches behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge the greate glory of them that they dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpyſed in thys worlde / than ſhall they ſaye theſe wordes. Theſe bene they whome we ſome tyme had in ſcorne / and in hate and deriſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / we wytles dampned hell houndes bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd that theyr lyfe had bene woodnes / and madnes / and ſuppoſyd that theyr ende had ben without worſhip / howe nowe they ben counted
<pb n="lxxii" facs="tcp:8704:71"/>
among the ſonnes of god / and they taken theyr lotte amonge his ſayntes / therfore we haue er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the way of trouthe and the lyght of ryghtwyſeneſſe lyghted not to vs / we bene wery of the waye of wyckednes and dampnacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / what profyte hathe our pryde done to vs? or great auaunte or boſt of rycheſſe / what hath it gyuen to vs? all tho thynges bene paſſed from vs as a ſhadowe. Than the iudge ſhall ſaye vnto them with a ſterne chere. Go ye awaye from me ye curſed lymmes / into the fyre of hell euerlaſtynge / that is ordeyned to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll and hys aungelles. Than may the ſoule ſaye to the bodye theſe wordes. Come on thou curſed careyne / come and go with me / I am compelled to come agayne to the / that we may go to geder eyther to others ſhame / to take our ioyes as we haue deſeruyd / payne for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. That thynge that we loued / nowe it is gone from vs / and all that we hated is come vpon vs / nowe is ioye tourned into ſorowe / and our myrthe into wepynge / nowe is our laughter tourned into mournynge / and all our game into weylynge / nothynge abydeth to vs / but fyre hote brennynge / water colde chyllynge / wormes and edders / toodes and ſnakes / euer gnawyng / euer dyenge and neuer dede / darkenes palpable (that is ſo thycke / that it may be felte) wantyng the ſyght of all comeforte / ſeynge al thyng that may dyſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte / fyre intollerable / drede vntellable / qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fendes felowſhip alway diſcorde wont
<pb facs="tcp:8704:72"/>
any frendſhyp / and full deſpeyre of any ende / neuertheleſſe / aſſay we in this lyfe / yf we may leue thys fendes churche / and brynge our ſelfe bothe bodye and ſoule into the churche of Ieſu Chryſt / whyle grace and mercy may be graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted / aſke we of hym / that offryd hym ſelfe vpon a croſſe with a wylfull chere to ſaue vs all when we were loſte / for thus it is wryten of the wordes of god / that he ſpekyth to a ſynne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full ſoule. Turne the agayne / turne the agayne: thou ſynnefull ſoule: turne the agayne / tourne agayne that we may beholde the / forſothe god knowyth thy myſgouernaunce / and wyll not forſake the / yf thou wylt turne agayne / as he ſayth by the prophete Ieremye / forſothe thou haſte do fornycacyon with many louers / neuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theles tourne thou to me ſaythe the lorde / and I ſhall receyue the / and take the to grace. Vpon this ſayth ſaynt Gregory. In thys god ſhowith howe moche he louyth vs / for whan we forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken hym / he forſakyth not vs. As ſaynt Auſten ſayth. O man myſtruſte thou not of the mercy of god / for more is his mercy / than thy wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chednes. And thus ſaythe kynge Dauyd to Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. whan Abner had ſende meſſengers to kynge Dauyd / to entreate hym of fryndſhyp / kynge Dauyd anſwered to the meſſangers / as ſpoken vnto Abner / I wyll gladly make frendſhype with the / but this one thyng I tell the forſoth thou ſhalt not ſe my face / tyll thou ſhalt brynge with the Michol / and ſo commyng thou ſhalt ſe
<pb n="lxxiii" facs="tcp:8704:72"/>
me / this ſayenge is thus ſhortely to mene / ye that woll haue kynge Dauyd / amercyful lorde to you / ye muſte brynge with you this woman Mychol / yf ye woll ſe hys gracyous face / for Dauyd loued moche thys woman as the ſtory tellethe. Dauyd the kynge in this place berith the fygure of Ieſu Chriſt. And Mychol is to ſay whan it is declared the water of all / than is this thus to mene / ye that deſyren in all your herte to fynde and haue the mercy of god / and ſe his gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyous face in blyſſe / ye muſt haue water of very penaunce from your herte with ful contrycyon of wyll neuer to tourne to ſyn / &amp; yf that ye wol be true &amp; no more breke this coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt: god wol not that ye be dede / but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ye haue euerlaſtyng lyfe. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶ Here endyth the Lanterne of lyght.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:8704:73"/>
            <head>Tabula. ¶Here begynneth the table of this preſent boke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>¶ Fyrſt a prologe or a preface.</label> Ca. i. Fo. ii.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Item a peticion.</label> Ca. ii. Fo. iij.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>what Antechryſte is in generall with .vi. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycyons.</label> Ca. iii. Fo. iiij.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>what Antechryſte is in ſpecyall with .iii. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertyes.</label> Ca. iiij. Fo. viij.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>what Antechryſte is in ſpecyall with .v. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycions.</label> Ca. v. Fo. ix.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church only apꝓpryed to god is.</label> Ca. vi. Folio .xii.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>what is the materyal church.</label> Ca. vij. Fo. xx.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of good and yll commynge to thys materyall churche.</label> Ca. viii. Fo. xxiiij.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of dyſcrecyon to knowe good from yll.</label> Ca. ix. Fo. xxvij.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Howe the goodes of the fyrſt and ſeconde church accorde.</label> Ca. x. Fo. xl.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of ioye in trybulacyon.</label> Ca. xi. fo. xli.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of the fendes cautelles by whiche he purſueth by his members the kepers of goddes heſtes.</label> Ca. xij Fo. xliij.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>what is the fendes church with her propertyes.</label> Ca. xiij. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> lxviii.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>¶ Here endyth the table of this preſent boke. <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:8704:73"/>
            <p>¶: Imprynted at London in Fleteſtrete / by me Robert Redman / dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge at the ſygne of the George / nexte to Saynt Dunſtones church. <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>town scene</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8704:74"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8704:74"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
